<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE concept PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN" "http://docs.oasis-open.org/dita/v1.1/OS/dtd/concept.dtd">
<concept id="gemfire_properties">
	<title>gemfire.properties and gfsecurity.properties (<keyword keyref="product_name"/>
		Properties)</title>
	<shortdesc id="shortdesc_p1g_rbp_rr">You use the <codeph>gemfire.properties</codeph> settings to
		join a distributed system and configure system member behavior. Distributed system members
		include applications, the cache server, the locator, and other <keyword
			keyref="product_name"/> processes. </shortdesc>
	<conbody>
		<p id="p_vtw_bcp_rr">You can place any security-related (properties that begin with
				<codeph>security-*</codeph>) configuration properties in
				<codeph>gemfire.properties</codeph> into a separate
				<codeph>gfsecurity.properties</codeph> file. Placing these configuration settings in
			a separate file allows you to restrict access to security configuration data. This way,
			you can still allow read or write access for your <codeph>gemfire.properties</codeph>
			file. </p>
		<p id="p_w4b_ccp_rr">You can also define provider-specific properties ("ssl" properties) in
				<codeph>gfsecurity.properties</codeph> instead of defining them at the command-line
			or in your environment.</p>
		<p id="p_lgg_ccp_rr">You can specify non-ASCII text in your properties files by using
			Unicode escape sequences. See <xref
				href="non-ascii_strings_in_config_files.xml"
				type="concept" format="dita" scope="local"/> for more details. </p>
		<note>Unless otherwise indicated, these settings only affect activities within this distributed
			system - not activities between clients and servers or between a gateway sender and
			gateway receiver in a multi-site installation. </note>
		<table id="table_4F6DA593C76A447F851B5FE382C169DE">
			<tgroup cols="3">
				<colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="1.02*"/>
				<colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="3.12*"/>
				<colspec colname="3" colnum="3" colwidth="1*"/>
				<thead>
					<row>
						<entry>Setting </entry>
						<entry>Definition </entry>
						<entry>Default </entry>
					</row>
				</thead>
				<tbody>
					<row>
						<entry id="entry_gnr_scp_rr">ack-severe-alert-threshold </entry>
						<entry id="entry_irv_scp_rr">Number of seconds the distributed system will
							wait after the <codeph>ack-wait-threshold</codeph> for a message to be
							acknowledged before it issues an alert at severe level. A value of zero
							disables this feature. </entry>
						<entry id="entry_xsz_scp_rr">0 </entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry id="entry_wbd_tcp_rr">ack-wait-threshold </entry>
						<entry id="entry_glg_tcp_rr">Number of seconds a distributed message can
							wait for acknowledgment before it sends an alert to signal that
							something might be wrong with the system member that is unresponsive.
								<p>The waiter continues to wait. The alerts are logged in the system
								member’s log as warnings. </p>Valid values are in the range
							0...2147483647 </entry>
						<entry id="entry_d4k_tcp_rr">15 </entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry id="entry_sz4_tcp_rr">archive-disk-space-limit </entry>
						<entry id="entry_s5s_tcp_rr">Maximum size (in megabytes) of all inactive
							statistic archive files combined. If this limit is exceeded, inactive
							archive files are deleted, oldest first, until the total size is within
							the limit. If set to zero, disk space use is unlimited. </entry>
						<entry id="entry_n3x_tcp_rr">0 </entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry id="entry_rvb_5cp_rr">archive-file-size-limit </entry>
						<entry id="entry_lz2_5cp_rr">The maximum size (in megabytes) of a single
							statistic archive file. Once this limit is exceeded, a new statistic
							archive file is created, and the current archive file becomes inactive.
							If set to zero, file size is unlimited. </entry>
						<entry id="entry_bhj_5cp_rr">0 </entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry id="entry_m1v_n3p_rr">async-distribution-timeout </entry>
						<entry id="entry_bmg_ddp_rr">The number of milliseconds a process that is publishing to this
							process should attempt to distribute a cache operation before switching
							over to asynchronous messaging for this process. The switch to
							asynchronous messaging lasts until this process catches up, departs, or
							some specified limit is reached, such as async-queue-timeout or
							async-max-queue-size. <p>To enable asynchronous messaging, the value
								must be set above zero. Valid values are in the range 0...60000.
									<note>This setting controls only peer-to-peer communication and
									does not apply to client/server or multi-site communication.
								</note>
							</p>
						</entry>
						<entry id="entry_lyk_ddp_rr">0 </entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry id="entry_ibq_ddp_rr">async-max-queue-size </entry>
						<entry id="entry_ex5_ddp_rr">Affects non-conflated asynchronous queues for members that
							publish to this member. This is the maximum size the queue can reach (in
							megabytes) before the publisher asks this member to leave the
							distributed system. <p>Valid values are in the range 0..1024. <note>This
									setting controls only peer-to-peer communication and does not
									apply to client/server or multi-site communication. </note>
							</p>
						</entry>
						<entry id="entry_kbz_ddp_rr">8 </entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry id="entry_gb5_fdp_rr">async-queue-timeout </entry>
						<entry id="entry_cj3_fdp_rr">Affects asynchronous queues for members that publish to this
							member. This is the maximum milliseconds the publisher should wait with
							no distribution to this member before it asks this member to leave the
							distributed system. Used for handling slow receivers. <note>This setting
								controls only peer-to-peer communication and does not apply to
								client/server or multi-site communication. </note>
						</entry>
						<entry id="entry_z4l_fdp_rr">60000 </entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry id="bindaddress_Prop">bind-address </entry>
						<entry id="entry_bqb_gdp_rr">Relevant only for multi-homed hosts - machines
							with multiple network interface cards. Specifies the adapter card the
							cache binds to for peer-to-peer communication. Also specifies the
							default location for <keyword keyref="product_name"/> servers to listen
							on, which is used unless overridden by the
								<codeph>server-bind-address</codeph>. An empty string causes the
							member to listen on the default card for the machine. This is a
							machine-wide attribute used for system member and client/server
							communication. It has no effect on locator location, unless the locator
							is embedded in a member process. <p>Specify the IP address, not the
								hostname, because each network card may not have a unique hostname.
								An empty string (the default) causes the member to listen on the
								default card for the machine. </p>
						</entry>
						<entry id="entry_ncf_gdp_rr">
							<i>not set</i>
						</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry id="entry_oj2_ndp_rr">cache-xml-file </entry>
						<entry id="entry_h13_ndp_rr">Declarative initialization file for the
							member's cache. </entry>
						<entry id="entry_bhm_ndp_rr">cache.xml </entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry id="entry_bmq_ndp_rr">cluster-configuration-dir</entry>
						<entry id="entry_lst_ndp_rr">This property specifies the directory in which
							the cluster configuration related disk-store and artifacts are stored.
							This property is only applicable to dedicated locators that have
							"enable-cluster-configuration" set to true.</entry>
						<entry id="entry_t4z_ndp_rr">
							<i>not set</i>
						</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry id="entry_ztf_4dp_rr">cluster-ssl-ciphers </entry>
						<entry id="entry_jrj_4dp_rr">Used for SSL security. A space-separated list of the valid SSL
							ciphers for peer-to-peer connections in the cluster. A setting of 'any'
							uses any ciphers that are enabled by default in the configured JSSE
							provider. This attribute must be consistent across all members of the
							distributed system. <keyword keyref="product_name"/> applies this
							peer-to-peer connection property setting to client/server, JMX manager,
							WAN gateway and HTTP service connections unless the corresponding SSL
							property (<codeph>server-ssl-ciphers</codeph>,
								<codeph>jmx-manager-ssl-ciphers</codeph>,
								<codeph>gateway-ssl-ciphers</codeph>, or
								<codeph>http-service-ssl-ciphers</codeph>) is defined. See <xref
								href="../../managing/security/implementing_ssl.xml"/>.</entry>
						<entry id="entry_yzn_4dp_rr">any</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry id="entry_swr_4dp_rr">cluster-ssl-enabled </entry>
						<entry id="entry_wqv_4dp_rr">Used for SSL security. Boolean indicating whether to use SSL for
							peer-to-peer communications. A true setting requires the use of
							locators. This attribute must be consistent across all members of the
							distributed system. <keyword keyref="product_name"/> applies this
							peer-to-peer connection property setting to client/server, JMX manager,
							WAN gateway, and HTTP service connections unless the corresponding SSL
							property (<codeph>server-ssl-enabled</codeph>,
								<codeph>jmx-manager-ssl-enabled</codeph>,
								<codeph>gateway-ssl-enabled</codeph>, or
								<codeph>http-service-ssl-enabled</codeph>) is defined. See <xref
								href="../../managing/security/implementing_ssl.xml"/>.</entry>
						<entry id="entry_vmz_4dp_rr">false</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry id="entry_kkg_pdp_rr">cluster-ssl-keystore, gateway-ssl-keystore,
							http-service-ssl-keystore, jmx-manager-ssl-keystore,
							server-ssl-keystore</entry>
						<entry id="entry_m3k_pdp_rr">Properties that dentify the keystores to use for SSL
								connections.<codeph>cluster-ssl-keystore</codeph> defines the
							keystore for <keyword keyref="product_name"/> peer-to-peer connections.
							If you specify only <codeph>cluster-ssl-keystore</codeph>, then the same
							keystore is also used for client/server, JMX manager, WAN gateway and
							HTTP service connections. Specify the gateway, jmx-manager, server- or
							http-service- prefix with this property to use a different keystore for
							the respective SSL connection type. See <xref
								href="../../managing/security/implementing_ssl.xml"
								/>.<note>javax.net.ssl.keyStore is deprecated. Use
									<codeph>cluster-ssl-keystore</codeph> instead.</note></entry>
						<entry colname="3" id="entry_jbp_pdp_rr">
							<i>not set</i>
						</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry id="entry_czk_tdp_rr">cluster-ssl-keystore-password, gateway-ssl-keystore-password,
							http-service-ssl-keystore-password, jmx-manager-ssl-keystore-password,
							server-ssl-keystore-password</entry>
						<entry id="entry_sq4_tdp_rr">Properties that identify the passwords for the
							keystores used with SSL connections. See <xref
								href="../../managing/security/implementing_ssl.xml"
								/>.<note>javax.net.ssl.keyStorePassword is deprecated. Use
								cluster-ssl-keystore-password instead.</note></entry>
						<entry colname="3" id="entry_k4s_tdp_rr">
							<i>not set</i>
						</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry id="entry_c31_5dp_rr">cluster-ssl-keystore-type, gateway-ssl-keystore-type,
							http-service-ssl-keystore-type, jmx-manager-ssl-keystore-type,
							server-ssl-keystore-type</entry>
						<entry id="entry_n5d_5dp_rr">System properties that identify the types of
							keystores used with SSL connections. See <xref
								href="../../managing/security/implementing_ssl.xml"
								/>.<note>javax.net.ssl.keyStoreType is deprecated. Use
								cluster-ssl-keystore-type instead.</note></entry>
						<entry colname="3" id="entry_df3_5dp_rr">
							<i>not set</i>
						</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry id="entry_asj_22p_rr">cluster-ssl-protocols </entry>
						<entry id="entry_t5p_22p_rr">Used for SSL security. A space-separated list of the valid SSL
							protocols for peer-to-peer connections in the cluster. A setting of
							'any' uses any protocol that is enabled by default in the configured
							JSSE provider. <keyword keyref="product_name"/> applies this
							peer-to-peer connection property setting to client/server, JMX manager,
							WAN gateway and HTTP service connections unless the corresponding SSL
							property (<codeph>server-ssl-protocols</codeph>,
								<codeph>jmx-manager-ssl-protocols</codeph>,
								<codeph>gateway-ssl-protocols</codeph>, or
								<codeph>http-service-ssl-protocols</codeph>) is defined. See <xref
								href="../../managing/security/implementing_ssl.xml"/>.</entry>
						<entry id="entry_cb5_22p_rr">any </entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry id="entry_jby_22p_rr">cluster-ssl-require-authentication </entry>
						<entry id="entry_njb_f2p_rr">Used for SSL security. Boolean indicating whether to require
							authentication for member communication. <keyword keyref="product_name"
							/> applies this peer-to-peer connection property setting to
							client/server, JMX manager, WAN gateway and HTTP service connections
							unless the corresponding SSL property
								(<codeph>server-ssl-require-authentication</codeph>,
								<codeph>jmx-manager-ssl-require-authentication</codeph>,
								<codeph>gateway-ssl-require-authentication</codeph>, or
								<codeph>http-service-ssl-require-authentication</codeph>) is
							defined. See <xref href="../../managing/security/implementing_ssl.xml"
							/>.</entry>
						<entry id="entry_lff_f2p_rr">true </entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry id="entry_h14_f2p_rr">cluster-ssl-truststore, gateway-ssl-truststore,
							http-service-ssl-truststore, jmx-manager-ssl-truststore,
							server-ssl-truststore</entry>
						<entry id="entry_t3s_f2p_rr">Properties that identify the truststores to use for SSL
							connections. <codeph>cluster-ssl-truststore</codeph> defines the
							truststore for <keyword keyref="product_name"/> peer-to-peer
							connections. If you specify only
							<codeph>cluster-ssl-truststore</codeph>, then the same truststore is
							also used for client/server, JMX manager, WAN gateway and HTTP service
							connections. Specify the gateway-, jmx-manager, server-, or
							http-service- prefix with this property to use a different truststore
							for the respective SSL connection type. See <xref
								href="../../managing/security/implementing_ssl.xml"
								/>.<note>javax.net.ssl.trustStore is deprecated. Use
									<codeph>cluster-ssl-truststore</codeph> instead.</note></entry>
						<entry colname="3" id="entry_ikw_f2p_rr">
							<i>not set</i>
						</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry id="entry_tt1_g2p_rr">cluster-ssl-truststore-password,
							gateway-ssl-truststore-password, http-service-ssl-truststore-password,
							jmx-manager-ssl-truststore-password,
							server-ssl-truststore-password</entry>
						<entry id="entry_u32_g2p_rr">Properties that identifies the passwords for
							the truststores used with SSL connections. See <xref
								href="../../managing/security/implementing_ssl.xml"
							/>.</entry>
						<entry colname="3" id="entry_vqh_g2p_rr">
							<i>not set</i>
						</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry id="entry_w3l_g2p_rr">conflate-events </entry>
						<entry id="entry_qpq_g2p_rr">Used only by clients in a client/server
							installation. This is a client-side property that is passed to the
							server. Affects subscription queue conflation in this client's servers.
							Specifies whether to conflate (true setting), not conflate (false), or
							to use the server's conflation setting (server). </entry>
						<entry id="entry_fhv_g2p_rr">server </entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry id="entry_ezz_g2p_rr">conserve-sockets </entry>
						<entry id="entry_bjd_h2p_rr">Specifies whether sockets are shared by the system member’s
							threads. If true, threads share, and a minimum number of sockets are
							used to connect to the distributed system. If false, every application
							thread has its own sockets for distribution purposes. You can override
							this setting for individual threads inside your application. Where
							possible, it is better to set conserve-sockets to true and enable the
							use of specific extra sockets in the application code if needed. WAN
							deployments increase the messaging demands on a <keyword
								keyref="product_name"/> system. To avoid hangs related to WAN
							messaging, always set <codeph>conserve-sockets=false</codeph> for
								<keyword keyref="product_name"/> members that participate in a WAN
							deployment.</entry>
						<entry id="entry_dbh_h2p_rr">true</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry id="entry_w4l_h2p_rr">delta-propagation </entry>
						<entry id="entry_zbr_h2p_rr">Specifies whether to distribute the deltas for
							entry updates, instead of the full values, between clients and servers
							and between peers. </entry>
						<entry id="entry_knx_h2p_rr">true </entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry id="entry_tbh_32p_rr">deploy-working-dir </entry>
						<entry id="entry_vjl_32p_rr"> Working directory used when deploying JAR
							application files to distributed system members. This directory can be
							local and unique to the member or a shared resource. See <xref
								href="../../configuring/cluster_config/deploying_application_jars.xml"
								type="concept" format="dita" scope="local"/> for more information. </entry>
						<entry id="entry_tfp_32p_rr">. (current directory) </entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry id="entry_zc5_32p_rr">disable-auto-reconnect </entry>
						<entry id="entry_c2y_32p_rr">By default, a <keyword keyref="product_name"/>
							member (both locators and servers) will attempt to reconnect and
							reinitialize the cache after it has been forced out of the distributed
							system by a network partition event or has otherwise been shunned by
							other members. Use this property to turn off the autoreconnect behavior.
							See <xref
								href="../../managing/autoreconnect/member-reconnect.xml"
							/> for more details.</entry>
						<entry id="entry_syc_j2p_rr">false </entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry id="entry_e23_j2p_rr">disable-tcp</entry>
						<entry id="entry_fmn_j2p_rr">Boolean indicating whether to disable the use
							of TCP/IP sockets for inter-cache point-to-point messaging. If disabled,
							the cache uses datagram (UDP) sockets. </entry>
						<entry id="entry_amr_j2p_rr">false</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>distributed-system-id </entry>
						<entry>Identifier used to distinguish messages from different distributed
							systems. Set this to different values for different systems in a
							multi-site (WAN) configuration. This is required for Portable Data
							eXchange (PDX) data serialization. This setting must be the same for
							every member in the same distributed system and unique to the
							distributed system within the WAN installation. -1 means no setting.
							Valid values are integers in the range -1...255.</entry>
						<entry>-1</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry id="entry_k4v_j2p_rr">durable-client-id </entry>
						<entry id="entry_q3b_k2p_rr">Used only for clients in a client/server
							installation. If set, this indicates that the client is durable and
							identifies the client. The ID is used by servers to reestablish any
							messaging that was interrupted by client downtime. </entry>
						<entry id="entry_ohf_k2p_rr">
							<i>not set</i>
						</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry id="entry_hbl_k2p_rr">durable-client-timeout </entry>
						<entry id="entry_ixg_l2p_rr">Used only for clients in a client/server
							installation. Number of seconds this client can remain disconnected from
							its server and have the server continue to accumulate durable events for
							it. </entry>
						<entry id="entry_lsk_l2p_rr">300 </entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry id="entry_rs4_l2p_rr">enable-network-partition-detection </entry>
						<entry id="entry_wgs_l2p_rr">Boolean instructing the system to detect and
							handle splits in the distributed system, typically caused by a
							partitioning of the network (split brain) where the distributed system
							is running. We recommend setting this property to <codeph>true</codeph>.
							You must set this property to the same value across all your distributed
							system members. In addition, you must set this property to
								<codeph>true</codeph> if you are using persistent regions and
							configure your regions to use DISTRIBUTED_ACK or GLOBAL scope to avoid
							potential data conflicts. </entry>
						<entry id="entry_pkw_l2p_rr">false</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry id="entry_tl1_m2p_rr">enable-cluster-configuration</entry>
						<entry id="entry_hrd_m2p_rr">A value of "true" causes the creation of
							cluster configuration on dedicated locators. The cluster configuration
							service on dedicated locator(s) with this property set to "true" would
							serve the configuration to new members joining the distributed system
							and also save the configuration changes caused by the
								<codeph>gfsh</codeph> commands. This property is only applicable to
							dedicated locators..</entry>
						<entry id="entry_enh_m2p_rr">true</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry id="entry_ggg_p2p_rr">enable-time-statistics </entry>
						<entry id="entry_xqj_p2p_rr">Boolean instructing the system to track
							time-based statistics for the distributed system and caching. Disabled
							by default for performance reasons and not recommended for production
							environments. You must also configure
								<codeph>statistics-sampling-enabled</codeph> to true and specify a
								<codeph>statistics-archive-file</codeph>. </entry>
						<entry id="entry_jjn_p2p_rr">false </entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry id="entry_otq_s2p_rr">enforce-unique-host </entry>
						<entry id="entry_hx5_s2p_rr">Whether partitioned regions will put redundant
							copies of the same data in different members running on the same
							physical machine. By default, <keyword keyref="product_name"/> tries to
							put redundant copies on different machines, but it will put them on the
							same machine if no other machines are available. Setting this property
							to true prevents this and requires different machines for redundant
							copies. </entry>
						<entry id="entry_d1z_s2p_rr">false </entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>gateway-ssl-ciphers</entry>
						<entry>A space-separated list of the valid SSL ciphers for WAN gateway
							connections. A setting of 'any' uses any ciphers that are enabled by
							default in the configured JSSE provider. If this property is not set,
							then <keyword keyref="product_name"/> uses the value of
								<codeph>cluster-ssl-ciphers</codeph> to determine which SSL ciphers
							are used for WAN connections. See <xref
								href="../../managing/security/security_multisite.xml"/>.</entry>
						<entry>value of <codeph>ssl-ciphers</codeph></entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>gateway-ssl-enabled</entry>
						<entry>Enables or disables SSL for WAN gateway connections. If this property
							is not set, then <keyword keyref="product_name"/> uses the value of
								<codeph>cluster-ssl-enabled</codeph> to determine whether JMX
							connections use SSL. See <xref
								href="../../managing/security/security_multisite.xml"/>.</entry>
						<entry>value of <codeph>ssl-enabled</codeph></entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>gateway-ssl-protocols</entry>
						<entry>A space-separated list of the valid SSL protocols for WAN gateway
							connections. A setting of 'any' uses any protocol that is enabled by
							default in the configured JSSE provider. If this property is not set,
							then <keyword keyref="product_name"/> uses the value of
								<codeph>cluster-ssl-protocols</codeph> to determine which SSL
							protocols are used by WAN connections. See <xref
								href="../../managing/security/security_multisite.xml"/>.</entry>
						<entry>value of <codeph>ssl-protocols</codeph></entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>gateway-ssl-require-authentication</entry>
						<entry>Boolean indicating whether to require authentication for WAN gateway
							connections. If this property is not set, then <keyword
								keyref="product_name"/> uses the value of
								<codeph>cluster-ssl-require-authentication</codeph> to determine
							whether WAN connections require authentication. See <xref
								href="../../managing/security/security_multisite.xml"/>.</entry>
						<entry>value of <codeph>ssl-require-authentication</codeph></entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry colname="1" id="entry_crt_t2p_rr">groups </entry>
						<entry colname="2" id="entry_l4x_t2p_rr">Defines the list of groups that
							this member belongs to. Use commas to separate group names. Note that
							anything defined by the roles gemfire property will also be considered a
							group. See <xref
								href="../../configuring/cluster_config/using_member_groups.xml"
								type="concept" format="dita" scope="local"/> for more information. </entry>
						<entry colname="3" id="entry_gjq_52p_rr">
							<i>not set</i>
						</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry id="entry_dzt_52p_rr">http-service-bind-address</entry>
						<entry id="entry_ysx_52p_rr">If set, then the <keyword keyref="product_name"
							/> member binds the embedded HTTP service to the specified address. If
							this property is not set but the HTTP service is enabled using
								<codeph>http-service-port</codeph>, then <keyword
								keyref="product_name"/> binds the HTTP service to the member's local
							address. Used by the <keyword keyref="product_name"/> Pulse Web
							application and the developer REST API service.</entry>
						<entry id="entry_u4d_v2p_rr">
							<i>not set</i>
						</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry id="entry_frh_v2p_rr">http-service-port</entry>
						<entry id="entry_hjl_v2p_rr">If non-zero, then <keyword
								keyref="product_name"/> starts an embedded HTTP service that listens
							on this port. The HTTP service is used to host the <keyword
								keyref="product_name"/> Pulse Web application and the development
							REST API service. If you are hosting the Pulse web app on your own Web
							server and are not using the development REST API service, then disable
							this embedded HTTP service by setting this property to zero. Ignored if
								<codeph>jmx-manager</codeph> and <codeph>start-dev-rest-api</codeph>
							are both set to false. </entry>
						<entry id="entry_fsp_v2p_rr">7070</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry id="entry_yvt_v2p_rr">http-service-ssl-ciphers</entry>
						<entry id="entry_zxw_v2p_rr">A space separated list of the SSL cipher suites
							to enable. Those listed must be supported by the available
							providers.</entry>
						<entry id="entry_yg1_w2p_rr">
							<i>not set</i>
						</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry id="entry_ocl_w2p_rr">http-service-ssl-enabled</entry>
						<entry id="entry_k1n_y2p_rr">Specifies if the HTTP service is started with
							separate ssl configuration. If not specified, then the global property
							cluster-ssl-enabled (and its other related properties) are used to
							create server socket.</entry>
						<entry id="entry_d2r_y2p_rr">false</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry id="entry_xkv_y2p_rr">http-service-ssl-protocols</entry>
						<entry id="entry_q4z_y2p_rr">A space separated list of the SSL protocols to
							enable. Those listed must be supported by the available
							providers.</entry>
						<entry id="entry_oh2_z2p_rr">any</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry id="entry_osj_z2p_rr">http-service-ssl-require-authentication</entry>
						<entry id="entry_byn_z2p_rr">Boolean indicating whether to require
							authentication for HTTP service connections. If this property is not
							set, then <keyword keyref="product_name"/> uses the value of
								<codeph>cluster-ssl-require-authentication</codeph> to determine
							whether HTTP service connections require authentication.</entry>
						<entry id="entry_bqs_z2p_rr">false</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry colname="1" id="entry_tgy_z2p_rr">jmx-manager </entry>
						<entry colname="2" id="entry_a5b_1fp_rr">If true then this member is willing
							to be a JMX Manager. All the other JMX Manager properties will be used
							when it does become a manager. If this property is false then all other
								<codeph>jmx-manager-*</codeph> properties are ignored. </entry>
						<entry colname="3" id="entry_ysg_1fp_rr">false (except on locators) </entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry colname="1" id="entry_hdl_1fp_rr">jmx-manager-access-file </entry>
						<entry colname="2" id="entry_tqs_1fp_rr">By default the JMX Manager will
							allow full access to all mbeans by any client. If this property is set
							to the name of a file then it can restrict clients to only being able to
							read MBeans; they will not be able to modify MBeans. The access level
							can be configured differently in this file for each user name defined in
							the password file. For more information about the format of this file
							see Oracle's documentation of the
							com.sun.management.jmxremote.access.file system property. Ignored if
								<codeph>jmx-manager</codeph> is false or if
								<codeph>jmx-manager-port</codeph> is zero. </entry>
						<entry colname="3" id="entry_xrw_1fp_rr">
							<i>not set</i>
						</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry colname="1" id="entry_dc1_bfp_rr">jmx-manager-bind-address </entry>
						<entry colname="2" id="entry_e22_bfp_rr">By default the jmx-manager (when
							configured with a port) will listen on all the local host's addresses.
							You can use this property to configure what IP address or host name the
							JMX Manager will listen on for non-HTTP connections. Ignored if JMX
							Manager is false or <codeph>jmx-manager-port</codeph> is zero. </entry>
						<entry colname="3" id="entry_hs3_bfp_rr">
							<i>not set</i>
						</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry colname="1" id="entry_zpm_bfp_rr">jmx-manager-hostname-for-clients </entry>
						<entry colname="2" id="entry_nxs_bfp_rr">Lets you control what hostname will
							be given to clients that ask the locator for the location of a JMX
							Manager. By default the IP address that the jmx-manager reports is used.
							But for clients on a different network this property allows you to
							configure a different hostname that will be given to clients. Ignored if
								<codeph>jmx-manager</codeph> is false or
								<codeph>jmx-manager-port</codeph> is zero. </entry>
						<entry colname="3" id="entry_vtt_ffp_rr">
							<i>not set</i>
						</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry colname="1" id="entry_pzx_ffp_rr">jmx-manager-http-port</entry>
						<entry colname="2" id="entry_rrb_gfp_rr"><i>Deprecated.</i> Use
								<codeph>http-service-port</codeph> instead.</entry>
						<entry colname="3" id="entry_n13_gfp_rr">7070 </entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry colname="1" id="entry_el4_gfp_rr">jmx-manager-password-file</entry>
						<entry colname="2" id="entry_w4r_gfp_rr">By default the JMX Manager will
							allow clients without credentials to connect. If this property is set to
							the name of a file then only clients that connect with credentials that
							match an entry in this file will be allowed. Most JVMs require that the
							file is only readable by the owner. For more information about the
							format of this file see Oracle's documentation of the
							com.sun.management.jmxremote.password.file system property. Ignored if
								<codeph>jmx-manager</codeph> is false or if
								<codeph>jmx-manager-port</codeph> is zero. </entry>
						<entry colname="3" id="entry_a1v_gfp_rr">
							<i>not set</i>
						</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry colname="1" id="entry_rxy_gfp_rr">jmx-manager-port </entry>
						<entry colname="2" id="entry_hcc_hfp_rr">The port this JMX Manager will
							listen to for client connections. If this property is set to zero then
								<keyword keyref="product_name"/> will not allow remote client
							connections but you can alternatively use the standard system properties
							supported by the JVM for configuring access from remote JMX clients.
							Ignored if <codeph>jmx-manager</codeph> is false. </entry>
						<entry colname="3" id="entry_c1g_hfp_rr">1099 </entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry colname="1" id="entry_b1m_hfp_rr">jmx-manager-ssl-enabled</entry>
						<entry colname="2" id="entry_xqp_hfp_rr">Enables or disables SSL for
							connections to the JMX Manager. If true and
								<codeph>jmx-manager-port</codeph> is not zero, then the JMX Manager
							will only accept SSL connections. If this property is not set, then
								<keyword keyref="product_name"/> uses the value of
								<codeph>cluster-ssl-enabled</codeph> to determine whether JMX
							connections should use SSL. See <xref
								href="../../managing/security/implementing_ssl.xml"
							/>.</entry>
						<entry colname="3" id="entry_ift_hfp_rr">value of
								<codeph>cluster-ssl-enabled</codeph></entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry colname="1" id="entry_pxw_hfp_rr">jmx-manager-ssl-ciphers</entry>
						<entry colname="2" id="entry_wk1_3fp_rr">A space-separated list of the valid
							SSL ciphers for JMX manager connections. A setting of 'any' uses any
							ciphers that are enabled by default in the configured JSSE provider. If
							this property is not set, then <keyword keyref="product_name"/> uses the
							value of <codeph>cluster-ssl-ciphers</codeph> to determine which SSL
							ciphers are used for JMX connections. See <xref
								href="../../managing/security/implementing_ssl.xml"
							/>.</entry>
						<entry colname="3" id="entry_qzd_3fp_rr">value of
								<codeph>cluster-ssl-ciphers</codeph></entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry colname="1" id="entry_srm_3fp_rr">jmx-manager-ssl-protocols</entry>
						<entry colname="2" id="entry_wfq_3fp_rr">A space-separated list of the valid
							SSL protocols for JMX manager connections. A setting of 'any' uses any
							protocol that is enabled by default in the configured JSSE provider. If
							this property is not set, then <keyword keyref="product_name"/> uses the
							value of <codeph>cluster-ssl-protocols</codeph> to determine which SSL
							protocols are used for JMX connections. See <xref
								href="../../managing/security/implementing_ssl.xml"
							/>.</entry>
						<entry colname="3" id="entry_bxt_3fp_rr">value of
								<codeph>cluster-ssl-ciphers</codeph></entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry colname="1" id="entry_jpb_jfp_rr"
							>jmx-manager-ssl-require-authentication</entry>
						<entry colname="2" id="entry_ffg_jfp_rr">Boolean indicating whether to
							require authentication for JMX Manager connections. If this property is
							not set, then <keyword keyref="product_name"/> uses the value of
								<codeph>cluster-ssl-require-authentication</codeph> to determine
							whether JMX connections require authentication. See <xref
								href="../../managing/security/implementing_ssl.xml"
							/>.</entry>
						<entry colname="3" id="entry_bfk_jfp_rr">value of
								<codeph>cluster-ssl-require-authentication</codeph></entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry colname="1" id="entry_abp_jfp_rr">jmx-manager-start </entry>
						<entry colname="2" id="entry_ygs_jfp_rr">If true then this member will start
							a jmx manager when it creates a cache. Management tools like gfsh can be
							configured to connect to the jmx-manager. In most cases you should not
							set this because a jmx manager will automatically be started when needed
							on a member that sets "jmx-manager" to true. Ignored if jmx-manager is
							false. </entry>
						<entry colname="3" id="entry_vsw_jfp_rr">false </entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry colname="1" id="entry_w3b_kfp_rr">jmx-manager-update-rate </entry>
						<entry colname="2" id="entry_zff_kfp_rr">The rate, in milliseconds, at which
							this member will push updates to any JMX Managers. Currently this value
							should be greater than or equal to the statistic-sample-rate. Setting
							this value too high will cause stale values to be seen by gfsh and
								<keyword keyref="product_name"/> Pulse. </entry>
						<entry colname="3" id="entry_pkj_kfp_rr">2000 </entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry colname="1" id="entry_j5n_kfp_rr"
							>load-cluster-configuration-from-dir</entry>
						<entry colname="2" id="entry_pvq_kfp_rr">Setting this property to "true"
							causes loading of cluster configuration from "cluster_config" directory
							in the locator. This property is only applicable to dedicated locators
							that have "enable-cluster-configuration" set to true.</entry>
						<entry colname="3" id="entry_o2v_kfp_rr">false</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry colname="1" id="entry_sbz_kfp_rr">locator-wait-time</entry>
						<entry colname="2" id="entry_d4c_lfp_rr">The number of seconds that a member
							should wait for a locator to start if a locator is not available when
							attempting to join the distributed system. Use this setting when you are
							starting locators and peers all at once. This timeout allows peers to
							wait for the locators to finish starting up before attempting to join
							the distributed system.</entry>
						<entry colname="3" id="entry_dhh_lfp_rr">0</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry id="entry_aql_lfp_rr">locators</entry>
						<entry id="entry_hjp_lfp_rr">
							<p>The list of locators used by system members. The list must be
								configured consistently for every member of the distributed system.
								If the list is empty, locators are not used. </p>
							<p>For each locator, provide a host name and/or address (separated by
								‘@’, if you use both), followed by a port number in brackets.
								Examples: <codeblock>locators=address1[port1],address2[port2] </codeblock>
								<codeblock>locators=hostName1@address1[port1],hostName2@address2[port2] </codeblock>
								<codeblock>locators=hostName1[port1],hostName2[port2]</codeblock>
							</p>
							<p>
								<note>On multi-homed hosts, this last notation will use the default
									address. If you use bind addresses for your locators, explicitly
									specify the addresses in the locators list—do not use just the
									hostname. </note>
							</p>
							<p>If you have values specified for the <codeph>locators</codeph>
								property, the <codeph>mcast-port</codeph> property defaults to
								0.</p>
							<p>
								<note>If you specify invalid DNS hostnames in this property, any
									locators or servers started with <codeph>gfsh</codeph> will not
									produce log files. Make sure you provide valid DNS hostnames
									before starting the locator or server with
									<codeph>gfsh</codeph>.</note>
							</p>
						</entry>
						<entry id="entry_wzx_lfp_rr">
							<i>not set</i>
						</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>lock-memory </entry>
						<entry>When <codeph>true</codeph>, locks heap and off-heap memory into RAM to prevent
							the operating system from paging the memory out to disk.</entry>
						<entry>false </entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry id="entry_tzl_mfp_rr">log-disk-space-limit </entry>
						<entry id="entry_t4z_mfp_rr">Maximum size in megabytes of all inactive log
							files combined. If this limit is exceeded, inactive log files are
							deleted, oldest first, until the total size is within the limit. If set
							to zero, disk space use is unlimited. </entry>
						<entry id="entry_awc_nfp_rr">0 </entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry id="entry_umg_nfp_rr">log-file</entry>
						<entry id="entry_ilj_nfp_rr">File to which a running system member writes
							log messages. If set to null, the default is used. <p>Each member type
								has its own default output: </p>
								<ul
									id="ul_B35299AB5D73458C8AF9080BB82DBB21">
									<li id="li_69DFF21E90444BA0B7DA201A355CA2AA">application:
										standard out </li>
									<li id="li_C9BC1E16C5DA48E5811607D0A4BC330A">locator:
											<codeph>&lt;locator_name>.log</codeph>
									</li>
									<li id="li_856ACFDBC4F1480A870D5A354681B495">server:
											<codeph>&lt;server_name>.log</codeph>
									</li>
								</ul>
						</entry>
						<entry id="entry_nvz_nfp_rr">null </entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry id="entry_mx2_4fp_rr">log-file-size-limit </entry>
						<entry id="entry_klp_4fp_rr">Maximum size in megabytes of a log file before
							it is closed and logging rolls on to a new (child) log file. If set to
							0, log rolling is disabled. </entry>
						<entry id="entry_lfw_4fp_rr">0 </entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry id="entry_zn1_pfp_rr">log-level </entry>
						<entry id="entry_ywd_pfp_rr">Level of detail of the messages written to the
							system member’s log. Setting log-level to one of the ordered levels
							causes all messages of that level and greater severity to be printed.
								<p>Valid values from lowest to highest are fine, config, info,
								warning, error, severe, and none. </p>
						</entry>
						<entry id="entry_uwh_pfp_rr">config </entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry id="entry_zz5_qfp_rr">max-wait-time-reconnect </entry>
						<entry id="entry_m4x_rfp_rr">Maximum number of milliseconds to wait for the
							distributed system to reconnect on each reconnect attempt. </entry>
						<entry id="entry_nhb_sfp_rr">60000 </entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry id="entry_ls2_sfp_rr">mcast-address </entry>
						<entry id="entry_lsl_tfp_rr">Address used to discover other members of the distributed system.
							Only used if mcast-port is non-zero. This attribute must be consistent
							across the distributed system. Select different multicast addresses and
							different ports for different distributed systems. Do not just use
							different addresses. Some operating systems may not keep communication
							separate between systems that use unique addresses but the same port
							number. <p>This default multicast address was assigned by IANA (<xref
									href="http://www.iana.org/assignments/multicast-addresses"
									format="html" scope="external"
									>http://www.iana.org/assignments/multicast-addresses</xref>).
								Consult the IANA chart when selecting another multicast address to
								use with <keyword keyref="product_name"/>. </p>
							<note>This setting controls only peer-to-peer communication and does not
								apply to client/server or multi-site communication. If multicast is
								enabled, distributed regions use it for most communication.
								Partitioned regions only use multicast for a few purposes, and
								mainly use either TCP or UDP unicast. </note>
						</entry>
						<entry id="entry_ubp_tfp_rr">
							<p>239.192.81.1 for IPv4 (the default IP version) </p>
							<p>FF38::1234 for IPv6 </p>
						</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry id="entry_r1w_tfp_rr">mcast-flow-control </entry>
						<entry id="entry_l1c_5fp_rr">Tuning property for flow-of-control protocol
							for unicast and multicast no-ack UDP messaging. Compound property made
							up of three settings separated by commas: byteAllowance,
							rechargeThreshold, and rechargeBlockMs. <p>Valid values range from these
								minimums: 10000,0.1,500 to these maximums: no_maximum ,0.5,60000.
									<note>This setting controls only peer-to-peer communication,
									generally between distributed regions. </note>
							</p>
						</entry>
						<entry id="entry_lsg_5fp_rr">1048576,0.25, 5000 </entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry id="entry_dkn_5fp_rr">mcast-port </entry>
						<entry id="entry_ylr_5fp_rr">Port used, along with the mcast-address, for multicast
							communication with other members of the distributed system. If zero,
							multicast is disabled. <note>Select different multicast addresses and
								ports for different distributed systems. Do not just use different
								addresses. Some operating systems may not keep communication
								separate between systems that use unique addresses but the same port
								number. </note>
							<p>Valid values are in the range 0..65535. </p>
							<p>
								<note>This setting controls only peer-to-peer communication and does not apply to
									client/server or multi-site communication. </note>
							</p>
							<p>If you have values specified for the <codeph>locators</codeph>
								property, the <codeph>mcast-port</codeph> property defaults to 0.
							</p>
						</entry>
						<entry id="entry_hcv_5fp_rr">10334 </entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry id="entry_os1_vfp_rr">mcast-recv-buffer-size </entry>
						<entry id="entry_jp2_vfp_rr">Size of the socket buffer used for incoming multicast
							transmissions. You should set this high if there will be high volumes of
							messages. <p>Valid values are in the range 2048.. OS_maximum. </p>
							<note>The default setting is higher than the default OS maximum buffer
								size on Unix, which should be increased to at least 1 megabyte to
								provide high-volume messaging on Unix systems. </note>
							<note>This setting controls only peer-to-peer communication and does not
								apply to client/server or multi-site communication. </note>
						</entry>
						<entry id="entry_hl3_vfp_rr">1048576 </entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry id="entry_qbm_vfp_rr">mcast-send-buffer-size </entry>
						<entry id="entry_hmp_vfp_rr">The size of the socket buffer used for outgoing
							multicast transmissions. <p>Valid values are in the range 2048.. OS_maximum. <note>This
									setting controls only peer-to-peer communication and does not
									apply to client/server or multi-site communication. </note>
							</p>
						</entry>
						<entry id="entry_hbt_vfp_rr">65535 </entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry id="entry_qd1_wfp_rr">mcast-ttl </entry>
						<entry id="entry_cd2_wfp_rr">How far multicast messaging goes in your network. Lower settings
							may improve system performance. A setting of 0 constrains multicast
							messaging to the machine. <note>This setting controls only peer-to-peer
								communication and does not apply to client/server or multi-site
								communication. </note>
						</entry>
						<entry id="entry_p23_wfp_rr">32 </entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry id="entry_zd4_wfp_rr">member-timeout </entry>
						<entry id="entry_bmr_wfp_rr"><keyword keyref="product_name"/> uses the
								<codeph>member-timeout</codeph> server configuration, specified in
							milliseconds, to detect the abnormal termination of members. The
							configuration setting is used in two ways: 1) First it is used during
							the UDP heartbeat detection process. When a member detects that a
							heartbeat datagram is missing from the member that it is monitoring
							after the time interval of 2 * the value of
								<codeph>member-timeout</codeph>, the detecting member attempts to
							form a TCP/IP stream-socket connection with the monitored member as
							described in the next case. 2) The property is then used again during
							the TCP/IP stream-socket connection. If the suspected process does not
							respond to the <i>are you alive</i> datagram within the time period
							specified in <codeph>member-timeout</codeph>, the membership coordinator
							sends out a new membership view that notes the member's failure.
								<p>Valid values are in the range 1000..600000. </p>
						</entry>
						<entry id="entry_tpv_wfp_rr">5000 </entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry id="entry_lxj_xfp_rr">membership-port-range </entry>
						<entry id="entry_p4n_xfp_rr">The range of ports available for unicast UDP messaging and for
							TCP failure detection. This is specified as two integers separated by a
							hyphen. Different members can use different ranges. <p><keyword
									keyref="product_name"/> randomly chooses at least two unique
								integers from this range for the member, one for UDP unicast
								messaging and the other for TCP failure detection messaging. If
								tcp-port is configured to 0, it will also randomly select a port
								from this range for TCP sockets used for peer-to-peer communication
								only.</p><p>Therefore, the specified range must include at least
								three available port numbers (UDP, FD_SOCK, and TCP
								DirectChannel).</p><p>The system uniquely identifies the member
								using the combined host IP address and UDP port number. </p><p>You
								may want to restrict the range of ports that <keyword
									keyref="product_name"/> uses so the product can run in an
								environment where routers only allow traffic on certain ports. </p>
						</entry>
						<entry id="entry_dmc_zfp_rr">1024-65535 </entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry id="entry_xmg_zfp_rr">memcached-port </entry>
						<entry id="entry_fgk_zfp_rr">If specified and is non-zero, sets the port
							number for an embedded Gemcached server and starts the Gemcached server. </entry>
						<entry id="entry_jhn_zfp_rr"> 0 </entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry id="entry_urh_1gp_rr">memcached-protocol </entry>
						<entry id="entry_prl_1gp_rr">Sets the protocol used by an embedded Gemcached
							server. Valid values are <codeph>BINARY</codeph> and
								<codeph>ASCII.</codeph> If you omit this property, the ASCII
							protocol is used. </entry>
						<entry id="entry_mxp_1gp_rr">ASCII </entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry id="entry_cf5_1gp_rr">name </entry>
						<entry id="entry_xdc_bgp_rr">Symbolic name used to identify this system
							member. </entry>
						<entry id="entry_qfb_cgp_rr">
							<i>not set</i>
						</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>
							off-heap-memory-size 
						</entry>
						<entry>Specifies the size of off-heap memory in megabytes (m) or gigabytes (g). For
							example:<codeblock>off-heap-memory-size=4096m
off-heap-memory-size=120g</codeblock></entry>
						<entry>
							<i>not set</i>
						</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry id="entry_n2f_cgp_rr">redundancy-zone </entry>
						<entry id="entry_pvl_cgp_rr">Defines this member's redundancy zone. Used to
							separate member's into different groups for satisfying partitioned
							region redundancy. If this property is set, <keyword
								keyref="product_name"/> will not put redundant copies of data in
							members with the same redundancy zone setting. See <xref
								href="../../developing/partitioned_regions/configuring_ha_for_pr.xml"
							/> for more details.</entry>
						<entry id="entry_u3r_cgp_rr">
							<i>not set</i>
						</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>remote-locators</entry>
						<entry>Used to configure the locators that a cluster will use in order to
							connect to a remote site in a multi-site (WAN) configuration. To use
							locators in a WAN configuration, you must specify a unique distributed
							system ID (<codeph>distributed-system-id</codeph>) for the local cluster
							and remote locator(s) for the remote clusters to which you will connect.
								<p>For each remote locator, provide a host name and/or address
								(separated by ‘@’, if you use both), followed by a port number in
								brackets. Examples: <codeblock>remote-locators=address1[port1],address2[port2] </codeblock>
								<codeblock>remote-locators=hostName1@address1[port1],hostName2@address2[port2] </codeblock>
								<codeblock>remote-locators=hostName1[port1],hostName2[port2]</codeblock>
							</p></entry>
						<entry><i>not set</i></entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry id="entry_n5h_2gp_rr">remove-unresponsive-client </entry>
						<entry id="entry_xfs_ggp_rr">When this property is set to true, the primary
							server drops unresponsive clients from all secondaries and itself.
							Clients are deemed unresponsive when their messaging queues become full
							on the server. While a client's queue is full, puts that would add to
							the queue block on the server. </entry>
						<entry id="entry_mxw_ggp_rr">false </entry>
					</row>

					<row>
						<entry id="entry_pf5_hgp_rr">security-* </entry>
						<entry id="entry_exy_hgp_rr">Used for authentication. Any custom properties
							needed by your <codeph>AuthInitialize</codeph> or
								<codeph>Authenticator</codeph> callbacks. <note>Any security-related
								(properties that begin with <codeph>security-*</codeph>)
								configuration properties that are normally configured in
									<codeph>gemfire.properties</codeph> can be moved to a separate
									<codeph>gfsecurity.properties</codeph> file. Placing these
								configuration settings in a separate file allows you to restrict
								access to security configuration data. This way, you can still allow
								read or write access for your <codeph>gemfire.properties</codeph>
								file. </note>
						</entry>
						<entry id="entry_oqc_3gp_rr">
							<i>not set</i>
						</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry id="entry_qnz_3gp_rr">security-client-accessor </entry>
						<entry id="entry_mzc_jgp_rr">Used for authorization. Static creation method
							returning an <codeph>AccessControl</codeph> object, which determines
							authorization of client-server cache operations. This specifies the
							callback that should be invoked in the pre-operation phase, which is
							when the request for the operation is received from the client. </entry>
						<entry id="entry_dkg_jgp_rr">
							<i>not set</i>
						</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry id="entry_db4_jgp_rr">security-client-accessor-pp </entry>
						<entry id="entry_c5r_jgp_rr">Used for authorization. The callback that
							should be invoked in the post-operation phase, which is when the
							operation has completed on the server but before the result is sent to
							the client. The post-operation callback is also invoked for the updates
							that are sent from server to client through the notification channel. </entry>
						<entry id="entry_zmv_jgp_rr">
							<i>not set</i>
						</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry id="entry_tdz_jgp_rr">security-client-auth-init </entry>
						<entry id="entry_kvc_kgp_rr">Used for authentication. Static creation method
							returning an <codeph>AuthInitialize</codeph> object, which obtains
							credentials for peers in a distributed system. The obtained credentials
							should be acceptable to the <codeph>Authenticator</codeph> specified
							through the security-peer-authenticator property on the peers. </entry>
						<entry id="entry_kkh_kgp_rr">
							<i>not set</i>
						</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry id="entry_qqm_kgp_rr">security-client-authenticator </entry>
						<entry id="entry_emq_kgp_rr">Used for authentication. Static creation method
							returning an <codeph>Authenticator</codeph> object, which is used by a
							peer to verify the credentials of the connecting peer. </entry>
						<entry id="entry_mfv_kgp_rr">
							<i>not set</i>
						</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry id="entry_usz_kgp_rr">security-client-dhalgo </entry>
						<entry id="entry_qfd_lgp_rr">Used for authentication. For secure
							transmission of sensitive credentials like passwords, you can encrypt
							the credentials using the Diffie-Hellman key exchange algorithm. Do this
							by setting the security-client-dhalgo system property on the clients to
							the name of a valid symmetric key cipher supported by the JDK. </entry>
						<entry id="entry_ycp_lgp_rr">
							<i>not set</i>
						</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry id="entry_wct_lgp_rr">security-log-file </entry>
						<entry id="entry_cj3_mgp_rr">Used with authentication. The log file for
							security log messages. If not specified, the member's regular log file
							is used. </entry>
						<entry id="entry_ss4_pgp_rr">
							<i>not set</i>
						</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry id="entry_oft_pgp_rr">security-log-level </entry>
						<entry id="entry_fxf_qgp_rr">Used with authentication. Logging level detail
							for security log messages. <p>Valid values from lowest to highest are
								fine, config, info, warning, error, severe, and none. </p>
						</entry>
						<entry id="entry_qhj_qgp_rr">config </entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry id="entry_tgn_rgp_rr">security-peer-auth-init </entry>
						<entry id="entry_ftq_rgp_rr">Used with authentication. Static creation
							method returning an <codeph>AuthInitialize</codeph> object, which
							obtains credentials for peers in a distributed system. The obtained
							credentials should be acceptable to the <codeph>Authenticator</codeph>
							specified through the security-peer-authenticator property on the peers. </entry>
						<entry id="entry_yz5_rgp_rr">
							<i>not set</i>
						</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry id="entry_pry_rgp_rr">security-peer-authenticator </entry>
						<entry id="entry_uyb_sgp_rr">Used with authentication. Static creation
							method returning an <codeph>Authenticator</codeph> object, which is used
							by a peer to verify the credentials of the connecting peer. </entry>
						<entry id="entry_bjf_sgp_rr">
							<i>not set</i>
						</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry id="entry_by3_sgp_rr">security-peer-verifymember-timeout </entry>
						<entry id="entry_n1m_sgp_rr">Used with authentication. Timeout in
							milliseconds used by a peer to verify membership of an unknown
							authenticated peer requesting a secure connection. </entry>
						<entry id="entry_cmp_sgp_rr">1000 </entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry id="serverbindaddress_Prop">server-bind-address </entry>
						<entry id="entry_tbz_sgp_rr">Relevant only for multi-homed hosts - machines with multiple
							network interface cards. Network adapter card a <keyword
								keyref="product_name"/> server binds to for client/server
							communication. You can use this to separate the server’s client/server
							communication from its peer-to-peer communication, spreading the traffic
							load. <p>This is a machine-wide attribute used for communication with
								clients in client/server and multi-site installations. This setting
								has no effect on locator configuration. </p><p>Specify the IP
								address, not the hostname, because each network card may not have a
								unique hostname. </p><p>An empty string causes the servers to listen
								on the same card used for peer-to-peer communication. This is either
								the <codeph>bind-address</codeph> or, if that is not set, the
								machine’s default card. </p>
						</entry>
						<entry id="entry_jtd_tgp_rr">
							<i>not set</i>
						</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry id="entry_zk3_tgp_rr">server-ssl-ciphers</entry>
						<entry id="entry_ccm_tgp_rr">A space-separated list of the valid SSL ciphers
							for client/server connections. A setting of 'any' uses any ciphers that
							are enabled by default in the configured JSSE provider. If this property
							is not set, then <keyword keyref="product_name"/> uses the value of
								<codeph>cluster-ssl-ciphers</codeph> to determine which ciphers are
							used for client connections. See <xref
								href="../../managing/security/implementing_ssl.xml"
							/>.</entry>
						<entry colname="3" id="entry_m2t_tgp_rr">value of
								<codeph>cluster-ssl-ciphers</codeph></entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry id="entry_x4b_5gp_rr">server-ssl-enabled</entry>
						<entry colname="2" id="entry_w1f_5gp_rr">Enables or disables SSL for
							client/server connections. If this property is not set, then <keyword
								keyref="product_name"/> uses the value of
								<codeph>cluster-ssl-enabled</codeph> to determine whether client
							connections use SSL. See <xref
								href="../../managing/security/implementing_ssl.xml"
							/>.</entry>
						<entry colname="3" id="entry_q2j_5gp_rr">value of
								<codeph>cluster-ssl-enabled</codeph></entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry id="entry_ktn_5gp_rr">server-ssl-protocols</entry>
						<entry colname="2" id="entry_ocs_5gp_rr">A space-separated list of the valid
							SSL protocols for client/server connections. A setting of 'any' uses any
							protocol that is enabled by default in the configured JSSE provider. If
							this property is not set, then <keyword keyref="product_name"/> uses the
							value of <codeph>cluster-ssl-protocols</codeph> to determine which SSL
							protocols are used for client connections. See <xref
								href="../../managing/security/implementing_ssl.xml"
							/>.</entry>
						<entry colname="3" id="entry_akz_5gp_rr">value of
								<codeph>cluster-ssl-protocols</codeph></entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry id="entry_sjt_vgp_rr">server-ssl-require-authentication</entry>
						<entry id="entry_qpw_vgp_rr">Boolean indicating whether to require
							authentication for client/server connections. If this property is not
							set, then <keyword keyref="product_name"/> uses the value of
								<codeph>cluster-ssl-require-authentication</codeph> to determine
							whether client connections require authentication. See <xref
								href="../../managing/security/implementing_ssl.xml"
							/>.</entry>
						<entry colname="3" id="entry_yvz_vgp_rr">value of
								<codeph>cluster-ssl-require-authentication</codeph></entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry id="socketbuffersize_Prop">socket-buffer-size </entry>
						<entry id="entry_pwg_wgp_rr">Receive buffer sizes in bytes of the TCP/IP
							connections used for data transmission. To minimize the buffer size
							allocation needed for distributing large, serializable messages, the
							messages are sent in chunks. This setting determines the size of the
							chunks. Larger buffers can handle large messages more quickly, but take
							up more memory. </entry>
						<entry id="entry_tfk_wgp_rr">32768 </entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry id="entry_ygr_wgp_rr">socket-lease-time </entry>
						<entry id="entry_yfv_wgp_rr">Time, in milliseconds, a thread can have
							exclusive access to a socket it is not actively using. A value of zero
							causes socket leases to never expire. This property is ignored if
							conserve-sockets is true. <p>Valid values are in the range 0..600000.
							</p>
						</entry>
						<entry id="entry_lrz_wgp_rr">60000 </entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry id="entry_bj2_xgp_rr">ssl-ciphers, ssl-enabled, ssl-protocols,
							ssl-require-authentication </entry>
						<entry id="entry_c2j_xgp_rr"><i>Deprecated</i>. Use
								<codeph>cluster-ssl-ciphers</codeph>,
								<codeph>cluster-ssl-enabled</codeph>,
								<codeph>cluster-ssl-protocols</codeph>, or
								<codeph>cluster-ssl-require-authentication</codeph> instead.</entry>
						<entry id="entry_nn4_xgp_rr">
							<i>Deprecated</i>
						</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry id="entry_lft_xgp_rr">start-dev-rest-api</entry>
						<entry id="entry_ptw_xgp_rr">If set to true, then the developer REST API
							service will be started when cache is created. REST service can be
							configured using <codeph>http-service-port</codeph> and
								<codeph>http-service-bind-address</codeph> properties.</entry>
						<entry id="entry_mm1_ygp_rr">false</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry id="entry_twd_ygp_rr">start-locator </entry>
						<entry id="entry_mhh_ygp_rr">If set, automatically starts a locator in the
							current process when the member connects to the distributed system and
							stops the locator when the member disconnects. <p>To use, specify the
								locator with an optional address or host specification and a
								required port number, in one of these formats: <codeblock>start-locator=address[port1] </codeblock>
								<codeblock>start-locator=port1</codeblock>If you only specify the
								port, the address assigned to the member is used for the locator.
							</p>If not already there, this locator is automatically added to the
							list of locators in this set of <codeph>gemfire properties</codeph>. </entry>
						<entry id="entry_ocl_ygp_rr">
							<i>not set</i>
						</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry id="entry_ybq_ygp_rr">statistic-archive-file </entry>
						<entry id="entry_nj5_ygp_rr">The file to which the running system member
							writes statistic samples. For example: "StatisticsArchiveFile.gfs". An
							empty string disables archiving. Adding .gz suffix to the file name
							causes it to be compressed. </entry>
						<entry id="entry_utx_ygp_rr">
							<i>not set</i>
						</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry id="entry_ln2_zgp_rr">statistic-sample-rate </entry>
						<entry id="entry_xmh_zgp_rr">How often to sample statistics, in
							milliseconds. <p>Valid values are in the range 100..60000. </p>
						</entry>
						<entry id="entry_vtk_zgp_rr">1000 </entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry id="entry_qmq_zgp_rr">statistic-sampling-enabled </entry>
						<entry id="entry_d25_zgp_rr">Whether to collect and archive statistics on
							the member. <p>Statistics sampling provides valuable information for
								ongoing system tuning and troubleshooting purposes. Sampling
								statistics at the default sample rate does not impact system
								performance. We recommend enabling statistics sampling in production
								environments. </p>
							<note>This setting does not apply to partitioned regions, where
								statistics are always enabled. </note>
						</entry>
						<entry id="entry_jyx_zgp_rr">false </entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry id="entry_ovd_1hp_rr">tcp-port </entry>
						<entry id="entry_b2h_1hp_rr">The TCP port to listen on for cache
							communications. If set to zero, the operating system selects an
							available port. Each process on a machine must have its own TCP port.
							Note that some operating systems restrict the range of ports usable by
							non-privileged users, and using restricted port numbers can cause
							runtime errors in <keyword keyref="product_name"/> startup. <p>Valid
								values are in the range 0..65535. </p>
						</entry>
						<entry id="entry_efm_1hp_rr">0 </entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry id="entry_m4r_1hp_rr">tombstone-gc-threshold </entry>
						<entry id="entry_rfv_1hp_rr">The number of tombstones that can accumulate
							before the <keyword keyref="product_name"/> member triggers garbage
							collection for tombstones. See <xref
								href="../../developing/distributed_regions/how_region_versioning_works.xml#topic_321B05044B6641FCAEFABBF5066BD399"
								type="topic" format="dita" scope="local"
								><?xm-replace_text How Destroy and Clear Operations Are Resolved?></xref>. </entry>
						<entry id="entry_tzc_bhp_rr">100000 </entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry id="entry_w5h_bhp_rr">udp-fragment-size </entry>
						<entry id="entry_jjl_bhp_rr">Maximum fragment size, in bytes, for
							transmission over UDP unicast or multicast sockets. Smaller messages are
							combined, if possible, for transmission up to the fragment size setting.
								<p>Valid values are in the range 1000..60000. </p>
						</entry>
						<entry id="entry_nhp_bhp_rr">60000 </entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry id="entry_pct_bhp_rr">udp-recv-buffer-size </entry>
						<entry id="entry_qrw_bhp_rr">The size of the socket buffer used for incoming
							UDP point-to-point transmissions. If disable-tcp is false, a reduced
							buffer size of 65535 is used by default. <p>The default setting of
								1048576 is higher than the default OS maximum buffer size on Unix,
								which should be increased to at least 1 megabyte to provide
								high-volume messaging on Unix systems. </p>
							<p>Valid values are in the range 2048.. OS_maximum. </p>
						</entry>
						<entry id="entry_j41_chp_rr">1048576 </entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry id="entry_rnh_chp_rr">udp-send-buffer-size </entry>
						<entry id="entry_yxk_chp_rr">The size of the socket buffer used for outgoing
							UDP point-to-point transmissions. <p>Valid values are in the range
								2048..OS_maximum. </p>
						</entry>
						<entry id="entry_gl4_chp_rr">65535 </entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry id="entry_zk5_chp_rr">use-cluster-configuration</entry>
						<entry id="entry_hby_chp_rr">This property is only applicable for data
							members (non-client and non -ocator). A value of "true" causes a member
							to request and use the configuration from cluster configuration services
							running on dedicated locators. Setting this property to "false" causes a
							member to not request the configuration from the configuration services
							running on the locator(s).</entry>
						<entry id="entry_qhc_dhp_rr">true</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry id="entry_a5d_gbp_rr">user-command-packages</entry>
						<entry id="entry_ph4_dhp_rr">A comma separated list of Java packages that
							contain classes implementing the <codeph>CommandMarker</codeph>
							interface. Matching classes will be loaded when the VM starts and will
							be available in the GFSH command-line utility.</entry>
						<entry id="entry_gft_dhp_rr">
							<i>not set</i>
						</entry>
					</row>
				</tbody>
			</tgroup>
		</table>
	</conbody>
</concept>
