<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE task PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Task//EN" "task.dtd">
<task id="task_75639BFA7847461D9E006E91B728BB44">
	<title>Creating a Region with gfsh</title>
	<shortdesc>A simple and fast way to create a data region in the <keyword
			keyref="product_name_long"/> cache is to use the <codeph>gfsh</codeph> command-line
		tool. </shortdesc>
	<taskbody>
		<prereq id="prereq_602BEEFA895B4574A8CB71C6B9D09531">
			<p>Before you start, configure your <codeph>Cache</codeph> or
					<codeph>ClientCache</codeph> and determine the region shortcut and other
				attributes settings your region needs. </p>
		</prereq>
		<context id="context_CB39BA1CEABB471D966C181BD4FDFDD7">Region creation is subject to
			attribute consistency checks, both internal to the cache and, if the region is not
			local, between all caches where the region is defined. The requirements for consistency
			between region attributes are detailed in the online Java API documentation. </context>
		<steps id="steps_BACDDC3133A448FBB32BD8EC32C5A500">
			<step id="step_CCA3939999A74B8FAFE0922F1827E245">
				<cmd>Start a <codeph>gfsh</codeph> prompt. </cmd>
			</step>
			<step id="step_349B9B16293342539BED24EFB63A40E0">
				<cmd>Connect to a server that is currently acting as a JMX Manager node. </cmd>
			</step>
			<step id="step_3967754A5A894D86BD43A5CE8CF4AEAA">
				<cmd>Enter the <codeph>create region</codeph> command providing any desired region
					attributes as arguments. </cmd>
				<stepresult>For example:
					<codeblock>gfsh&gt;create region --name=region1 --type=REPLICATE</codeblock>
				</stepresult>
			</step>
			<step id="step_B635408A5AC64A078C13888482CDC543">
				<cmd>Add data into the region by using the <xref
						href="../../tools_modules/gfsh/command-pages/import.xml#topic_jw2_2ld_2l"/>
					command or <xref format="dita"
						href="../../tools_modules/gfsh/command-pages/put.xml" scope="local"
						type="concept">put</xref> gfsh command. </cmd>
			</step>
			<step id="step_FB018B9592F542AA9A12B802D2458C8F">
				<cmd>After you modify data in the region you can use the <xref
						href="../../tools_modules/gfsh/command-pages/export.xml#topic_263B70069BFC4A7185F86B3272011734"
						type="topic" format="dita" scope="local"/> command to generate a snapshot of
					the current region's data for later use. </cmd>
			</step>
			<step id="step_AC381DF4A7B04ADC86E53E423287831C">
				<cmd>Export the configuration files of your server so that you can save your
					region's configuration and recreate the region with the same attributes the next
					time you start up your cache server. See <xref
						href="../../tools_modules/gfsh/command-pages/export.xml#topic_C7C69306F93743459E65D46537F4A1EE"
						type="topic" format="dita" scope="local"/> for details. </cmd>
				<info>
					<note>
						<p>The cluster configuration service, which is enabled by default,
						automatically saves the configuration on the locators in the distributed
						system. After you use the gfsh create region command, any new servers that
						you start that attach to the same locator receive the same configuration.
						You can also create alternate configurations within a distributed system by
						specifying a group when creating the region and starting servers. See <xref
							href="../../configuring/cluster_config/gfsh_persist.xml" />.
						</p>
					</note>
				</info>
			</step>
		</steps>
	</taskbody>
</task>
