<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="topic_fpy_z3h_j5">
  <title>How Consistency Is Achieved in WAN Deployments</title>
  <shortdesc>When two or more <keyword keyref="product_name"/> systems are configured to distribute
    events over a WAN, each system performs local consistency checking before it distributes an
    event to a configured gateway sender. Discarded events are not distributed across the WAN. </shortdesc>
  <body>
    <p>Regions can also be configured to distribute updates to other <keyword keyref="product_name"
      /> clusters over a WAN. With a distributed WAN configuration, multiple gateway senders
      asynchronously queue and send region updates to another <keyword keyref="product_name"/>
      cluster. It is possible for multiple sites to send updates to the same region entry at the
      same time. It is also possible that, due to a slow WAN connection, a cluster might receive
      region updates after a considerable delay, and after it has applied more recent updates to a
      region. To ensure that WAN-replicated regions eventually reach a consistent state, <keyword
        keyref="product_name"/> first ensures that each cluster performs consistency checking to
      regions before queuing updates to a gateway sender for WAN distribution. In order words,
      region conflicts are first detected and resolved in the local cluster, using the techniques
      described in the previous sections. </p>
    <p>When a <keyword keyref="product_name"/> cluster in a WAN configuration receives a distributed
      update, conflict checking is performed to ensure that all sites apply updates in the same way.
      This ensures that regions eventually reach a consistent state across all <keyword
        keyref="product_name"/> clusters. The default conflict checking behavior for WAN-replicated
      regions is summarized as follows: </p>
      <ul id="ul_253ADE6D68D440868F4F8583E235DBF9">
        <li id="li_03FE9075F139497D8E5A83112EEAD9D9">If an update is received from the same <keyword
            keyref="product_name"/> cluster that last updated the region entry, then there is no
          conflict and the update is applied. </li>
        <li id="li_81388D57DCAA457DB32C9D56439B6AAB">If an update is received from a different
            <keyword keyref="product_name"/> cluster than the one that last updated the region
          entry, then a potential conflict exists. A cluster applies the update only when the update
          has a timestamp that is later than the timestamp currently recorded in the cache. </li>
      </ul>
    <note>
      <p>If you use the default conflict checking feature for WAN deployments, you must ensure that
      all <keyword keyref="product_name"/> members in all clusters synchronize their system clocks.
      For example, use a common NTP server for all <keyword keyref="product_name"/> members that
      participate in a WAN deployment.
      </p>
    </note>
    <p>As an alternative to the default conflict checking behavior for WAN deployments, you can
      develop and deploy a custom conflict resolver for handling region events that are distributed
      over a WAN. Using a custom resolver enables you to handle conflicts using criteria other than,
      or in addition to, timestamp information. For example, you might always prioritize updates
      that originate from a particular site, given that the timestamp value is within a certain
      range. </p>
    <p>When a gateway sender distributes an event to another <keyword keyref="product_name"/> site,
      it adds the distributed system ID of the local cluster, as well as a timestamp for the event.
      In a default configuration, the cluster that receives the event examines the timestamp to
      determine whether or not the event should be applied. If the timestamp of the update is
      earlier than the local timestamp, the cluster discards the event. If the timestamp is the same
      as the local timestamp, then the entry having the highest distributed system ID is applied (or
      kept). </p>
    <p>You can override the default consistency checking for WAN events by installing a conflict
      resolver plug-in for the region. If a conflict resolver is installed, then any event that can
      potentially cause a conflict (any event that originated from a different distributed system ID
      than the ID that last modified the entry) is delivered to the conflict resolver. The resolver
      plug-in then makes the sole determination for which update to apply or keep. </p>
    <p>See "Implementing a GatewayConflictResolver" under <xref
        href="../events/resolving_multisite_conflicts.xml#topic_E97BB68748F14987916CD1A50E4B4542"
        type="topic" format="dita" scope="local"/> to configure a custom resolver. </p>
  </body>
</topic>
