<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE concept PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN" "http://docs.oasis-open.org/dita/v1.1/OS/dtd/concept.dtd">
<concept id="how_replication_works">
	<title>How Replication and Preloading Work</title>
	<shortdesc>To work with replicated and preloaded regions, you should understand how their data
		is initialized and maintained in the cache. </shortdesc>
	<conbody>
		<section id="section_C75BB463A0584491ABD982A55E5A050F">
			<p>Replicated and preloaded regions are configured by using one of the
					<codeph>REPLICATE</codeph> region shortcut settings, or by setting the region
				attribute <codeph>data-policy</codeph> to <codeph>replicate</codeph>,
					<codeph>persistent-replicate</codeph>, or <codeph>preloaded</codeph>. </p>
		</section>
		<section id="section_B4E76BBCC6104A27BC0A8ECA6B9CDF91">
			<title>Initialization of Replicated and Preloaded Regions</title>
			<p>At region creation, the system initializes the preloaded or replicated region with
				the most complete and up-to-date data set it can find. The system uses these data
				sources to initialize the new region, following this order of preference: </p>
			<ol id="ol_6A401FA1C2A14A6399E12DB33300CEE2">
				<li id="li_FB16D10A71D14F20A2AB697FA74182C8">Another replicated region that is
					already defined in the distributed system. </li>
				<li id="li_82BBF866C4704D7AA88E94D94DCB0E84">For persistent replicate only. Disk
					files, followed by a union of all copies of the region in the distributed cache. </li>
				<li id="li_CDE3479A87BA4EEEA48D9DC45DB0EAA3">For preloaded region only. Another
					preloaded region that is already defined in the distributed system. </li>
				<li id="li_973ED0AB3BB345BD8B457DAA428F1732">The union of all copies of the region
					in the distributed cache. <p/>
				</li>
			</ol>
			<p>
				<image placement="break" id="image_5F50EBA30CE3408091F07A198F821741"
					href="../../images_svg/distributed_replica_preload.svg"/>
			</p>
			<p>While a region is being initialized from a replicated or preloaded region, if the
				source region crashes, the initialization starts over. </p>
			<p>If a union of regions is used for initialization, as in the figure, and one of the
				individual source regions goes away during the initialization (due to cache closure,
				member crash, or region destruction), the new region may contain a partial data set
				from the crashed source region. When this happens, there is no warning logged or
				exception thrown. The new region still has a complete set of the remaining members'
				regions. </p>
		</section>
		<section id="section_6BE7555A711E4CA490B02E58B5DDE396">
			<title>Behavior of Replicated and Preloaded Regions After Initialization</title>
			<p>Once initialized, the preloaded region operates like the region with a
					<codeph>normal</codeph>
				<codeph>data-policy</codeph>, receiving distributions only for entries it has
				defined in the local cache. </p>
			<p>
				<image placement="break" id="image_994CA599B1004D3F95E1BB7C4FAC2AEF"
					href="../../images_svg/distributed_preload.svg"/>
			</p>
			<p/>
			<p>If the region is configured as a replicated region, it receives all new creations in
				the distributed region from the other members. This is the push distribution model.
				Unlike the preloaded region, the replicated region has a contract that states it
				will hold all entries that are present anywhere in the distributed region. </p>
			<p>
				<image placement="break" id="image_2E7F3EB6213A47FEA3ABE32FD2CB1503"
					href="../../images_svg/distributed_replica.svg"/>
			</p>
		</section>
	</conbody>
</concept>
