<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE concept PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN" "concept.dtd">
<concept id="errors-in-delta-propagation"> 
  <title id="title_633EDBB0709745C5BE626A28E1893012">Errors in Delta
	 Propagation</title> 
  <conbody id="conbody_E19C5EE369BA406F97FA1F4BE3E2D4FB"> 
	 <p id="p_26563964E8BA4EBF93F4504FA752A25D">Errors in delta propagation fall
		into two categories based on how they are handled: 
	 <ul id="ol_66BCC3C71EA34FCFA36EC3A6BD5FB613"> 
		<li id="li_A8D39303D7B44D9CBDA2EC4077E62EA1">
		  <p id="p_A63F10EC6E3F4EB88E3D53615B9E4DC5">Problems applying the delta
			 that can be remedied if the originating member sends the full value in place of
			 the delta. Your put operation does not see errors or exceptions related to the
			 failed delta propagation. The system automatically does a full value
			 distribution to the receiver where the problem occurs. This type of error
			 includes:
		  </p>
		  <ul id="ul_01AA34A2F1A24E64989D2ADCCFB432D3"> 
			 <li id="li_55680F6D311D47E98B393784FEE5C487">Unavailable entry value
				in the receiving cache, either because the entry is missing or its value is
				null. In both cases, there is nothing to apply the delta to and the full value
				must be sent. This is most likely to occur if you destroy or invalidate your
				entries locally, either through application calls or through configured actions
				like eviction or entry expiration. 
			 </li> 
			 <li
			  id="li_D358C947A8A44B208193DE425EFC7C00"><codeph>InvalidDeltaException</codeph>
				thrown by 
				<codeph>fromDelta</codeph> method, programmed by you. This
				exception enables you to avoid applying deltas that would violate data
				consistency checks or other application requirements. Throwing this exception
				causes GemFire to send the full value.
			 </li> 
			 <li id="li_51DE3F7274364B02AD8518B896863048">Any error applying the
				delta in a client in server-to-client propagation. The client retrieves the
				full value from the server.
			 </li> 
		  </ul>
		</li> 
		<li id="li_B230F1D8100D4E1EAD0322F80D6372DD">Problems creating or
		  distributing the delta that cannot be fixed by distributing the full value.
		  These problems are caused by errors or exceptions in 
		  <codeph>hasDelta</codeph> or 
		  <codeph>toDelta</codeph>. In these cases, your 
		  <codeph>put</codeph> operation fails with an exception. 
		</li> 
	 </ul> 
	 </p> 
  </conbody>
</concept>
