<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE concept PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN" "concept.dtd">
<concept
	id="implementing-delta-propagation">
	<title
		id="title_7969E8015B314FFCB01ACFE4E4B19772">Implementing Delta Propagation</title>
	<shortdesc>By default, delta propagation is enabled in your distributed system and is used for
		objects that implement the delta interface. You program the client-side methods to extract
		delta information for your entries and to apply received delta information. </shortdesc>
	<conbody
		id="conbody_9CE12524178A4FA988341F953795DF49">
		<p>For more information, see <xref
				href="delta-propagation-api.xml#delta-propagation-api"
				type="concept"
				format="dita"
				scope="local">Delta Propagation API</xref>. </p>
		<p>
			<b>Prerequisites</b></p>
			<ul
				id="ol_1420D0AC31C341588E1850E0F1A274A9">
				<li
					id="li_BF938E5D15104B299DD74853A908B4B0">Study your object types and expected
					application behavior to determine which objects should use delta propagation.
					Delta propagation is not beneficial for all data and data modification
					scenarios. See <xref
						href="performance.xml#performance"
						type="concept"
						format="dita"
						scope="local"><?xm-replace_text Exceptions and Limitations   ?></xref>. </li>
				<li id="li_A0E992F60192401A9EC8658DC6CA3DBC">Decide whether to enable cloning. Cloning is
				disabled by default. See <xref scope="local"
					href="delta-propagation-properties.xml#delta-propagation-properties"
					type="concept" format="dita">cloning-enabled</xref>.</li>
				<li id="li_3F25C2D482804DEF932FCD65CF899F1B">If you enable cloning, consider
							providing your own implementation, to optimize performance. </li>
				<li id="li_702CC6FE95044EA3A41F576746D94B6B">If you do not enable cloning,
							be sure to synchronize your delta code. </li>
				<li id="li_C7F36AD82BB0497F99AE8FBF5C9B69B7">If you do not enable cloning, review all associated
				listener code for dependencies on the entry event old value. Without cloning,
					<keyword keyref="product_name"/> modifies the entry in place and so loses its
				reference to the old value. For delta events, the <codeph>EntryEvent</codeph>
				methods to retrieve the old and new values both return the new value. </li>
			</ul>
		<p>
			<b>Procedure</b>
		</p>
		<p>For every class in which you want delta propagation, implement the delta interface and
			update your methods to support delta propagation. Exactly how you do this depends on
			your application and object needs, but these steps describe the basic approach.</p>			
			<ol
				id="ol_E87A912B84764F76BEC669118C118293">
				<li
					id="li_F652D59AFE224FB8B10CD7C87F5766DE">Study the object contents to decide how
					to handle delta changes. <p>Delta propagation has the same issues of distributed
						concurrency control as the distribution of full objects, but on a more
						detailed level. Some parts of your objects may be able to change independent
						of one another while others may always need to change together. Send deltas
						large enough to keep your data logically consistent. If, for example, field
						A and field B depend on each other, then your delta distributions should
						either update both fields or neither. As with regular updates, the fewer
						producers you have on a data region, the lower your likelihood of
						concurrency issues. </p>
				</li>
				<li id="li_F74B0C91493042A7AB42A52F4051F009">In the application code that puts entries, put the
				fully populated object into the local cache. This usually means doing a
					<codeph>get</codeph> on the entry, unless you are sure it does not already exist
				anywhere in the distributed region. <p>Even though you are planning to send only
					deltas, errors on the receiving end could cause <keyword keyref="product_name"/>
					to request the full object, so you must provide it to the originating put
					method. Do this even in empty producers, with regions configured for no local
					data storage. </p>
			</li>
				<li
					id="li_A2AD70EC801F431499CF37DD2B52173F">Change each field’s update method to
					record information about the update. <p>The information must be sufficient for
							<codeph>toDelta</codeph> to encode the delta and any additional required
						delta information when it is invoked. </p>
				</li>
				<li
					id="li_8E21845E3E844AE992DE1B0649A480D6">Write <codeph>hasDelta</codeph> to
					report on whether a delta is available. </li>
				<li
					id="li_EF53E58B35504A66AADEEA26AF85FEF8">When writing your serialization
					methods, <codeph>toDelta</codeph>, <codeph>fromDelta</codeph>,
						<codeph>toData</codeph>, <codeph>fromData</codeph>, be sure to exclude any
					fields used to manage delta state, which do not need to be sent. </li>
				<li
					id="li_85842697E9374C47A236F028FE70916D">Write <codeph>toDelta</codeph> to
					create a byte stream with the changes to the object and any other information
					that <codeph>fromDelta</codeph> will need to apply the changes. Before returning
					from <codeph>toDelta</codeph>, reset your delta state to indicate that there are
					no delta changes waiting to be sent. </li>
				<li
					id="li_54F4533308754ED58C13604EC375D531">Write <codeph>fromDelta</codeph> to
					decode the byte stream that <codeph>toDelta</codeph> creates and update the
					object. </li>
				<li
					id="li_E755698CCE38462990510F1DD491054C">Make sure you provide adequate
					synchronization to your object to maintain a consistent object state. <p>If you
						do not use cloning, you will probably need to synchronize on reads and
						writes to avoid reading partially written updates from the cache. This might
						involve <codeph>toDelta</codeph>, <codeph>fromDelta</codeph>, and other
						object access and update methods. Additionally, your implementation should
						take into account the possibility of concurrent invocations of
							<codeph>fromDelta</codeph> and one or more of the object's update
						methods. </p>
				</li>
			</ol>
	</conbody>
</concept>
