<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE concept PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN" "concept.dtd">
<concept id="concept_5C7614F71F394C62ACA1BDC5684A7AC4">
	<title>Creating Hash Indexes</title>
	<shortdesc><?xm-replace_text Short Description?>
		<keyword keyref="product_name"/> supports the creation of hash indexes for the purposes of
		performing equality-based queries.</shortdesc>
	<conbody>
		<section id="section_8A927DFB29364DA7856E7FE122FC1654">
			<title>Why Create a HashIndex</title>
			<p>By creating a hash index, you can vastly improve the memory usage of your index. If
				you are doing equality based queries, your indexing footprint is significantly
				reduced. As an example, previously when you created an index that contained string
				fields, copies of the strings were included in the index. By using hash indexes, we
				ensure that indexed expressions are canonicalized and stored in the index as
				pointers to the objects lying in the region. In internal test cases we have seen
				improvements in the 30% range depending on the keys and data being used. </p>
			<p>
				<note>Your performance results may vary depending on the keys and data being
					indexed. </note>
			</p>
		</section>
		<section id="section_2EF23A54378E44FFBF1BEB32E41ABD61">
			<title>Performance Considerations</title>
			<p>The performance of put operations when using a hash index should be comparable to
				other indexes or slightly slower. Queries themselves are expected to be slightly
				slower due to the implementation of hash index and the cost of recalculating the key
				on request, which is the trade-off for the space savings that using a hash index
				provides. </p>
		</section>
		<section id="section_800401C53E5841269F389329B8A4CDF3">
			<title>Limitations</title>
			<p> The following limitations must be considered when creating hash indexes: </p>
			<ul id="ul_40819CE310E14D93BBDCD2FA183F0805">
				<li id="li_9509FB9D874A4CD4989DB8B82EACDC6A">You can only use hash indexes with
					equals and not equals queries. </li>
				<li id="li_33E15E0ED85F4C64A2840C02AA707F76">Hash index maintenance will be slower
					than the other indexes due to synchronized add methods. </li>
				<li id="li_9A408D8325A54A1893804F9D71B1C858">Hash indexes cannot be maintained
					asynchronously. If you attempt to create a hash index on a region with
					asynchronous set as the maintenance mode, an exception will be thrown. </li>
				<li>You cannot use hash indexes for queries with multiple iterators or nested
					collections.</li>
			</ul>
		</section>
		<section id="section_CA2476E015D14DE7B522377C931A8492">
			<title>Examples of Creating a Hash Index</title>
			<p>
				<b>Using the Java API:</b></p>
				<codeblock>QueryService qs = cache.getQueryService();
 qs.createHashIndex("myHashIndex", "mktValue", "/exampleRegion");</codeblock>
			<p>
				<b>Using gfsh:</b></p>
				<codeblock>gfsh&gt; create index --name=myHashIndex --expression=mktValue --region=/exampleRegion</codeblock>
			<p>
				<b>Using cache.xml:</b></p>
				<codeblock>&lt;region name=exampleRegion&gt;
 &lt;region-attributes . . . &gt;
 &lt;/region-attributes&gt;
 &lt;index name="myHashIndex" from-clause="/exampleRegion p" expression="p.mktValue" type="hash"/&gt;
 ...
&lt;/region&gt;</codeblock>
		</section>
	</conbody>
</concept>
