<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE concept PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN" "http://docs.oasis-open.org/dita/v1.1/OS/dtd/concept.dtd">
<concept id="indexing_guidelines">
	<title>Tips and Guidelines on Using Indexes</title>
	<shortdesc>Optimizing your queries with indexes requires a cycle of careful planning, testing,
		and tuning. Poorly-defined indexes can degrade the performance of your queries instead of
		improving it. This section gives guidelines for index usage in the query service. </shortdesc>
	<conbody>
		<section id="section_A8885DFC334243508C4563C9692E0801">
			<p>When creating indexes, keep in mind the following: </p>
			<ul id="ul_D11E8735415E4372A080751496B32004">
				<li id="li_ED7FD1B37A00490ABCCFDFC49AE85D04">Indexes incur maintenance costs as they
					must be updated when the indexed data changes. An index that requires many
					updates and is not used very often may require more system resources than using
					no index at all. </li>
				<li id="li_51231BCB72774F8082A97C9806CBA437">Indexes consume memory. </li>
				<li id="li_A6B6C9A09ADD4625B42A2012B25568D0">Indexes have limited support on
					overflow regions. See <xref
						href="indexes_with_overflow_regions.xml#concept_87BE7DB32C714EB0BF7532AF93569328"
						type="concept" format="dita" scope="local"/> for details. </li>
				<li>If you are creating multiple indexes on the same region, first define your
					indexes and then create the indexes all at once to avoid iterating over the
					region multiple times. See <xref
						href="create_multiple_indexes.xml#topic_omf_pxn_jq"/> for details.</li>
			</ul>
		</section>
		<section id="section_A8AFAA243B5C43DD9BB9F9235A48AF53">
			<title> Tips for Writing Queries that Use Indexes</title>
			<p>As with query processors that run against relational databases, the way a query is
				written can greatly affect execution performance. Among other things, whether
				indexes are used depends on how each query is stated. These are some of the things
				to consider when optimizing your <keyword keyref="product_name"/> queries for
				performance: </p>
			<ul id="ul_833384B6F6774C3BA5BF6CE622FFE7A1">
				<li id="li_6D6F5BF5D6FB4DA9AFED3A3892E7AF38">In general an index will improve query
					performance if the FROM clauses of the query and index match exactly. </li>
				<li id="li_A67AD152B41942749AA5FEA961EEBA63">The query evaluation engine does not
					have a sophisticated cost-based optimizer. It has a simple optimizer which
					selects best index (one) or multiple indexes based on the index size and the
					operator that is being evaluated. </li>
				<li id="li_717A1FB3EE5B4ABF801DCE9ACDF3F201">For AND operators, you may get better
					results if the conditions that use indexes and conditions that are more
					selective come before other conditions in the query. </li>
				<li id="li_FC9A23B9F1CC487689E5482D78EEACE4">Indexes are not used in expressions
					that contain NOT, so in a WHERE clause of a query, <codeph>qty &gt;= 10</codeph>
					could have an index on <codeph>qty</codeph> applied for efficiency. However,
						<codeph>NOT(qty &lt; 10)</codeph> could not have the same index applied. </li>
				<li>Whenever possible, provide a hint to allow the query engine to prefer a specific
					index. See <xref href="query_index_hints.xml#topic_cfb_mxn_jq"/></li>
			</ul>
		</section>
	</conbody>
</concept>
