<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE concept PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN" "concept.dtd">
<concept
	id="concept_AEFA04AF9ABD42C0A37ED31806596D24">
	<title>Enabling Queue Conflation to Improve Update Performance</title>
	<shortdesc> Conflation of entry update messages can reduce the number of update messages a native
		client receives,  thereby increasing performance. The native client receives only the most
		recent update for a particular entry key. </shortdesc>
	<conbody>
		<p>Conflation is enabled for a cache server region, so all clients receiving updates for a
			particular region benefit from the conflation. To enable conflation, set the cache
			server’s <codeph>enable-subscription-conflation</codeph> region attribute to
				<codeph>true</codeph>. This region attribute is <codeph>false</codeph> by default. </p>
		<p> The queue managment code conflates entry updates as part of the enqueue operation. If the
			previous enqueued item for that key is also an <codeph>update</codeph> operation, the
			queue management code removes that previously enqueued update, leaving only the latest
			update to be sent when event distribution occurs. For high availability,  conflation
			also occurs for any secondary queues. </p>
		<p> Only entry <codeph>update</codeph> messages in a cache server region with
				<codeph>distributed-no-ack</codeph> scope are conflated. Region operations and entry
			operations other than updates are not conflated. </p>
		<p> For more information, see <xref
				href="../../developing/events/conflate_server_subscription_queue.xml"/>. </p>
		<section
			id="section_BE506A32A8E44073B197B03AC5232C01">
			<title>Overriding Queue Conflation Per-Client</title>
			<p>Override conflation on a per-client basis by setting the conflate-events property in the
				native client’s <codeph>gfcpp.properties</codeph> file. </p>
			<p>Valid settings are:</p>
				<ul
					id="ul_0D518989C24047768358A4DC04952392">
					<li
						id="li_8768B191B99944A4B56C981A99458C3A"><codeph>server</codeph>. Uses the
						server settings. </li>
					<li
						id="li_654E1DE7814C44B5889B624BEC88C1DA"><codeph>true</codeph>. Conflates
						everything sent to the client. </li>
					<li id="li_31E43C020F4F4BA6BDCEDFB28E249895"><codeph>false</codeph>. Does not conflate anything
						sent to the client. </li>
				</ul>
		</section>
	</conbody>
</concept>
