<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE concept PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN" "http://docs.oasis-open.org/dita/v1.1/OS/dtd/concept.dtd">
<concept id="helping_the_engine_resolve_attributes"> 
  <title>Help the Query Engine Resolve Query Attributes</title> 
  <prolog audience="basic"> 
  </prolog> 
  <conbody> 
	 <section id="section_C6ADE55BC48142B48AB744DA8444796D"> 
		<p>To run successfully, the query engine must be able to access all
		  attributes specified in the query. 
		</p> 
		<p>To help the engine process your query at optimal speed: 
		<ol id="ol_D82F2AE759CE437D902AF51D918146E5"> 
		  <li id="li_A56586AE0151488D987065F6C789A9EB">Use iterator variables to
			 explicitly associate each querying attribute to a single collection in the FROM
			 clause. This ensures the engine can associate any querying attribute used
			 anywhere in the query with one of the FROM clause collections. 
		  </li> 
		  <li id="li_BFD3A832F5CE4AC99024F49508020F0A">Explicitly specify the
			 object type for each collection in the FROM clause. This lets the engine
			 quickly determine the object type of the elements in each FROM clause
			 collection. 
		  </li> 
		</ol>The querying engine can do some object type discovery on its own and
		it can scan for the querying attributes within all of the object types in the
		FROM clause collections. Both of these activities use cycles, however, and the
		attributes search can fail if a same-named attribute is contained in more than
		one of the collections. 
		</p> 
	 </section> 
	 <section id="section_F13E4C2D91014A7EB91A96E566E9E17C"> 
		<title>Use Iterator Variables</title> 
		<p>Associate a name to each collection expressed in the FROM clause and
		  use the name everywhere you reference any of the collection's querying
		  attribute. 
		</p> 
		<p>In this example, 
		  <codeph>pflo</codeph> and 
		  <codeph>posnVal</codeph> are explicit iterator variables: 
		  <codeblock>IMPORT cacheRunner.Position; 
SELECT DISTINCT pflo."type", posnVal.qty 
    FROM /portfolios pflo, positions.values posnVal TYPE Position 
    WHERE pflo.status = 'active' and posnVal.mktValue &gt; 25.00</codeblock> 
		</p> 
		<p>Make the name unique to the query. The variable is added to the
		  current scope and becomes the iterator variable bound to the elements of the
		  collection as they are iterated. 
		  <note>Iterator variables avoid ambiguity in your queries when there are
			 attributes from different collections with the same name. Even if there is no
			 ambiguity at the time you write a query, a change to your cache could introduce
			 ambiguity at a later point and cause the query to fail until iterator variables
			 are added. 
		  </note> 
		</p> 
	 </section> 
	 <section id="section_0EE4CBE1E1254966889C4EDE5C8501FF"> 
		<title>Specify the Object Types of FROM Clause Collections</title> 
		<p>Specify the object types in one of these ways: 
		<ul id="ul_C7062EBA368B4263801B67AC770621AE"> 
		  <li id="li_683C65B2860F4714BED1C6497B7EE61D">Through region
			 configuration, using key and value constraints 
		  </li> 
		  <li id="li_677CC39754314A55B6643985971E9C40">By providing the object
			 type specification in the query string 
		  </li> 
		</ul>Usually, the best approach is a mix of the two. 
		</p> 
		<p>Region object constraints and typing or typecasting inside the query
		  tells the query engine the types of the objects in the FROM clause collections.
		  The specific types of the collections themselves - map or array or some other
		  type - is not relevant to the querying engine. The only thing that matters is
		  the types of the elements contained in the collections. 
		</p> 
	 </section> 
	 <section id="section_9B373CD8DF374209A029C13C7546CEA3"> 
		<title>Use Region Configuration to Specify Object Type</title> 
		<p>The region configuration settings constrain the key and value types
		  that are stored in the cache and automatically provide typing information to
		  the query engine. This type of object specification works for all of your
		  top-level cached objects and has the added advantage of protecting the
		  homogeneity of the data for querying. Set the types with the 
		  <codeph>value-constraint</codeph> and 
		  <codeph>key-constraint</codeph> region attributes. The querying engine
		  refers to these attributes when it accesses the region contents. In this
		  example, 
		  <codeph>/portfolios</codeph> resolves to a collection of entry values.
		  This collection is defined by the region’s 
		  <codeph>value-constraint</codeph> to have elements of type 
		  <codeph>cacheRunner.Portfolio</codeph>. This query relies on the 
		  <codeph>value-constraint</codeph> to resolve 
		  <codeph>id</codeph>. 
		  <codeblock>SELECT DISTINCT * FROM /portfolios 
    WHERE (id = 'XYZ-1' OR id = 'ABC-1')</codeblock> 
		</p> 
	 </section> 
	 <section id="section_F7F9626C7F3B4D3B82D5C87FD23EF8E7"> 
		<title>Provide Object Type Specification in a Query String </title> 
		<p>You have to provide explicit typing in your queries for elements in
		  collections that are nested inside your region entries and for entries and keys
		  in regions where you are not able to specify a value constraint or key
		  constraint. Typing is a 
		  <ph
		  conref="../../product_short_name.xml#ditacomponent_4CDD0B39CDD54D2AAF1CBC81A1FDBA19/ph_2E41EB9BE730428A970C1C206D14DC09"><?xm-replace_text Phrase?></ph>
		  ease-of-use extension of the standard OQL typecasting syntax. 
		</p> 
		<p>To provide explicit typing: 
		<ol id="ol_65E4861F2707477C9CDDC87E925A6AED"> 
		  <li id="li_654F176697BC4EC0B720E7EA5548FC4F">Import non-common object
			 class definitions immediately before the SELECT statement in your query string 
		  </li> 
		  <li id="li_518B5D8ED0E24080BB2DF114C6B7222A">Type or typecast your
			 collections in the FROM clause where you first reference them 
		  </li> 
		</ol> 
		</p> 
		<p>The IMPORT statement allows you to provide custom Java classes to the
		  query engine. IMPORT statements are passed to the engine in the same string as
		  the query that uses them. The IMPORT is only required in a query if the class
		  name is used explicitly in the query string. The only place you can have a
		  package name in a query is in an IMPORT statement. 
		</p> 
		<p>These are valid IMPORT statements: 
		  <codeblock>IMPORT com.myFolder.Portfolio; 
IMPORT com.myFolder.Portfolio AS MyPortfolio;</codeblock> 
		</p> 
		<p>The first form of the import statement allows 
		  <codeph>Portfolio</codeph> to be used as the name of the class 
		  <codeph>com.myFolder.Portfolio</codeph>. The second form provides an
		  alternate class name to be used. This is useful when a class name is not unique
		  across packages and classes in a single query. 
		</p> 
		<p>Example: 
		  <codeblock>IMPORT com.commonFolder.Portfolio; 
IMPORT com.myFolder.Portfolio AS MyPortfolio; 
SELECT DISTINCT mpflo.status 
    FROM /portfolios pflo TYPE Portfolio, /myPortfolios mpflo TYPE MyPortfolio 
    WHERE pflo.status = 'active' and mpflo.id = pflo.id </codeblock> 
		</p> 
		<p> 
		  <note>You need to include the IMPORT statements required by your query
			 in the string that you pass to the query engine. Thus, the string to run the
			 previous example is this: "<codeph>IMPORT com.commonFolder.Portfolio; IMPORT
				com.myFolder.Portfolio AS MyPortfolio; SELECT DISTINCT mpflo.status FROM
				/portfolios pflo TYPE Portfolio, /myPortfolios mpflo TYPE MyPortfolio WHERE
				pflo.status = 'active' and mpflo.id = pflo.id</codeph>" 
		  </note> 
		</p> 
		<p/> 
		<p>Common type names do not require an IMPORT statement. This table lists
		  the common types defined by the system and the Java types that they represent.
		  You can just use these to typecast in your queries without importing them
		  first. 
		</p> 
		<table id="table_EB3B474F6D334730BA150ECB18ADF6B9"> 
		  <tgroup cols="2"> 
			 <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="*"/> 
			 <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="*"/> 
			 <thead> 
				<row> 
				  <entry>Common Object Type Name 
				  </entry> 
				  <entry>Java Representation 
				  </entry> 
				</row> 
			 </thead> 
			 <tbody> 
				<row> 
				  <entry>short 
				  </entry> 
				  <entry>short or java.lang.Short 
				  </entry> 
				</row> 
				<row> 
				  <entry>long 
				  </entry> 
				  <entry>long or java.lang.Long 
				  </entry> 
				</row> 
				<row> 
				  <entry>int 
				  </entry> 
				  <entry>int or java.lang.Integer 
				  </entry> 
				</row> 
				<row> 
				  <entry>float 
				  </entry> 
				  <entry>float or java.lang.Float 
				  </entry> 
				</row> 
				<row> 
				  <entry>double 
				  </entry> 
				  <entry>double or java.lang.Double 
				  </entry> 
				</row> 
				<row> 
				  <entry>char 
				  </entry> 
				  <entry>char or java.lang.Character 
				  </entry> 
				</row> 
				<row> 
				  <entry>string 
				  </entry> 
				  <entry>java.lang.String 
				  </entry> 
				</row> 
				<row> 
				  <entry>boolean 
				  </entry> 
				  <entry>boolean or java.lang.Boolean 
				  </entry> 
				</row> 
				<row> 
				  <entry>byte or octet 
				  </entry> 
				  <entry>byte or java.lang.Byte 
				  </entry> 
				</row> 
				<row> 
				  <entry>date 
				  </entry> 
				  <entry>java.sql.Date 
				  </entry> 
				</row> 
				<row> 
				  <entry>time 
				  </entry> 
				  <entry>java.sql.Time 
				  </entry> 
				</row> 
				<row> 
				  <entry>timestamp 
				  </entry> 
				  <entry>java.sql.Timestamp 
				  </entry> 
				</row> 
				<row> 
				  <entry>array&lt;type &gt; 
				  </entry> 
				  <entry>java.lang.Object[] 
				  </entry> 
				</row> 
				<row> 
				  <entry>collection&lt;type&gt; 
				  </entry> 
				  <entry>java.util.Collection 
				  </entry> 
				</row> 
				<row> 
				  <entry>list&lt;type&gt; 
				  </entry> 
				  <entry>java.util.List 
				  </entry> 
				</row> 
				<row> 
				  <entry>map&lt;type,type&gt; or dictionary&lt;type,type&gt; 
				  </entry> 
				  <entry>java.lang.Map 
				  </entry> 
				</row> 
				<row> 
				  <entry>set&lt;type&gt; 
				  </entry> 
				  <entry>java.util.Set 
				  </entry> 
				</row> 
			 </tbody> 
		  </tgroup> 
		</table> 
		<p>The querying engine treats primitives as equivalent to their
		  respective wrapper types. 
		</p> 
		<p>With all object types available to the query engine, connect each FROM
		  clause collection to a type by using either the TYPE keyword or with
		  typecasting. 
		</p> 
		<p>This query uses the imported 
		  <codeph>cacheRunner.Position</codeph> class to TYPE 
		  <codeph>positions.values</codeph> as a collection of values: 
		  <codeblock><b>IMPORT cacheRunner.Position; </b>
SELECT DISTINCT mktValue 
    FROM /portfolios, <b>positions.values TYPE Position</b> 
    WHERE mktValue &gt; 25.00</codeblock> 
		</p> 
		<p>This query is equivalent: 
		  <codeblock><b>IMPORT cacheRunner.Position; </b>
SELECT DISTINCT mktValue 
    FROM /portfolios, <b>(collection&lt;Position&gt;)positions.values</b> 
    WHERE mktValue &gt; 25.00</codeblock> 
		</p> 
		<p> 
		  <note>All of the lines in these examples have to be passed to the query
			 engine, including the IMPORT statement. IMPORT statements in your Java code are
			 not passed to the query engine. 
		  </note> 
		</p> 
		<p>In the next example, the FROM clause collections are a collection of 
		  <codeph>Portfolio</codeph> instances and a collection of 
		  <codeph>Map.Entry</codeph>s whose values are instances of 
		  <codeph>Positions</codeph>. When 
		  <codeph>Map</codeph>s are used as collections, they are treated as
		  collections of entries, that is, instances of 
		  <codeph>java.util.Map.Entry</codeph>. 
		  <codeblock>IMPORT cacheRunner.Position; 
SELECT DISTINCT posEntry.value.mktValue 
    FROM /portfolios, (map&lt;string,Position&gt;)positions posEntry 
    WHERE posEntry.value.mktValue &gt; 25.00</codeblock> 
		</p> 
		<p>The IMPORT statements in these examples assume that the imported
		  packages are available in the CLASSPATH. The class’s package name cannot be
		  used in the FROM clause - it must be specified in an IMPORT statement. 
		</p> 
	 </section> 
  </conbody> 
</concept> 
