<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE concept PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN" "http://docs.oasis-open.org/dita/v1.1/OS/dtd/concept.dtd">
<concept id="configuring_total_buckets">
	<title>Configuring the Number of Buckets for a Partitioned Region</title>
	<shortdesc id="shortdesc_1B09D44F6D77466FAA1F271D6A5A3862">Decide how many buckets to assign to
		your partitioned region and set the configuration accordingly. </shortdesc>
	<conbody>
		<section id="section_DF52B2BF467F4DB4B8B3D16A79EFCA39">
			<p>The total number of buckets for the partitioned region determines the granularity of
				data storage and thus how evenly the data can be distributed. <keyword
					keyref="product_name"/> distributes the buckets as evenly as possible across the
				data stores. The number of buckets is fixed after region creation. </p>
			<p>The partition attribute <codeph>total-num-buckets</codeph> sets the number for the
				entire partitioned region across all participating members. Set it using one of the
				following: </p>
				<ul id="ul_38e5c582-c595-4b88-b4be-57e43bf77ecf">
					<li id="li_4FA315CC0A05455099F9D779F2FA1AE2">XML:
						<codeblock outputclass="language-xml">&lt;region name="PR1"&gt; 
  &lt;region-attributes refid="PARTITION"&gt; 
    &lt;partition-attributes total-num-buckets="7"/&gt; 
  &lt;/region-attributes&gt; 
&lt;/region&gt; </codeblock>
					</li>
					<li id="li_3B98E3CE47EF434881A1DE709D4B1173">Java:
						<codeblock outputclass="language-java">RegionFactory rf = 
	cache.createRegionFactory(RegionShortcut.PARTITION);
rf.setPartitionAttributes(new PartitionAttributesFactory().setTotalNumBuckets(7).create());
custRegion = rf.create("customer");</codeblock></li>
					<li>gfsh:<p>Use the <parmname>--total-num-buckets</parmname> parameter of the
								<cmdname>create region</cmdname> command. For
							example:<codeblock>gfsh>create region --name="PR1" --type=PARTITION --total-num-buckets=7</codeblock></p>
					</li>
				</ul>
		</section>
		<section id="section_C956D9BA41C546F89D07DCFE901E539F">
			<title>Calculate the Total Number of Buckets for a Partitioned Region</title>
			<p>Follow these guidelines to calculate the total number of buckets for the partitioned
				region: </p>
				<ul id="ul_72C6333BD6AD40C3B93B4648DBB342A5">
					<li id="li_6C28895141F641768DB399676A75AD29">Use a prime number. This provides
						the most even distribution. </li>
					<li id="li_D8E7F80C0B6B4C6EBD09CE2E1758C522">Make it at least four times as
						large as the number of data stores you expect to have for the region. The
						larger the ratio of buckets to data stores, the more evenly the load can be
						spread across the members. Note that there is a trade-off between load
						balancing and overhead, however. Managing a bucket introduces significant
						overhead, especially with higher levels of redundancy. </li>
				</ul>
			<p>You are trying to avoid the situation where some members have significantly more data
				entries than others. For example, compare the next two figures. This figure shows a
				region with three data stores and seven buckets. If all the entries are accessed at
				about the same rate, this configuration creates a hot spot in member M3, which has
				about fifty percent more data than the other data stores. M3 is likely to be a slow
				receiver and potential point of failure. </p>
			<p>
				<image placement="break" id="image_04B05CE3C732430C84D967A062D9EDDA"
					href="../../images_svg/partitioned_data_buckets_1.svg"/>
			</p>
			<p>Configuring more buckets gives you fewer entries in a bucket and a more balanced data
				distribution. This figure uses the same data as before but increases the number of
				buckets to 13. Now the data entries are distributed more evenly. </p>
			<p>
				<image placement="break" id="image_326202046D07414391BA5CBA474920CA"
					href="../../images_svg/partitioned_data_buckets_2.svg"/>
			</p>
		</section>
	</conbody>
</concept>
