<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic
  id="topic_zpj_n35_yk">
  <title>Moving Partitioned Region Data to Another Member</title>
  <shortdesc>You can use the <codeph>PartitionRegionHelper</codeph>
    <codeph>moveBucketByKey</codeph> and <codeph>moveData</codeph> methods to
    explicitly move partitioned region data from one member to another. </shortdesc>
  <body>
    <p>The <codeph>moveBucketByKey</codeph> method moves the bucket that
      contains the specified key from a source member to a destination member.
      For example, you could use the method to move a popular product item to a
      new, empty member to reduce load on the source member.</p>
    <p>For
      example:<codeblock>Object product = ...
Region r = ...
DistributedSystem ds = ...
String memberName = ...

//Find the member that is currently hosting the product.
Set&lt;DistributedMember> sourceMembers =
PartitionRegionHelper.getAllMembersForKey(r, product);

//Find the member to move the product to.
DistributedMember destination = ds.findDistributedMember(memberName);

//In this example we assume there is always at least one source.
//In practice, you should check that at least one source
//for the data is available.
source = sourceMembers.iterator().next();

//Move the bucket to the new node. The bucket will
//be moved when this method completes. It throws an exception
//if there is a problem or invalid arguments.
PartitionRegionHelper.moveBucketByKey(r, source, destination, product);</codeblock>See
      the Java API documentation for
        <codeph>com.gemstone.gemfire.cache.partition.PartitionRegionHelper.moveBucketByKey</codeph>
      for more details.</p>
    <p>The <codeph>moveData</codeph> method moves data up to a given percentage
      (measured in bytes) from a source member to a destination member. For
      example, you could use this method to move a specified percentage of data
      from an overloaded member to another member to improve distribution. </p>
    <p>For
      example:<codeblock>Region r = ...
DistributedSystem ds = ...
String sourceName = ...
String destName = ...

//Find the source member.
DistributedMember source = ds.findDistributedMember(sourceName);
DistributedMember destination = ds.findDistributedMember(destName);

//Move up to 20% of the data from the source to the destination node.
PartitionRegionHelper.moveData(r, source, destination, 20);</codeblock>See
      the Java API documentation for
        <codeph>com.gemstone.gemfire.cache.partition.PartitionRegionHelper.moveData</codeph>
      for more details.</p>
    <p>For more information on partitioned regions and rebalancing, see <xref
        href="../partitioned_regions/chapter_overview.xml">Partitioned
        Regions</xref>.</p>
  </body>
</topic>
