<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE concept PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN" "concept.dtd">
<concept id="concept_3B5E445B19884680900161BDF25E32C9">
	<title>About <keyword keyref="product_name_long"/></title>
	<shortdesc id="shortdesc_DABFF8298A6B400C8C49EFA91A20BA98"><keyword keyref="product_name_long"/>
		is a data management platform that provides real-time, consistent access to data-intensive
		applications throughout widely distributed cloud architectures. </shortdesc>
	<conbody>
		<section id="section_itx_b41_mr">
			<p><keyword keyref="product_name"/> pools memory, CPU, network resources, and optionally
				local disk across multiple processes to manage application objects and behavior. It
				uses dynamic replication and data partitioning techniques to implement high
				availability, improved performance, scalability, and fault tolerance. In addition to
				being a distributed data container, <keyword keyref="product_name"/> is an in-memory
				data management system that provides reliable asynchronous event notifications and
				guaranteed message delivery. </p>
		</section>
		<section id="section_0031B81824874FC18F0828DB66150833">
			<title>Main Concepts and Components</title>
			<p><i>Caches</i> are an abstraction that describe a node in a <keyword
					keyref="product_name"/> distributed system. Application architects can arrange
				these nodes in peer-to-peer or client/server topologies. </p>
			<p>Within each cache, you define data <i>regions</i>. Data regions are analogous to
				tables in a relational database and manage data in a distributed fashion as
				name/value pairs. A <i>replicated</i> region stores identical copies of the data on
				each cache member of a distributed system. A <i>partitioned</i> region spreads the
				data among cache members. After the system is configured, client applications can
				access the distributed data in regions without knowledge of the underlying system
				architecture. You can define listeners to create notifications about when data has
				changed, and you can define expiration criteria to delete obsolete data in a region. </p>
			<p>For large production systems, <keyword keyref="product_name"/> provides
					<i>locators</i>. Locators provide both discovery and load balancing services.
				You configure clients with a list of locator services and the locators maintain a
				dynamic list of member servers. By default, <keyword keyref="product_name"/> clients
				and servers use port 40404 and multicast to discover each other. </p>
		</section>
		<section id="section_zrl_c41_mr">
			<p>For more information on product features, see <xref
					href="product_intro.xml"/>. </p>
		</section>
	</conbody>
</concept>
