<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE concept PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN" "http://docs.oasis-open.org/dita/v1.1/OS/dtd/concept.dtd">
<concept id="backup_restore_disk_store">
	<title>Creating Backups for System Recovery and Operational Management</title>
	<shortdesc>A backup is a copy of persisted data from a disk store. A backup is used to restore the
		disk store to the state it was in when the backup was made. The appropriate back up and
		restore procedures differ based upon whether the distributed system is online or offline. An
		online system has currently running members. An offline system does not have any running
		members.</shortdesc>
	<conbody>
		<ul id="ul_846C3274F78048BDA87AEFB1C7BDB80C">
			<li id="li_F44346175E244C1897CD1EEDB64ED25D">
				<xref
					href="backup_restore_disk_store.xml#backup_restore_disk_store/section_63AB5917BF24432898A79DBE8E4071FF"
					type="section" format="dita" scope="local"/></li>
			<li id="li_460B36BA05A34105A1ACBFEAAF50542A">
				<xref
					href="backup_restore_disk_store.xml#backup_restore_disk_store/section_C08E52E65DAD4CD5AE076BBDCF1DB340"
					type="section" format="dita" scope="local"/>
			</li>
			<li id="li_1E254E660FB748E5B3FC51D6D392E2E0">
				<xref
					href="backup_restore_disk_store.xml#backup_restore_disk_store/section_59E23EEA4AB24374A45B99A8B44FD49B"
					type="section" format="dita" scope="local"/>
			</li>
			<li id="li_562F49A71472451BBFD4030934188D5E">
				<xref
					href="backup_restore_disk_store.xml#backup_restore_disk_store/section_22809A237A344015B40C962B704D8F34"
					type="section" format="dita" scope="local"/>
			</li>
			<li id="li_CB907E6965A94A259C1341BC65FEDBE5">
				<xref
					href="backup_restore_disk_store.xml#backup_restore_disk_store/section_6F998080AF7640D1A9E951D155A75E3A"
					type="section" format="dita" scope="local"/>
			</li>
			<li id="li_676A3AD6A48E4D0688ED792369CC6A8C">
				<xref
					href="backup_restore_disk_store.xml#backup_restore_disk_store/section_D08DC489B9D947DE97B8F96261E4A977"
					type="section" format="dita" scope="local"/>
			</li>
		</ul>
		<section id="section_63AB5917BF24432898A79DBE8E4071FF">
			<title>Making a Backup While the System Is Online</title>
			<p>The gfsh command <codeph>backup disk-store</codeph> creates a backup of the disk
				stores for all members running in the distributed system. The backup works by
				passing commands to the running system members; therefore, the members need to be
				online for this operation to succeed. Each member with persistent data creates a
				backup of its own configuration and disk stores. The backup does not block any
				activities within the distributed system, but it does use resources. </p>
			<note>Do not
					try to create backup files from a running system by using your operating
					system's file copy commands. This would create incomplete and unusable copies.
				</note>
			<p>
				<b>Preparing to Make a Backup</b></p>
				<ul id="ul_s5w_wsz_pt">
					<li>Consider compacting your disk store before making a backup. If
						auto-compaction is turned off, you may want to do a manual compaction to
						save on the quantity of data copied over the network by the backup. For more
						information on configuring a manual compaction, see <xref scope="local"
							href="compacting_disk_stores.xml#compacting_disk_stores/li_63CF8C35153D4173AADF7DC35FEC61F9"
							type="li" format="dita">Manual Compaction</xref>. </li>
					<li>Run the backup during a period of low activity in your system. The backup
						does not block system activities, but it uses file system resources on all
						hosts in your distributed system, and it can affect performance.</li>
					<li>Configure each member with any additional files or directories to be backed
						up by modifying the member's <codeph>cache.xml</codeph> file. Additional
						items that ought to be included in the backup:<ul id="ul_hhs_ctz_pt">
							<li>application jar files </li>
							<li>other files that the application needs when starting, such as a file
								that sets the classpath </li>
						</ul>For example, to include file <codeph>myExtraBackupStuff</codeph> in the
						backup, the <codeph>cache.xml</codeph> file specification of the data store
						would include:
						<codeblock>&lt;backup&gt;./myExtraBackupStuff&lt;/backup&gt;</codeblock>
						Directories are recursively copied, with any disk stores that are found
						excluded from this user-specified backup.</li>
					<li>Back up to a SAN (recommended) or to a directory that all members can
						access. Make sure the directory exists and has the proper permissions for
						all members to write to the directory and create subdirectories. <p>The
							directory specified for the backup can be used multiple times. Each time
							a backup is made, a new subdirectory is created within the specified
							directory, and that new subdirectory's name represents the date and
							time. </p>
						<p>You can use one of two locations for the backup: </p>
							<ul id="ul_qmg_3tz_pt">
								<li>a single physical location, such as a network file server, for
									example:
									<codeblock>/export/fileServerDirectory/gemfireBackupLocation</codeblock>
								</li>
								<li>a directory that is local to all host machines in the system,
									for example: <codeblock>./gemfireBackupLocation</codeblock>
								</li>
							</ul>
						</li>
					<li>Make sure all members with persistent data are running in the system, because offline
						members cannot back up their disk stores. Output from the backup command
						will not identify members hosting replicated regions that are offline.</li>
				</ul>
			<p>
				<b>How to Do a Full Online Backup</b></p>
				<ol id="ol_870E3FACA7FC4DCE9D517FE542847CFC">
					<li id="li_5DD5496960ED444C92D3AA7C17E06057">If auto-compaction is disabled, and
						manual compaction is needed:
						<codeblock>gfsh&gt;compact disk-store --name=Disk1</codeblock>
					</li>
					<li id="li_AD066159054B443BA4D4CBD7743F6AFA">Run the <codeph>gfsh backup
							disk-store</codeph> command, specifying the backup directory location.
						For example: <codeblock>gfsh&gt;backup disk-store --dir=/export/fileServerDirectory/gemfireBackupLocation</codeblock>
						<p>The output will list information for each member that has successfully
							backed up disk stores.  The tabular information will contain the
							member's name, its UUID, the directory backed up, and the host name of
							the member.  </p><p>Any online member that fails to complete its backup
							will leave a file named <codeph>INCOMPLETE_BACKUP</codeph> in its
							highest level backup directory. The existence of this file identifies
							that the backup file contains only a partial backup, and it cannot be
							used in a restore operation.</p></li>
					<li id="li_5215F6C4360B4F6FBCAB5E9D115B0CE4">Validate the backup for later
						recovery use. On the command line, each backup can be checked with commands
						such as
						<codeblock>cd 2010-04-10-11-35/straw_14871_53406_34322/diskstores/ds1
gfsh validate offline-disk-store --name=ds1 --disk-dirs=/home/dsmith/dir1</codeblock></li>
				</ol>
			<p>
				<b>How to Do an Incremental Backup</b>
			</p>
			<p>An incremental backup contains items that have changed since a previous backup was
				made.</p>
			<p>To do an incremental backup, specify the backup directory that the incremental backup
				will be based upon with the <codeph>--baseline-dir</codeph> argument. For example:</p>
				<codeblock>gfsh&gt;backup disk-store --dir=/export/fileServerDirectory/gemfireBackupLocation
--baseline-dir=/export/fileServerDirectory/gemfireBackupLocation/2012-10-01-12-30</codeblock>
			<p>The output will appear the same as the  output for a full online backup.</p>
			<p>Any online member that fails to complete its incremental backup will leave a file
				named <codeph>INCOMPLETE_BACKUP</codeph> in its highest level backup directory. The
				existence of this file identifies that the backup file contains only a partial
				backup, and it cannot be used in a restore operation. The next time a backup is
				made, a full backup will be made. </p>
		</section>
		<section id="section_C08E52E65DAD4CD5AE076BBDCF1DB340">
			<title>What a Full Online Backup Saves</title>
			<p>For each member with persistent data, a full backup includes the following:</p>
				<ul
					id="ul_E08684424FA84732AA61C7C981288D26">
					<li id="li_089BCC632AD1420183B346A3B6A28682">Disk store files for all members
						containing persistent region data. </li>
					<li id="li_9439844AEB85456F8DF18381C89B08FE">Files and directories specified  in
						the <codeph>cache.xml</codeph> configuration file as
							<codeph>&lt;backup&gt;</codeph> elements. For example:
						<codeblock>&lt;backup&gt;./systemConfig/gf.jar&lt;/backup&gt;
&lt;backup&gt;/users/user/gfSystemInfo/myCustomerConfig.doc&lt;/backup&gt;</codeblock>
					</li>
					<li id="li_5C0E32CB0B8F476E9691C54335BF625F">Deployed JAR files that were
						deployed using the gfsh <xref
							href="../../tools_modules/gfsh/command-pages/deploy.xml" type="concept"
							format="dita" scope="local">deploy</xref> command. </li>
					<li id="li_6121E8AF44F7467AB05494A41339F1D6">Configuration files from the member
						startup. <ul id="ul_743FF442E72540C681CA607358114D97">
							<li id="li_4C42D24269454181A5423DA3BD2AC554"
									><codeph>gemfire.properties</codeph>, including the properties
								with which the member was started. </li>
							<li id="li_03E2508C5EB243E6A3FEB39DA30C8D57"><codeph>cache.xml</codeph>,
								if used. </li>
						</ul>These configuration files are not automatically restored, to avoid
						interfering with more recent configurations. In particular, if these are
						extracted from a master <codeph>jar</codeph> file, copying the separate
						files into your working area can override the files in the
							<codeph>jar</codeph>. If you want to back up and restore these files,
						add them as custom <codeph>&lt;backup&gt;</codeph> elements. </li>
					<li id="li_A49BCC861F9E46CE92AA94C6530C04DC">A restore script, called
							<codeph>restore.bat</codeph> on Windows, and called
							<codeph>restore.sh</codeph> on Linux. This script may later be used to
						do a restore. The script copies files back to their original locations.
					</li>
				</ul>
		</section>
		<section id="section_59E23EEA4AB24374A45B99A8B44FD49B">
			<title>What an Incremental Online Backup Saves</title>
			<p>An incremental backup saves the difference between the last backup and the current
				data. An incremental backup copies only operations logs that are not already present
				in the baseline directories for each member. For incremental backups, the restore
				script contains explicit references to operation logs in one or more previously
				chained incremental backups. When the restore script is run from an incremental
				backup, it also restores the operation logs from previous incremental backups that
				are part of the backup chain. </p>
			<p>If members are missing from the baseline directory because they were offline or did
				not exist at the time of the baseline backup, those members place full backups of
				all their files into the incremental backup directory. </p>
		</section>
		<section id="section_22809A237A344015B40C962B704D8F34">
			<title>Disk Store Backup Directory Structure and Contents</title>
				<codeblock>$ cd thebackupdir
$ ls -R
./2012-10-18-13-44-53:
dasmith_e6410_server1_8623_v1_33892 dasmith_e6410_server2_8940_v2_45565

./2012-10-18-13-44-53/dasmith_e6410_server1_8623_v1_33892:
config diskstores README.txt restore.sh user

./2012-10-18-13-44-53/dasmith_e6410_server1_8623_v1_33892/config:
cache.xml

./2012-10-18-13-44-53/dasmith_e6410_server1_8623_v1_33892/diskstores:
DEFAULT

./2012-10-18-13-44-53/dasmith_e6410_server1_8623_v1_33892/diskstores/DEFAULT:
dir0

./2012-10-18-13-44-53/dasmith_e6410_server1_8623_v1_33892/diskstores/DEFAULT/dir0:
BACKUPDEFAULT_1.crf BACKUPDEFAULT_1.drf BACKUPDEFAULT.if

./2012-10-18-13-44-53/dasmith_e6410_server1_8623_v1_33892/user:</codeblock>
		</section>
		<section id="section_6F998080AF7640D1A9E951D155A75E3A">
			<title>Offline Members—Manual Catch-Up to an Online Backup</title>
			<p>If you must have a member offline during an online backup, you can manually back up
				its disk stores. Bring this member’s files into the online backup framework
				manually, and create a restore script by hand starting with a copy of another
				member’s script: </p>
			<ol id="ol_of4_4qz_pt">
				<li>Duplicate the directory structure of a backed up member for this member. </li>
				<li>Rename directories as needed to reflect this member’s particular backup,
					including disk store names. </li>
				<li>Clear out all files other than the restore script. </li>
				<li>Copy in this member’s files. </li>
				<li>Modify the restore script to work for this member. </li>
			</ol>
		</section>
		<section id="section_D08DC489B9D947DE97B8F96261E4A977">
			<title>Restore Using a Backup Made While the System Was Online</title>
			<p>The <codeph>restore.sh</codeph> or <codeph>restore.bat</codeph> script copies files
				back to their original locations. </p>
				<ol id="ol_AAE417692C3745FEA7E8D83F2A88D135">
					<li id="li_79408F8EEFC342DE82CEB5D53093438F">Restore your disk stores while
						cache members are offline and the system is down. </li>
					<li id="li_8FA1C0BCCE2748F4ACDA8CA1B9346863">Look at each of the restore scripts
						to see where they will place the files and make sure the destination
						locations are ready. A restore script will refuse to copy over files with
						the same names. </li>
					<li id="li_8B059003024241F1B2293C4A43372F59">Run each restore script on the host
						where the backup originated. </li>
				</ol>
			<p>The restore copies these files back to their original location:</p>
				<ul
					id="ul_FDE0B5475EB3404C840C8A22AAD746AC">
					<li id="li_9EF35C6DF88547BB81D4474D3DEB8EF6">Disk store files for all stores
						containing persistent region data. </li>
					<li id="li_E4C9A0F923614D5CB5093E497485AAB1">Any files or directories you have
						configured to be backed up in the <codeph>cache.xml</codeph>
						<codeph>&lt;backup&gt;</codeph> elements. </li>
				</ul>
		</section>
	</conbody>
</concept>
