<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE concept PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN" "http://docs.oasis-open.org/dita/v1.1/OS/dtd/concept.dtd">
<concept id="handling_missing_disk_stores">
	<title>Handling Missing Disk Stores</title>
	<conbody>
		<section id="section_9345819FC27E41FB94F5E54979B7C506">
			<p>This section applies to disk stores that hold the latest copy of your data for at
				least one region. </p>
		</section>
		<section id="section_9E8FBB7935F34239AD5E65A3E857EEAA">
			<title>Show Missing Disk Stores</title>
			<p>Using <codeph>gfsh</codeph>, the <codeph>show missing-disk-stores</codeph> command
				lists all disk stores with most recent data that are being waited on by other
				members. </p>
			<p>For replicated regions, this command only lists missing members that are preventing
				other members from starting up. For partitioned regions, this command also lists any
				offline data stores, even when other data stores for the region are online, because
				their offline status may be causing <codeph>PartitionOfflineExceptions</codeph> in
				cache operations or preventing the system from satisfying redundancy. </p>
			<p>Example: <codeblock>gfsh&gt;show missing-disk-stores
          Disk Store ID             |   Host    |               Directory                                           
------------------------------------ | --------- | -------------------------------------
60399215-532b-406f-b81f-9b5bd8d1b55a | excalibur | /usr/local/gemfire/deploy/disk_store1</codeblock>
				<note> You need to be connected to JMX Manager in <codeph>gfsh</codeph> to run this
					command. </note>
			</p>
			<p>
				<note>The disk store directories listed for missing disk stores may not be the
					directories you have currently configured for the member. The list is retrieved
					from the other running members—the ones who are reporting the missing member.
					They have information from the last time the missing disk store was online. If
					you move your files and change the member’s configuration, these directory
					locations will be stale. </note>
			</p>
			<p>Disk stores usually go missing because their member fails to start. The member can
				fail to start for a number of reasons, including: <ul
					id="ul_EC27DB5CA63A485DBC659078D6A48540">
					<li id="li_5EFAC1F824364D77BB7AF04CBA97EC50">Disk store file corruption. You can
						check on this by validating the disk store. </li>
					<li id="li_3FBB8BD66FC0425F9E7142BACA2FF4EF">Incorrect distributed system
						configuration for the member </li>
					<li id="li_39C9C85625A1495FA722759D04365F13">Network partitioning </li>
					<li id="li_5F0CE3F6C3834B5EB880764D4CE07140">Drive failure </li>
				</ul>
			</p>
		</section>
		<section id="section_FDF161F935054AB190D9DB0D7930CEAA">
			<title>Revoke Missing Disk Stores</title>
			<p>This section applies to disk stores for which both of the following are true: <ul
					id="ul_3990F53A29814E91BD2BB04069FCEBD3">
					<li id="li_C4CF0C4461CA4493907CEFE3C532D8F5">Disk stores that have the most
						recent copy of data for one or more regions or region buckets. </li>
					<li id="li_11A2EDAB88854F85A4D85F831D95B942">Disk stores that are unrecoverable,
						such as when you have deleted them, or their files are corrupted or on a
						disk that has had a catastrophic failure. </li>
				</ul>
			</p>
			<p>When you cannot bring the latest persisted copy online, use the revoke command to
				tell the other members to stop waiting for it. Once the store is revoked, the system
				finds the remaining most recent copy of data and uses that. </p>
			<note>Once revoked, a disk store cannot be reintroduced into the system. </note>
			<p>Use gfsh show missing-disk-stores to properly identify the disk store you need to
				revoke. The revoke command takes the disk store ID as input, as listed by that
				command. </p>
			<p>Example:
				<codeblock>gfsh&gt;revoke missing-disk-store --id=60399215-532b-406f-b81f-9b5bd8d1b55a
Missing disk store successfully revoked</codeblock>
			</p>
			<p> </p>
		</section>
	</conbody>
</concept>
