<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE concept PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN" "http://docs.oasis-open.org/dita/v1.1/OS/dtd/concept.dtd">
<concept id="syncing_offline_disk_store">
	<title>Keeping a Disk Store Synchronized with the Cache</title>
	<conbody>
		<section id="section_7D01550D750E48289EFBA9BBDB5A334E">
			<p>You can take several actions to optimize disk store use and data loading at startup.
			</p>
		</section>
		<section id="section_7B95B20F07BD40699CDB7F3D6A93B905">
			<title>Change Region Configuration</title>
			<p>When your disk store is offline, you can keep the configuration for its regions
				up-to-date with your <codeph>cache.xml</codeph> and API settings. The disk store
				retains region capacity and load settings, including entry map settings (initial
				capacity, concurrency level, load factor), LRU eviction settings, and the statistics
				enabled boolean. If the configurations do not match at startup, the
					<codeph>cache.xml</codeph> and API override any disk store settings and the disk
				store is automatically updated to match. So you do not need to modify your disk
				store to keep your cache configuration and disk store synchronized, but you will
				save startup time and memory if you do. </p>
			<p>For example, to change the initial capacity of the disk store:
				<codeblock>gfsh&gt;alter disk-store --name=myDiskStoreName --region=partitioned_region 
--disk-dirs=/firstDiskStoreDir,/secondDiskStoreDir,/thirdDiskStoreDir 
--initialCapacity=20</codeblock>
			</p>
			<p>To list all modifiable settings and their current values for a region, run the command with no
				actions specified:
				<codeblock>gfsh&gt;alter disk-store --name=myDiskStoreName --region=partitioned_region
--disk-dirs=/firstDiskStoreDir,/secondDiskStoreDir,/thirdDiskStoreDir  </codeblock></p>
		</section>
		<section id="section_0CA17ED106394686A1A5B30601758DA6">
			<title>Take a Region Out of Your Cache Configuration and Disk Store</title>
			<p>You might remove a region from your application if you decide to rename it or to
				split its data into two entirely different regions. Any significant data
				restructuring can cause you to retire some data regions. </p>
			<p>This applies to the removal of regions while the disk store is offline. Regions you destroy
				through API calls or by <codeph>gfsh</codeph> are automatically removed from the
				disk store of online members. </p>
			<p>In your application development, when you discontinue use of a persistent region, remove the
				region from the member’s disk store as well. </p>
			<note>Perform the following operations with caution. You are permanently removing data. </note>
			<p>You can remove the region from the disk store in one of two ways: </p>
				<ul
					id="ul_9BAB7856F25F4848867C3401D71DD3C0">
					<li id="li_C015576E1DE746DBB056EB9B752D0B96">Delete the entire set of disk store
						files. Your member will initialize with an empty set of files the next time
						you and start it. Exercise caution when removing the files from the file
						system, as more than one region can be specified to use the same disk store
						directories. </li>
					<li id="li_2392081C6A004D46A14D124C551BFC53">Selectively remove the discontinued
						region from the disk store with a command such
						as:<codeblock>gfsh&gt;alter disk-store --name=myDiskStoreName --region=partitioned_region
--disk-dirs=/firstDiskStoreDir,/secondDiskStoreDir,/thirdDiskStoreDir --remove</codeblock>
					</li>
				</ul>
			<p>To guard against unintended data loss, <keyword keyref="product_name"/> maintains the
				region in the disk store until you manually remove it. Regions in the disk stores
				that are not associated with any region in your application are still loaded into
				temporary regions in memory and kept there for the life of the member. The system
				has no way of detecting whether the cache region will be created by your API at some
				point, so it keeps the temporary region loaded and available. </p>
		</section>
	</conbody>
</concept>
