<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE concept PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN" "http://docs.oasis-open.org/dita/v1.1/OS/dtd/concept.dtd">
<concept id="how_data_loaders_work">
	<title>How Data Loaders Work</title>
	<shortdesc>By default, a region has no data loader defined. Plug an application-defined loader
		into any region by setting the region attribute cache-loader on the members that host data
		for the region. </shortdesc>
	<conbody>
		<section id="section_1E600469D223498DB49446434CE9B0B4">
			<p>The loader is called on cache misses during get operations, and it populates the
				cache with the new entry value in addition to returning the value to the calling
				thread. </p>
			<p>A loader can be configured to load data into the <keyword keyref="product_name"/>
				cache from an outside data store. To do the reverse operation, writing data from the
					<keyword keyref="product_name"/> cache to an outside data store, use a cache
				writer event handler. See <xref
					href="../events/implementing_cache_event_handlers.xml#implementing_cache_event_handlers"
					type="concept" format="dita" scope="local"/>. </p>
			<p>How to install your cache loader depends on the type of region. </p>
		</section>
		<section id="section_5CD65D559F1A490DAB5ED9326860FE8D">
			<title>Data Loading in Partitioned Regions</title>
			<p>Because of the huge amounts of data they can handle, partitioned regions support
				partitioned loading. Each cache loader loads only the data entries in the member
				where the loader is defined. If data redundancy is configured, data is loaded only
				if the member holds the primary copy. So you must install a cache loader in every
				member where the partitioned attributes <codeph>local-max-memory</codeph> is not
				zero. </p>
			<p>If you depend on a JDBC connection, every data store must have a connection to the
				data source, as shown in the following figure. Here the three members require three
				connections. See <xref
					href="../transactions/configuring_db_connections_using_JNDI.xml#topic_A5E3A67C808D48C08E1F0DC167C5C494"
					type="topic" format="dita" scope="local"/> for information on how to configure
				data sources. </p>
			<note>Partitioned regions generally require more JDBC connections than distributed
				regions. </note>
			<p>
				<image placement="break" id="image_CD7CE9BD22ED4782AB6B296187AB983A"
					href="../../images_svg/cache_data_loader.svg"/>
			</p>
		</section>
		<section id="section_6A2CE777CE9E4BD682B881F6986CF66C">
			<title>Data Loading in Distributed Regions</title>
			<p>In a non-partitioned distributed region, a cache loader defined in one member is
				available to all members that have the region defined. Loaders are usually defined
				in just a subset of the caches holding the region. When a loader is needed, all
				available loaders for the region are invoked, starting with the most convenient
				loader, until the data is loaded or all loaders have been tried. </p>
			<p>In the following figure, these members of one distributed system can be running on
				different machines. Loading for the distributed region is performed from M1. </p>
			<p>
				<image placement="break" id="image_3C39A50218D64EF28A5448EB01A4C6EC"
					href="../../images_svg/cache_data_loader_2.svg"/>
			</p>
		</section>
		<section id="section_BE33D9AB27104D1BB8AC8BFCE11A063E">
			<title>Data Loading in Local Regions</title>
			<p>For local regions, the cache loader is available only in the member where it is
				defined. If a loader is defined, it is called whenever a value is not found in the
				local cache. </p>
		</section>
	</conbody>
</concept>
