<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE dita PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Composite//EN" "ditabase.dtd">
<dita>
	<topic id="topic_686158E9AFBD47518BE1B4BEB232C190">
		<title>Starting a JMX Manager</title>
		<body>
			<p>JMX Manager nodes are members that manage other <keyword keyref="product_name"/>
				members (as well as themselves). A JMX Manager node can manage all other members in
				the distributed system. Typically a locator will function as the JMX Manager, but
				you can also turn any other distributed system member such as a server into a JMX
				Manager node as well. </p>
			<p>To allow a server to become a JMX Manager you configure <keyword
					keyref="product_name"/> property <codeph>jmx-manager=true</codeph>, in the
					server's<codeph>gemfire.properties</codeph> file. This property configures the
				node to become a JMX Manager node passively; if gfsh cannot locate a JMX Manager
				when connecting to the distributed system, the server node will be started as a JMX
				Manager node. </p>
			<note>The default property setting for all locators is
					<codeph>gemfire.jmx-manager=true</codeph>. For other members, the default
				property setting is <codeph>gemfire.jmx-manager=false</codeph>. </note>
			<p>To force a server to become a JMX Manager node whenever it is started, set the
					<keyword keyref="product_name"/> properties
					<codeph>jmx-manager-start=true</codeph> and <codeph>jmx-manager=true</codeph> in
				the server's gemfire.properties file. Note that both of these properties must be set
				to true for the node. </p>
			<p>To start the member as a JMX Manager node on the command line, provide<codeph>
					--J=-Dgemfire.jmx-manager-start=true and --J=-Dgemfire.jmx-manager=true</codeph>
				as arguments to either the <codeph>start server</codeph> or <codeph>start
					locator</codeph> command. </p>
			<p>For example, to start a server as a JMX Manager on the gfsh command line:
				<codeblock>gfsh&gt;start server --name=&lt;<varname>server-name</varname>&gt; --J=-Dgemfire.jmx-manager=true \
--J=-Dgemfire.jmx-manager-start=true</codeblock>By
				default, any locator can become a JMX Manager when started. When you start up a
				locator, if no other JMX Manager is detected in the distributed system, the locator
				starts one automatically. If you start a second locator, it will detect the current
				JMX Manager and will not start up another JMX Manager unless the second locator's
					<codeph>gemfire.jmx-manager-start</codeph> property is set to true. </p>
			<p>For most deployments, you only need to have one JMX Manager per distributed system.
				However, you can run more than JMX Manager if necessary. If you want to provide
				high-availability and redundancy for the Pulse monitoring tool, or if you are
				running additional JMX clients other than gfsh, then use the
					<codeph>jmx-manager-start=true</codeph> property to force individual nodes
				(either locators or servers) to become JMX Managers at startup. Since there is some
				performance overhead to being a JMX Manager, we recommend using locators as JMX
				Managers. If you do not want a locator to become a JMX manager, then you must use
				the <codeph>jmx-manager=false</codeph> property when you start the locator.</p>
			<p>See <xref
					href="../../tools_modules/gfsh/command-pages/start.xml#topic_3764EE2DB18B4AE4A625E0354471738A"
					type="topic" format="dita" scope="local"><?xm-replace_text start server?></xref>
				and <xref
					href="../../tools_modules/gfsh/command-pages/start.xml#topic_591260CF25D64562A0EDD7260D2AC6D4"
					type="topic" format="dita" scope="local"
					><?xm-replace_text start locator?></xref> for more details. </p>
			<p>After the node becomes a JMX Manager, all other <codeph>jmx-manager-*</codeph>
				configuration properties listed in <xref scope="local"
					href="jmx_manager_operations.xml#topic_263072624B8D4CDBAD18B82E07AA44B6"
					type="topic" format="dita"><?xm-replace_text Configuring a JMX Manager?></xref>
				are applied. </p>
			<p>The following is an example of starting a new locator that also starts an embedded
				JMX Manager (after detecting that another JMX Manager does not exist). In addition,
					<codeph>gfsh</codeph> also automatically connects you to the new JMX Manager.
				For example:
				<codeblock>gfsh>start locator --name=locator1
Starting a GemFire Locator in /home/stymon/test2/locator1...
............................................
Locator in /home/stymon/test2/locator1 on ubuntu.local[10334] as locator1 is currently online.
Process ID: 2081
Uptime: 30 seconds
GemFire Version: 8.0.0
Java Version: 1.7.0_65
Log File: /home/stymon/test2/locator1/locator1.log
JVM Arguments: -Dgemfire.enable-cluster-configuration=true -Dgemfire.load-cluster-configuration-from-dir=false
-Dgemfire.launcher.registerSignalHandlers=true -Djava.awt.headless=true -Dsun.rmi.dgc.server.gcInterval=9223372036854775806
Class-Path: /home/stymon/Pivotal_GemFire_800_b48319_Linux/lib/locator-dependencies.jar:/usr/local/java/lib/tools.jar

Successfully connected to: [host=ubuntu.local, port=1099]

Cluster configuration service is up and running.
</codeblock>
				Or you can enter the command directly in your terminal:
				<codeblock>stymon@ubuntu:~$ gfsh start locator --name=locator1
....................................
Locator in /home/stymon/locator1 on ubuntu.local[10334] as locator1 is currently online.
Process ID: 2359
Uptime: 21 seconds
GemFire Version: 8.0.0
Java Version: 1.7.0_65
Log File: /home/stymon/locator1/locator1.log
JVM Arguments: -Dgemfire.enable-cluster-configuration=true -Dgemfire.load-cluster-configuration-from-dir=false
 -Dgemfire.launcher.registerSignalHandlers=true -Djava.awt.headless=true -Dsun.rmi.dgc.server.gcInterval=9223372036854775806
Class-Path: /home/stymon/Pivotal_GemFire_800_b48319_Linux/lib/locator-dependencies.jar:/usr/local/java/lib/tools.jar

Successfully connected to: [host=ubuntu.local, port=1099]

Cluster configuration service is up and running.
</codeblock>Locators
				also keep track of all nodes that can become a JMX Manager. </p>
			<p>Immediately after creating its cache, the JMX Manager node begins federating the
				MBeans from other members. After the JMX Manager node is ready, the JMX Manager node
				sends a notification to all other members informing them that it is a new JMX
				Manager. The other members then put complete MBean states for themselves into each
				of their hidden management regions. </p>
			<p>At any point, you can determine whether a node is a JMX Manager by using the
				MemberMXBean isManager() method. </p>
			<p>Using the Java API, any managed node that has been configured with
					<codeph>jmx-manager=true</codeph> can also be turned into a JMX Manager Node by
				invoking the ManagementService startManager() method. <note>If you start the JMX
					Manager programmatically and wish to enable command processing, you must also
					add the absolute path of <codeph>gfsh-dependencies.jar</codeph> (located in
						<codeph>$GEMFIRE/lib</codeph> of your <keyword keyref="product_name"/>
					installation) to the CLASSPATH of your application. Do not copy this library to
					your CLASSPATH because this library refers to other dependencies in
						<codeph>$GEMFIRE/lib</codeph> by a relative path. </note></p>
		</body>
	</topic>
	<topic id="topic_263072624B8D4CDBAD18B82E07AA44B6">
		<title>Configuring a JMX Manager</title>
		<body>
			<p>In the <codeph>gemfire.properties</codeph> file, you configure a JMX manager as
				follows. </p>
			<table id="table_A413B5E4AA0E4B509042E40FA27DC920">
				<tgroup cols="3">
					<colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="1.43*"/>
					<colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="3.41*"/>
					<colspec colname="3" colnum="3" colwidth="1.00*"/>
					<thead>
						<row>
							<entry colname="1">Property </entry>
							<entry colname="2">Description </entry>
							<entry colname="3">Default </entry>
						</row>
					</thead>
					<tbody>
						<row>
							<entry colname="1">http-service-port </entry>
							<entry colname="2">If non-zero, then <keyword keyref="product_name"/>
								starts an embedded HTTP service that listens on this port. The HTTP
								service is used to host the <keyword keyref="product_name"/> Pulse
								Web application. If you are hosting the Pulse web app on your own
								Web server, then disable this embedded HTTP service by setting this
								property to zero. Ignored if <codeph>jmx-manager</codeph> is false. </entry>
							<entry colname="3">7070 </entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>http-service-bind-address</entry>
							<entry>If set, then the <keyword keyref="product_name"/> member binds
								the embedded HTTP service to the specified address. If this property
								is not set but the HTTP service is enabled using
									<codeph>http-service-port</codeph>, then <keyword
									keyref="product_name"/> binds the HTTP service to the member's
								local address.</entry>
							<entry><i>not set</i>
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry colname="1">jmx-manager </entry>
							<entry colname="2">
								<p>If <codeph>true</codeph> then this member can become a JMX
									Manager. All other <codeph>jmx-manager-*</codeph> properties are
									used when it does become a JMX Manager. If this property is
									false then all other <codeph>jmx-manager-*</codeph> properties
									are ignored. </p>
								<p>The default value is <codeph>true</codeph> on locators. </p>
							</entry>
							<entry colname="3">false (with Locator exception) </entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry colname="1">jmx-manager-access-file </entry>
							<entry colname="2">
								<p>By default the JMX Manager allows full access to all MBeans by
									any client. If this property is set to the name of a file, then
									it can restrict clients to only reading MBeans; they cannot
									modify MBeans. The access level can be configured differently in
									this file for each user name defined in the password file. For
									more information about the format of this file see Oracle's
									documentation of the
										<codeph>com.sun.management.jmxremote.access.file</codeph>
									system property. Ignored if <codeph>jmx-manager</codeph> is
									false or if <codeph>jmx-manager-port</codeph> is zero. See <xref
										href="../security/management_system_jmx_authentication.xml#topic_06B28974C3D34C019418C92B1FC189C8"
										type="topic" format="dita" scope="local"/> for more
									information. </p>
							</entry>
							<entry colname="3"><i>not set</i>
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry colname="1">jmx-manager-bind-address </entry>
							<entry colname="2"> By default, the JMX Manager when configured with a
								port listens on all the local host's addresses. You can use this
								property to configure which particular IP address or host name the
								JMX Manager will listen on. This property is ignored if
									<codeph>jmx-manager</codeph> is false or
									<codeph>jmx-manager-port</codeph> is zero. This address also
								applies to the <keyword keyref="product_name"/> Pulse server if you
								are hosting a Pulse web application. </entry>
							<entry colname="3"><i>not set</i>
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry colname="1">jmx-manager-hostname-for-clients </entry>
							<entry colname="2">Hostname given to clients that ask the locator for
								the location of a JMX Manager. By default the IP address of the JMX
								Manager is used. However, for clients on a different network, you
								can configure a different hostname to be given to clients. Ignored
								if <codeph>jmx-manager</codeph> is false or if
									<codeph>jmx-manager-port</codeph> is zero. </entry>
							<entry colname="3"><i>not set</i>
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry colname="1">jmx-manager-password-file </entry>
							<entry colname="2">By default the JMX Manager allows clients without
								credentials to connect. If this property is set to the name of a
								file, only clients that connect with credentials that match an entry
								in this file will be allowed. Most JVMs require that the file is
								only readable by the owner. For more information about the format of
								this file see Oracle's documentation of the
								com.sun.management.jmxremote.password.file system property. Ignored
								if jmx-manager is false or if jmx-manager-port is zero.See <xref
									href="../security/management_system_jmx_authentication.xml#topic_06B28974C3D34C019418C92B1FC189C8"
									type="topic" format="dita" scope="local"/> for more information. </entry>
							<entry colname="3"><i>not set</i>
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry colname="1">jmx-manager-port </entry>
							<entry colname="2">Port on which this JMX Manager listens for client
								connections. If this property is set to zero, <keyword
									keyref="product_name"/> does not allow remote client
								connections. Alternatively, use the standard system properties
								supported by the JVM for configuring access from remote JMX clients.
								Ignored if jmx-manager is false. The Default RMI port is 1099. </entry>
							<entry colname="3">1099 </entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry colname="1">jmx-manager-ssl </entry>
							<entry colname="2">If true and <codeph>jmx-manager-port</codeph> is not
								zero, the JMX Manager accepts only SSL connections. The ssl-enabled
								property does not apply to the JMX Manager, but the other SSL
								properties do. This allows SSL to be configured for just the JMX
								Manager without needing to configure it for the other <keyword
									keyref="product_name"/> connections. Ignored if
									<codeph>jmx-manager</codeph> is false. </entry>
							<entry colname="3">false </entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry colname="1">jmx-manager-start </entry>
							<entry colname="2"> If true, this member starts a JMX Manager when it
								creates a cache. In most cases you should not set this property to
								true because a JMX Manager is automatically started when needed on a
								member that sets <codeph>jmx-manager</codeph> to true. Ignored if
								jmx-manager is false. </entry>
							<entry colname="3">false </entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry colname="1">jmx-manager-update-rate </entry>
							<entry colname="2">The rate, in milliseconds, at which this member
								pushes updates to any JMX Managers. Currently this value should be
								greater than or equal to the <codeph>statistic-sample-rate</codeph>.
								Setting this value too high causes <codeph>gfsh</codeph> and
									<keyword keyref="product_name"/> Pulse to see stale values. </entry>
							<entry colname="3">2000 </entry>
						</row>
					</tbody>
				</tgroup>
			</table>
		</body>
	</topic>
	<topic id="topic_5B6DF783A14241399DC25C6EE8D0048A">
		<title>Stopping a JMX Manager</title>
		<body>
			<p>To stop a JMX Manager using gfsh, simply shut down the locator or server hosting the
				JMX Manager. </p>
			<p>For a locator:
				<codeblock>gfsh>stop locator --dir=locator1
Stopping Locator running in /home/stymon/test2/locator1 on ubuntu.local[10334] as locator1...
Process ID: 2081
Log File: /home/stymon/test2/locator1/locator1.log
....
No longer connected to ubuntu.local[1099].
</codeblock>
				For a server:
				<codeblock>gfsh&gt;stop server --dir=server1
Stopping Cache Server running in /home/stymon/test2/server1 ubuntu.local[40404] as server1...
Process ID: 1156
Log File: /home/stymon/test2/server1/server1.log
....


No longer connected to ubuntu.local[1099].</codeblock>Notice
				that <codeph>gfsh</codeph> has automatically disconnected you from the stopped JMX
				Manager. </p>
			<p>To stop a JMX manager using the management API, use the ManagementService
				stopManager() method to stop a member from being a JMX Manager. </p>
			<p>When a Manager stops, it removes all federated MBeans from other members from its
				Platform MBeanServer. It also emits a notification to inform other members that it
				is no longer considered a JMX Manager. </p>
		</body>
	</topic>
</dita>
