<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="topic_212EE5A2ABAB4E8E8EF71807C9ECEF1A">
	<title>Notification Federation</title>
	<shortdesc> All notifications emitted from managed nodes are federated to all JMX Managers in
		the system. </shortdesc>
	<body>
		<p>These notifications are federated and then emitted by the DistributedSystemMXBean. If you
			attach a <codeph>javax.management.NotificationListener</codeph> to your
			DistributedSystemMXBean, the NotificationListener can listen to notifications from all
			MemberMXBeans and all CacheServerMXBeans. </p>
		<section id="section_2909371D90764736B3AC7BE9E4BC1BE4">
			<title> Attaching Listeners to MXBeans</title>
			<p>When you attach a notification listener to the DistributedSystemMXBean, the
				DistributedSystemMXBean then acts as the notification hub for the entire distributed
				system. You do not have to attach a listener to each individual member or cache
				server MBean in order to listen to all the notifications in the distributed system.
			</p>The following is an example of attaching a NotificationListener to an MBean using
			the JMX MBeanServer API: <codeblock>NotificationListener myListener = ...
ObjectName mbeanName = ... 
MBeanServer.addNotificationListener(mbeanName, myListener, null, null);  </codeblock>
			<p>JMX Managers will emit notifications for all distributed system members with two
				exceptions: <ul id="ul_kjn_1xw_wj">
					<li id="li_CCB2BD5C4683486294C2AD514A21C9F2">If you use cache.xml to define
						resources such as regions and disks, then notifications for these resources
						are not federated to the JMX Manager. In those cases, the
						DistributedSystemMXBean cannot emit those notifications. </li>
					<li id="li_6DB504460C284C50AF1F15ABC5C83D3A">If a JMX Manager is started after a
						resource has been created, the JMX Manager cannot emit notifications for
						that resource. </li>
				</ul>
			</p>
		</section>
		<section id="section_7463D13112D54406953416356835E290">
			<title>System Alert Notifications</title>
			<p>System alerts are <keyword keyref="product_name"/> alerts wrapped within a JMX
				notification. The JMX Manager registers itself as an alert listener with each member
				of the system, and by default, it receives all messages logged with the SEVERE alert
				level by any node in the distributed system. Consequently, the
				DistributedSystemMXBean will then emit notifications for these alerts on behalf of
				the DistributedSystem. </p>
			<p>By default, the JMX Manager registers itself to send notifications only for SEVERE
				level alerts. To change the alert level that the JMX Manager will send notifications
				for, use the <codeph>DistributedMXBean.changeAlertLevel</codeph> method. Possible
				alert levels to set are WARNING, ERROR, SEVERE, and NONE. After changing the level,
				the JMX Manager will only emit that level of log message as notifications. </p>
			<p>Notification objects include <b>type</b>, <b>source</b> and <b>message</b>
				attributes. System alerts also include the <b>userData</b> attribute. For system
				alerts, the notification object attributes correspond to the following: <ul
					id="ul_F3559BE838F74787BECE76FBD4B47C38">
					<li id="li_D7B051D19B374946A25E3413E50C92AF"><b>type</b>: system.alert </li>
					<li id="li_66DA89D71D0042FCA4A3A5EA046F9FA8"><b>source</b>: Distributed System
						ID </li>
					<li id="li_4F4C018747FC4AEA9D3C6672709A6EED"><b>message</b>: alert message </li>
					<li id="li_9F2C786A97154D07BEAB60B10B6F1E00"><b>userData</b>: name or ID of the
						member that raised the alert </li>
				</ul>
			</p>
		</section>
	</body>
</topic>
