<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE concept PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN" "concept.dtd">
<concept
	id="security">
	<title
		id="title_9717E51087B346988389138843E158C4">Modifying Query Scope </title>
	<shortdesc>The query engine resolves names and path expressions according to the name space that
		is currently in scope in the query. This is not the region scope attribute, but the scope of
		the query statement. </shortdesc>
	<conbody>
		<p>The initial name space for any query is composed of the region paths of the cache on the
			cache server and the attributes of those paths. New name spaces are brought into scope
			based on the <codeph>FROM</codeph> clause in the <codeph>SELECT</codeph> statement. For
			example, in this query the <codeph>FROM</codeph> expression evaluates to the collection
			of entry values in <codeph>/portfolios</codeph>. This 
is added to the initial scope of the query and status is
resolved within the new scope.</p>
			<codeblock>SELECT DISTINCT *
FROM /portfolios
WHERE status = 'active'</codeblock>
		<p>Each <codeph>FROM</codeph> clause expression must resolve to a collection of objects
			available for iteration in the query expressions that follow. In the example above,
				<codeph>/portfolios</codeph> resolves to the Collection of entry values in the
			region. The entry value collection is iterated by the <codeph>WHERE</codeph> clause,
			comparing the status field to the string active. When a match is found, the value object
			is added to the return set. </p>
		<p>In the following query, the collection specified in the first FROM clause expression is used by
			the second FROM clause expression and by the projections of the SELECT statement. </p>
		<codeblock>IMPORT cacheRunner.Position;
SELECT DISTINCT "type"
FROM /portfolios, positions.values posnVal TYPE Position
WHERE posnVal.qty &gt; 1000.00</codeblock>
		<note>
			<p>You cannot change the order of the expressions in this FROM clause. The second
			expression depends on the scope created by the first expression.
			</p>
		</note>
	</conbody>
</concept>
