<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE concept PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN" "concept.dtd">
<concept id="concept_ylt_2cb_y4">
  <title>Cluster Configuration Files and Troubleshooting</title>
  <shortdesc>When you use the cluster configuration service in <keyword keyref="product_name"/>, you
    can examine the generated configuration files in the <filepath>cluster_config</filepath>
    directory on the locator. gfsh saves configuration files at the cluster-level and at the
    individual group-level.</shortdesc>
  <conbody>
    <p>The following directories and configuration files are available on the locator running the
      cluster configuration service:</p>
    <parml>
      <plentry>
        <pt>Cluster-level configuration</pt>
        <pd>For configurations that apply to all members of a cluster, the locator creates a
            <filepath>cluster</filepath> subdirectory within the <filepath>cluster_config</filepath>
          directory (or in the cluster configuration directory when starting up the locator with the
              <codeph>--cluster-config-dir=<i>value</i></codeph> parameter) specified All servers
          receive this configuration when they are started using gfsh. This directory contains:<ul
            id="ul_nm3_tp5_dl">
            <li><filepath>cluster.xml</filepath> -- A <keyword keyref="product_name"/>
              <filepath>cache.xml</filepath> file containing configuration common to all
              members</li>
            <li><filepath>cluster.properties</filepath> -- a <keyword keyref="product_name"/>
              <filepath> gemfire.properties</filepath> file containing properties common to all
              members</li>
            <li>Jar files that are intended for deployment to all members</li>
          </ul></pd>
      </plentry>
    </parml>
    <parml>
      <plentry>
        <pt>Group-level configuration</pt>
        <pd>When you specify the <codeph>--group</codeph> parameter in a gfsh command, (for example,
            <codeph>start server</codeph> or <codeph>create region</codeph>) the locator writes the
          configurations for each group in a subdirectory with the same name as the group. When you
          start a server that specifies one or more group names, the server receives both the
          cluster-level configurations and the configurations from all groups specified. This
          subdirectory contains:<ul id="ul_kbc_bs5_dl">
            <li><filepath><varname>&lt;group-name></varname>.xml</filepath> -- A <keyword
                keyref="product_name_long"/>
              <filepath>cache.xml</filepath> file containing configurations common to all members of
              the group</li>
            <li><filepath><varname>&lt;group-name></varname>.properties</filepath> -- a <keyword
                keyref="product_name_long"/>
              <filepath>gemfire.properties</filepath> file containing properties common to all
              members of the group</li>
            <li>Jar files that are intended for deployment to all members of the group</li>
          </ul>
        </pd>
      </plentry>
    </parml>
    <fig id="fig_nsm_jcb_y4">
      <image href="../../images_svg/cluster-group-config.svg" id="image_bs1_mcb_y4"/>
    </fig>
    <p>You can export a zip file that contains all artifacts of a cluster configuration. The zip
      file contains all of the files in the <filepath>cluster_config</filepath> (or otherwise
      specified) subdirectory of a locator. You can import this configuration to a new cluster. See
        <xref href="export-import.xml#concept_wft_dkq_34"/>. </p>
    <section>
      <title>Individual Configuration Files and Cluster Configuration Files</title>
      <p><keyword keyref="product_name"/> applies the cluster-wide configuration files first and
        then group-level configurations next. If a member has its own configuration files defined
        (cache.xml and gemfire.properties files), those configurations are applied last. Whenever
        possible, use the member group-level configuration files in the cluster-configuration
        service to apply non-cluster-wide configurations on individual members.</p>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Troubleshooting Tips</title>
      <ul id="ul_fyr_t2p_y4">
        <li>When you start a locator using gfsh, you should see the following
            message:<codeblock>Cluster configuration service is up and running.</codeblock><p>If you
            do not see this message, there may be a problem with the cluster configuration service.
            Use the <cmdname>status cluster-configuration-service</cmdname> command to check the
            status of the cluster configuration. <ul id="ul_p4v_2hp_y4">
              <li>If the command returns <systemoutput>RUNNING</systemoutput>, the cluster
                configuration is running normally.</li>
              <li>If the command returns <systemoutput>WAITING</systemoutput>, run the
                  <cmdname>status locator</cmdname> command. The output of this command returns the
                cause of the <systemoutput>WAITING</systemoutput> status. </li>
            </ul></p></li>
        <li>If a server start fails with the following exception:
            <codeph>ClusterConfigurationNotAvailableException</codeph>, the cluster configuration
          service may not be in the <systemoutput>RUNNING</systemoutput> state. Because the server
          requests the cluster configuration from the locator, which is not available, the
            <cmdname>start server</cmdname> command fails.</li>
        <li>You can determine what configurations a server received from a locator by examining the
          server's log file. See <xref
            href="../../managing/logging/logging.xml#concept_30DB86B12B454E168B80BB5A71268865"
          />.</li>
        <li>If a <cmdname>start server</cmdname> command specifies a cache.xml file that conflicts
          with the existing cluster configuration, the server startup may fail.</li>
        <li>If a gfsh command fails because the cluster configuration cannot be saved, the following
          message
          displays:<codeblock>Failed to persist the configuration changes due to this command, 
Revert the command to maintain consistency. Please use "status cluster-config-service" 
to determine whether Cluster configuration service is RUNNING."</codeblock></li>
        <li>There are some types of configurations that cannot be made using gfsh. See <xref
            href="gfsh_persist.xml#concept_r22_hyw_bl/section_bn3_23p_y4"/>.</li>
      </ul>
    </section>
  </conbody>
</concept>
