<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE concept PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN" "concept.dtd">
<concept id="concept_r22_hyw_bl">
  <title>Overview of the Cluster Configuration Service</title>
  <shortdesc> The <keyword keyref="product_name_long"/> cluster configuration service persists
    cluster configurations created by gfsh commands to the locators in a cluster and distributes the
    configurations to members of the cluster. </shortdesc>
  <conbody>
    <section>
      <title>Why Use the Cluster Configuration Service</title>
      <p>We highly recommend that you use the <codeph>gfsh</codeph> command line and the cluster
        configuration service as the primary mechanism to manage your distributed system
        configuration. Using a common cluster configuration reduces the amount of time you spend
        configuring individual members and enforces consistent configurations when bringing up new
        members in your cluster. You no longer need to reconfigure each new member that you add to
        the cluster. You no longer need to worry about validating your cache.xml file. It also
        becomes easier to propagate configuration changes across your cluster and deploy your
        configuration changes to different environments. </p>
      <p>You can use the cluster configuration service to:</p>
      <ul id="ul_wby_qk4_kl">
        <li>Save the configuration for an entire <keyword keyref="product_name_long"/> cluster.</li>
        <li>Restart members using a previously-saved configuration.</li>
        <li>Export a configuration from a development environment and migrate that configuration to
          create a testing or production system. </li>
        <li>Start additional servers without having to configure each server separately.</li>
        <li>Configure some servers to host certain regions and other servers to host different
          regions, and configure all servers to host a set of common regions. </li>
      </ul>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Using the Cluster Configuration Service</title>
      <p>To use the cluster configuration service in <keyword keyref="product_name"/>, you must use
        dedicated, standalone locators in your deployment. You cannot use the cluster configuration
        service with co-located locators (locators running in another process such as a server) or
        in multicast environments.</p>
      <p>The standalone locators distribute configuration to all locators in a cluster. Every
        locator in the cluster with <codeph>--enable-cluster-configuration</codeph> set to true
        keeps a record of all cluster-level and group-level configuration settings. </p>
      <note>The default behavior for gfsh is to create and save cluster configurations. You can
        disable the cluster configuration service by using the
          <codeph>--enable-cluster-configuration=false</codeph> option when starting locators. </note>
      <p>Subsequently, any servers that you start with gfsh that have
          <codeph>--use-cluster-configuration</codeph> set to <codeph>true</codeph> will pick up the
        cluster configuration from the locator as well as any appropriate group-level configurations
        (for member groups they belong to). To disable the cluster configuration service on a
        server, you must start the server with the <codeph>--use-cluster-configuration</codeph>
        parameter set to <codeph>false</codeph>. By default, the parameter is set to true.</p>
      <p>You can also load existing configuration files into the cluster configuration service by
        starting up a standalone locator with the parameter
          <codeph>--load-cluster-configuration-from-dir</codeph> set to true. See <xref
          href="gfsh_load_from_shared_dir.xml"/>.</p>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>How the Cluster Configuration Service Works</title>
      <p>When you use gfsh commands to create <keyword keyref="product_name_long"/> regions,
        disk-stores, and other objects, the cluster configuration service saves the configurations
        on each locator in the cluster (also called a <keyword keyref="product_name"/> distributed
        system). If you specify a group when issuing these commands, a separate configuration is
        saved containing only configurations that apply to the group. </p>
      <p>When you use gfsh to start new <keyword keyref="product_name_long"/> servers, the locator
        distributes the persisted configurations to the new server. If you specify a group when
        starting the server, the server receives the group-level configuration in addition to the
        cluster-level configuration. Group-level configurations are applied after cluster-wide
        configurations; therefore you can use group-level to override cluster-level settings.</p>
      <image href="../../images_svg/cluster_config_overview.svg" id="image_jjc_vhb_y4"/>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>gfsh Commands that Create Cluster Configurations</title>
      <p>The following gfsh commands cause the configuration to be written to all locators in the
        cluster (the locators write the configuration to disk):</p>
      <ul id="ul_x3s_5g5_j4">
        <li><cmdname>configure pdx</cmdname>*</li>
        <li>
          <cmdname>create region</cmdname>
        </li>
        <li>
          <cmdname>alter region</cmdname>
        </li>
        <li>
          <cmdname>alter runtime</cmdname>
        </li>
        <li>
          <cmdname>destroy region</cmdname>
        </li>
        <li>
          <cmdname>create index</cmdname>
        </li>
        <li>
          <cmdname>destroy index</cmdname>
        </li>
        <li>
          <cmdname>create disk-store</cmdname>
        </li>
        <li>
          <cmdname>destroy disk-store</cmdname>
        </li>
        <li>
          <cmdname>create async-event-queue</cmdname>
        </li>
        <li>
          <cmdname>deploy jar</cmdname>
        </li>
        <li>
          <cmdname>undeploy jar</cmdname>
        </li>
      </ul>
      <p><b>*</b> Note that the <cmdname>configure pdx</cmdname> command must be executed
          <i>before</i> starting your data members. This command does not affect any currently
        running members in the system. Data members (with cluster configuration enabled) that are
        started after running this command will pick up the new PDX configuration.</p>
    </section>
    <section id="section_bn3_23p_y4">
      <title>gfsh Limitations</title>
      <p>There are some configurations that you cannot create using gfsh, and that you must
        configure using cache.xml or the API:</p>
      <ul id="ul_vfs_1bp_y4">
        <li>Client cache configuration</li>
        <li>You cannot specify parameters and values for Java classes for the following objects: <ul
            id="ul_pn1_lnk_z4">
            <li><codeph>function</codeph></li>
            <li><codeph>custom-load-probe</codeph></li>
            <li><codeph>cache-listener</codeph></li>
            <li><codeph>cache-loader</codeph></li>
            <li><codeph>cache-writer</codeph></li>
            <li><codeph>compressor</codeph></li>
            <li><codeph>serializer</codeph></li>
            <li><codeph>instantiantor</codeph></li>
            <li><codeph>pdx-serializer</codeph><p>
                <note>The <cmdname>configure pdx</cmdname> command always specifies the
                    <apiname>com.gemstone.gemfire.pdx.ReflectionBasedAutoSerializer</apiname> class.
                  You cannot specify a custom PDX serializer in gfsh. </note>
              </p></li>
            <li><codeph>custom-expiry</codeph></li>
            <li><codeph>initializer</codeph></li>
            <li><codeph>declarable</codeph></li>
            <li><codeph>lru-heap-percentage</codeph></li>
            <li><codeph>lru-memory-size</codeph></li>
            <li><codeph>partition-resolver</codeph></li>
            <li><codeph>partition-listener</codeph></li>
            <li><codeph>transaction-listener</codeph></li>
            <li><codeph>transaction-writer</codeph></li>
          </ul>
        </li>
        <li>Adding or removing a TransactionListener</li>
        <li>Adding JNDI bindings</li>
        <li>Deleting an AsyncEventQueue</li>
      </ul>
    </section>
    <section id="section_fh1_c3p_y4">
      <title>Disabling the Cluster Configuration Service</title>
      <p>If you do not want to use the cluster configuration service, start up your locator with the
          <codeph>--enable-cluster-configuration</codeph> parameter set to false or do not use
        standalone locators. You will then need to configure the cache (via cache.xml or API)
        separately on all your distributed system members.</p>
    </section>
  </conbody>
</concept>
