<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE concept PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN" "http://docs.oasis-open.org/dita/v1.1/OS/dtd/concept.dtd">
<concept id="interactive_mode_ref">
	<title>Interactive Configuration Reference for the tc Server Module </title>
	<shortdesc>This section describes each prompt when entering into interactive configuration mode
		of the <keyword keyref="product_name"/> HTTP Session Management Module for tc Server. </shortdesc>
	<conbody>
		<p> See <xref href="tc_changing_gf_default_cfg.xml#tc_changing_gf_default_cfg"
				type="concept" format="dita" scope="local"/> for specific pointers on how to use the
			interactive mode for common configuration changes. </p>
		<codeblock>  Please enter a value for 'gemfire.maximum.vm.heap.size.mb'. Default '512':
  Please enter a value for 'gemfire.initial.vm.heap.size.mb'. Default '512':
  Please enter a value for 'gemfire.cms.initiating.heap.percentage'. Default '50':</codeblock>
		<p>The above properties allow you to fine-tune your JVM heap and garbage collector. For more
			information, refer to <xref
				href="../../managing/heap_use/heap_management.xml#resource_manager" type="concept"
				format="dita" scope="local"/>.
			<codeblock>  Please specify whether to enable a GemFire listener that logs session create, 
  update, destroy and expiration events. Default 'false':</codeblock>
		</p>
		<p>The above property determines whether a debug cache listener is added to the session
			region. When true, info-level messages are logged to the <keyword keyref="product_name"
			/> log when sessions are created, updated, invalidated, or expired. </p>
		<codeblock>With the gemfire-p2p template:
  Please specify whether to maintain a local GemFire cache. Default 'false':
  
With the gemfire-cs template:
  Please specify whether to maintain a local GemFire cache. Default 'true':</codeblock>
		<p>The above property determines whether a local cache is enabled; if this parameter is set
			to true, the app server load balancer should be configured for sticky session mode. </p>
		<codeblock>With the gemfire-p2p template:
  Please enter the id of the attributes of the GemFire region used to cache 
      sessions.
  Default 'REPLICATE':

With the gemfire-cs template:
  Please enter the id of the attributes of the <keyword keyref="product_name"/> region used to cache 
      sessions.
  Default 'PARTITION_REDUNDANT':</codeblock>
		<p>The above property determines the ID of the attributes for the cache region; possible
			values include PARTITION, PARTITION_REDUNDANT, PARTITION_PERSISTENT, REPLICATE,
			REPLICATE_PERSISTENT, and any other region shortcut that can be found in <xref
				href="../../basic_config/data_regions/region_shortcuts.xml"
				type="concept" format="dita" scope="local"
				><?xm-replace_text Region Shortcuts and Custom Named Region Attributes?></xref>.
			When using a partitioned region attribute, it is recommended that you use
			PARTITION_REDUNDANT (rather than PARTITION) to ensure that the failure of a server does
			not result in lost session data. </p>
		<codeblock>  Please enter the name of the GemFire region used to cache sessions. 
  Default 'gemfire_modules_sessions':</codeblock>
		<p>The above property determines the <keyword keyref="product_name"/> region name. </p>
		<codeblock>  Please enter the port that Tomcat Shutdown should listen on. Default '-1':
  Please enter the port that the JMX socket listener should listen on. 
      Default '6969':</codeblock>
		<p>The above properties are application server properties. </p>
		<codeblock>  Please enter a value for 'bio.http.port'. Default '8080':
  Please enter a value for 'bio.https.port'. Default '8443':</codeblock>
		<p>tc Server requires information about connector ports. <codeph>bio.http.port</codeph> is
			the http port for tc Server and <codeph>bio.https.port</codeph> is the secure http port
			for tc Server. </p>
		<codeblock>With the gemfire-p2p template:
  Please enter the name of the GemFire cache configuration file. 
  Default 'cache-peer.xml':
  
With the gemfire-cs template:
  Please enter the name of the GemFire cache configuration file. 
  Default 'cache-client.xml':</codeblock>
		<p>You can change the name of the cache configuration file with the above property. If you
			do change this value, be sure to include an xml file by that name in the
				<codeph>conf</codeph> subdirectory. </p>
		<codeblock>  Please enter the percentage of heap at which updates to the cache are refused.
  0.0 means disabled. Default '0.0':
  Please enter the percentage of heap at which sessions will be evicted from the 
  local cache. Default '80.0':</codeblock>
		<p>The above properties allow you to control the critical and eviction watermarks for the
			heap. By default, the critical watermark is disabled (set to 0.0) and the eviction
			watermark is set to 80%. </p>
		<codeblock>Applicable to the gemfire-p2p template ONLY:
  Please enter the list of locators used by GemFire members to discover each other. 
  The format is a comma-separated list of host[port]. Default ' ':</codeblock>
		<p>The above property specifies the list of locators. For more information on locators,
			refer to <xref
				href="tc_changing_gf_default_cfg.xml#tc_changing_gf_default_cfg/p2p_cfg_using_locators"
				type="section" format="dita" scope="local">Peer-to-peer Configuration Using
				Locators</xref>. </p>
		<codeblock>  Please enter the name of the file used to log GemFire messages. 
  Default 'gemfire_modules.log':</codeblock>
		<p>The above property determines the filename for the <keyword keyref="product_name"/> log
			file. </p>
		<codeblock>Applicable to the gemfire-p2p template ONLY:
  Please enter the port used by GemFire members to discover each other using 
  multicast networking. Default '10334': </codeblock>
		<p>The above property specifies the port used for multicast discovery. When using locators,
			this value should be 0. For more information on multicast discovery, refer to <xref
				href="tc_changing_gf_default_cfg.xml#tc_changing_gf_default_cfg/use_a_diff_mc_port"
				type="section" format="dita" scope="local">Using a Different Multicast Port</xref>. </p>
		<codeblock>Applicable to the gemfire-p2p template ONLY:
  Please specify whether to rebalance the GemFire cache at startup.
  Default 'false':</codeblock>
		<p>This property allows you to rebalance a partitioned <keyword keyref="product_name"/>
			cache when a new <keyword keyref="product_name"/> peer starts up. </p>
		<codeblock>  Please enter the name of the file used to store GemFire statistics. 
  Default 'gemfire_modules.gfs':
</codeblock>
		<p>The above property determines the filename for the <keyword keyref="product_name"/>
			statistics file. </p>
		<codeblock>  Please specify whether GemFire statistic sampling should be enabled. 
  Default 'false':</codeblock>
		<p>The above property determines whether statistics sampling should occur. See <xref
				href="../../managing/statistics/chapter_overview.xml" type="concept"
				format="dita" scope="local"/> for more information. </p>
	</conbody>
</concept>
