<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE concept PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN" "http://docs.oasis-open.org/dita/v1.1/OS/dtd/concept.dtd">
<concept id="tc_changing_gf_default_cfg">
	<title>Changing the Default <keyword keyref="product_name"/> Configuration in the tc Server
		Module</title>
	<shortdesc>By default, the tc Server HTTP module will run <keyword keyref="product_name"/>
		automatically with pre-configured settings. You can change these <keyword
			keyref="product_name"/> settings. </shortdesc>
	<conbody>
		<p> Here are the default <keyword keyref="product_name"/> settings: </p>
			<ul
				id="ul_5F0C1E4883C7487C91637C8F46D5785C">
				<li id="li_1FFCE93C376B4731B623D34859714C42"><keyword keyref="product_name"/> peer-to-peer
					members use locators for discovery. </li>
				<li id="li_552F339F4AFB4F30B621398587DBF718">The region name is set to
						<codeph>gemfire_modules_sessions</codeph>. </li>
				<li id="li_8D8F79E4BA3546478458D3D8F917094D">The cache region is replicated for
					peer-to-peer configurations and partitioned (with redundancy turned on) for
					client/server configurations. </li>
				<li id="li_CAA3E5F163E246519F8DA9D33FF5A0FD"><keyword keyref="product_name"/>
					clients have local caching turned on and when the local cache needs to evict
					data, it will evict least-recently-used (LRU) data first. </li>
			</ul>
			<note>On the application server side, the default inactive interval for session
				expiration is set to 30 minutes. To change this value, refer to <xref
					href="tc_additional_info.xml#tc_additional_info/section_C7C4365EA2D84636AE1586F187007EC4"
					type="section" format="dita" scope="local"
					><?xm-replace_text Session Expiration?></xref>. </note>
		<p> To change this default configuration, use the <codeph>--interactive</codeph> command line
			argument when creating the tc Server instance. Choose the appropriate command for the
			chosen topology and platform.</p>
		<codeblock>In Unix, for a peer-to-peer topology:
  $ ./tcruntime-instance.sh create my_instance_name --template gemfire-p2p \
        --interactive

In Unix, for a client/server topology:
  $ ./tcruntime-instance.sh create my_instance_name --template gemfire-cs \
         --interactive

In Windows, for a peer-to-peer topology:
  $ tcruntime-instance.bat create my_instance_name --template gemfire-p2p ^ 
         --interactive

In Windows, for a client/server topology:
  $ tcruntime-instance.bat create my_instance_name --template gemfire-cs ^ 
         --interactive
</codeblock>
		<p>In interactive mode, you will be prompted to specify a series of property values. Hit
			&lt;return&gt; for any property that should use the default value. </p>
		<p>After responding to approximately 20 prompts, you should see the following line: </p>
		<codeblock>Instance created.
</codeblock>
			<note>You cannot override region attributes on the cache server when using the HTTP
				Session Management Module. You must place all region attribute definitions in the
				region attributes template that you customize in tc Server. See <xref scope="local"
					href="tc_changing_gf_default_cfg.xml#tc_changing_gf_default_cfg/section_38D803A7E8474188898963F456188543"
					type="section" format="dita"/> for more information. </note>
		<p>For information on setting up your instance for the most common types of configurations,
			refer to the sections below. For more information about each interactive prompt, refer
			to <xref format="dita" href="interactive_mode_ref.xml" scope="local">Interactive Mode
				Reference</xref>. </p>
		<section id="use_a_diff_mc_port">
			<title>Using a Different Locator Port</title>
			<p>For a <keyword keyref="product_name"/> peer-to-peer member to communicate on a different port
				than the default (10334), answer the following question in the tc Server HTTP
				module's interactive mode: </p>
			<codeblock>Please enter the list of locators used by GemFire members to discover each other. 
The format is a comma-separated list of host[port]. Default 'localhost[10334]': localhost[10335]</codeblock>
			<p>This example changes the locator port to 10335 on localhost. </p>
		</section>
		<section id="section_38D803A7E8474188898963F456188543">
			<title>Overriding Region Attributes</title>
			<p>When using the HTTP Session Management Module, you cannot override region attributes directly
				on the cache server. You must place all region attribute definitions in the region
				attributes template that you customize within tc Server. For example, to specify a
				different name for the region's disk store, you could add the new disk-store-name
				specification to the region attributes template and then reference the template on
				the cache server. </p>
			<codeblock>&lt;region-attributes id="MY_SESSIONS" refid="PARTITION_REDUNDANT_PERSISTENT_OVERFLOW" 
<b>disk-store-name="mystore"</b>&gt;
  ...
&lt;/region-attributes&gt;
</codeblock>
			<p>Then on the cache server side, reference the modified region attributes template to
				allow the region to use the disk-store-name attribute:  </p>
			<codeblock>&lt;region name="gemfire_modules_sessions" refid="MY_SESSIONS"/&gt;</codeblock>
		</section>
	</conbody>
</concept>
