<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE concept PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN" "concept.dtd">
<!-- Created with XMetaL (http://www.xmetal.com) -->
<concept id="concept_915EAD135DD942F28A38513097ACB1F1"> 
  <title>Disconnection</title> 
  <shortdesc>While the client and servers are disconnected, their operation
	 varies depending on the circumstances.
  </shortdesc> 
  <conbody>
	 <section id="section_6AB8F4B8993F4EF9B32A93A100F07BEC"> 
		<title>Normal disconnect</title> 
		<p> When a durable client disconnects normally, the 
		  <codeph>Cache.close</codeph> request states whether to maintain the
		  client's message queue and durable subscriptions. The servers stop sending
		  messages to the client and release its connection. See<xref
		  href="7-Preserving_Data.htm#96574">Disconnecting From the Server</xref> for
		  more information.
		</p> 
		<p> If requested, the servers maintain the queues and durable interest
		  list until the client reconnects or times out. The non-durable interest list is
		  discarded. The servers continue to queue up incoming messages for entries on
		  the durable interest list. All messages that were in the queue when the client
		  disconnected remain in the queue, including messages for entries on the
		  non-durable list.
		</p> 
		<p> If the client requests to not have its subscriptions maintained, or
		  if there are no durable subscriptions, the servers unregister the client and
		  perform the same cleanup as for a non-durable client.
		</p> 
		<title>Abnormal disconnect</title> 
		<p> If the client crashes or loses its connections to all servers, the
		  servers automatically maintain its message queue and durable subscriptions
		  until the client reconnects or times out.
		</p> 
		<title>Client disconnected but operational</title> 
		<p> If the client operates while it is disconnected, it gets what data it
		  can from the local cache. Since updates are not allowed, the data can become
		  stale. An 
		  <codeph>UnconnectedException</codeph> occurs if an update is attempted.
		</p> 
		<title>Timing out while disconnected</title> 
		<p> The servers track how long to keep a durable client queue alive based
		  on the 
		  <codeph>durable-client-timeout</codeph> setting. If the client remains
		  disconnected longer than the timeout, the servers unregister the client and do
		  the same cleanup that is performed for a non-durable client. The servers also
		  log an alert. When a timed-out client reconnects, the servers treat it as a new
		  client making its initial connection.
		</p> 
	 </section>
  </conbody> 
</concept>
