<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE concept PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN" "concept.dtd">
<!-- Created with XMetaL (http://www.xmetal.com) -->
<concept id="concept_6335D20D9FB64D6486C28B0A1FDD0FF3"> 
  <title>Event Handling APIs</title> 
  <shortdesc>Code your event handlers to do minimal work before returning
	 control back to GemFire. For example, a listener implementation may choose to
	 hand off the event to a thread pool that processes the event on its thread
	 rather than the listener thread. Exceptions thrown by the listeners are caught
	 by GemFire and logged.
  </shortdesc> 
  <conbody>
	 <ul id="ul_50DBE31FF2D1461CBEED99A89233B6A4">
		<li id="li_10A262C4A556425794375753AB007D9A"><b>RegionEvent</b>—This
		  class provides information about the event, such as what region the event
		  originated in, whether the event originated in a cache remote to the event
		  handler, and whether the event resulted from a distributed operation.
		</li>
		<li id="li_EC05BC7A51EE4C349FF06A14A2EB6DEB"><b>EntryEvent</b>—This class
		  provides all of the information available for the 
		  <codeph>RegionEvent</codeph> . It also provides entry-specific
		  information, such as the old and new entry values and whether the event
		  resulted from a load operation.
		</li>
		<li
		 id="li_54994E7ABDB148AA8C72DD07CDE5FF44"><b>ICacheLoader</b>—Application
		  callback interface for loading data into a region.
		</li>
		<li
		 id="li_B63BBD7F8C484021B8950749B7414648"><b>ICacheWriter</b>—Application
		  callback interface for synchronously handling region and entry events before
		  the events occur. Entry events are 
		  <codeph>create</codeph>, 
		  <codeph>update</codeph>, 
		  <codeph>invalidate</codeph>, and 
		  <codeph>destroy</codeph>. Region events are invalidate and destroy .
		  This class has the ability to abort events.
		</li>
		<li
		 id="li_D4D038AF521B489883F138D8B758C2E5"><b>ICacheListener</b>—Application
		  callback interface for asynchronously handing region and entry events.
		  Listeners receive notifications when entries in a region change, or when
		  changes occur to the region attributes themselves. Entry events are 
		  <codeph>create</codeph>, 
		  <codeph>update</codeph>, 
		  <codeph>invalidate</codeph>, and 
		  <codeph>destroy</codeph>. Region events are 
		  <codeph>invalidate</codeph> and 
		  <codeph>destroy</codeph>. Multiple events can cause concurrent
		  invocation of 
		  <codeph>ICacheListener</codeph> methods. If event A occurs before event
		  B, there is no guarantee that their corresponding ICacheListener method
		  invocations will occur in the same order.
		</li>
	 </ul>
  </conbody> 
</concept>
