<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE concept PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN"
"concept.dtd">
<concept id="how-native-client-xacts-work">
  <title>How Native Client Transactions Work</title>

  <conbody>
    <p>The syntax for writing client transactions is the same as with server
    or peer transactions, but when a client performs a transaction, the
    transaction is delegated to a server that brokers the transaction. For
    information on transaction requirements and activities on the server side,
    see the <i>Transactions</i> chapter in the <i>GemFire User’s Guide</i>.
    </p>

    <note>The client cache blocks until the transaction is successfully
    committed. However, the client cache block is removed if the transaction
    is suspended.</note>

    <p>Depending on where the data resides, the server transaction delegate
    may or not be the same member that hosts the transaction. This is the same
    as for transactions run by the servers, but for server-run transactions,
    there is no delegate. There is just the member that is directly running
    its own transaction code. </p>

    <p>In this figure, the application code on client makes changes to data
    entries Y and Z within a transaction. The server delegate that performs
    the transaction, M1, does not host the primary copy of the data being
    modified. The transaction takes place on server M2, where the data
    resides. </p>

    <fig>
      <title>Transaction Run From a Client</title>

      <image href="../common/images/xact-run-from-client.gif"/>

      <p>To maintain cache consistency, the local client cache is not
      accessible during a transaction as it may reflect information
      inconsistent with the transaction in progress. When the transaction
      completes, the local cache is accessible again. </p>

      <p>In addition to the failure conditions common to all transactions,
      client transactions can also fail if the transaction delegate fails. If
      the delegate performing the transaction fails, the transaction code will
      throw a <codeph>TransactionException</codeph>. </p>
    </fig>
  </conbody>
</concept>
