<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE concept PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN" "concept.dtd">
<concept id="implementing-delta-propagation">
  <title id="title_7969E8015B314FFCB01ACFE4E4B19772">Implementing Delta Propagation</title>

  <conbody id="conbody_9CE12524178A4FA988341F953795DF49">
    <p id="p_13538AC20E734BD195D51D6B0472DAF1">By default, delta propagation is enabled in your distributed system.
    When enabled, delta propagation is used for objects that implement the
    delta interface. See Delta Propagation API. You program the client-side
    methods to extract delta information for your entries and to apply
    received delta information. </p>

    <ol>
      <li id="li_A0E992F60192401A9EC8658DC6CA3DBC"><p id="p_0872A9F41C714D4499B08AC3AE226FBC">Choose whether to enable cloning. Cloning is disabled by default.
      See See <xref format="dita" href="delta-propagation-properties.xml" scope="local">cloning-enabled</xref>. </p><ul id="ul_F262ACAA26194369ACC6F376A8A56809">
          <li>If you enable cloning, consider providing your own
          implementation, to optimize performance. </li>

          <li id="li_702CC6FE95044EA3A41F576746D94B6B">If you do not enable cloning, be sure to synchronize your delta
          code.</li>
        </ul></li>

      <li id="li_B9E27012E3E746828B2074D3D2DD1E1B">Study your object types and expected application behavior to
      determine which objects should use delta propagation. Delta propagation
      is not beneficial for all data and data modification scenarios. For
      guidance on your decision, see <xref href="performance.xml">Performance
      Considerations and Limitations</xref>.</li>

      <li id="li_C7F36AD82BB0497F99AE8FBF5C9B69B7">If you do not enable cloning, review all associated listener code
      for dependencies on the entry event old value. Without cloning, GemFire
      modifies the entry in place and so loses its reference to the old value.
      For delta events, the <codeph>EntryEvent</codeph> methods to retrieve
      the old and new values both return the new value. </li>

      <li><p id="p_A6CBA231DCD34C998285B5DDF4C51D00">For every class where you want delta propagation, implement the
      <codeph>delta</codeph> interface and update your methods to support
      delta propagation. Exactly how you do this depends on your application
      and object needs, but these steps describe the basic approach:</p><ol id="ol_E87A912B84764F76BEC669118C118293">
          <li id="li_F652D59AFE224FB8B10CD7C87F5766DE">Study the object contents to decide how to handle delta changes.
          Delta propagation has the same issues of distributed concurrency
          control as the distribution of full objects, but on a more detailed
          level. Some parts of your objects may be able to change independent
          of one another while others may always need to change together. Send
          deltas large enough to keep your data logically consistent. If, for
          example, field A and field B depend on each other, then your delta
          distributions should either update both fields or neither. As with
          regular updates, the fewer producers you have on a data region, the
          lower your likelihood of concurrency issues. </li>

          <li>In the application code that puts entries, put the fully
          populated object into the local cache. Even though you are planning
          to send only deltas, errors on the receiving end could cause GemFire
          to request the full object, so you must provide it to the
          originating put method. Do this even in empty producers, with
          regions configured for no local data storage. This usually means
          doing a <codeph>get</codeph> on the entry, unless you are sure it
          does not already exist anywhere in the distributed region. </li>

          <li id="li_A2AD70EC801F431499CF37DD2B52173F">Change each field’s update method to record information about
          the update. The information must be sufficient for
          <codeph>toDelta</codeph> to encode the delta and any additional
          required delta information when it is invoked. </li>

          <li id="li_8E21845E3E844AE992DE1B0649A480D6">Write <codeph>hasDelta</codeph> to report on whether a delta is
          available. </li>

          <li id="li_EF53E58B35504A66AADEEA26AF85FEF8">When writing your serialization methods,
          <codeph>toDelta</codeph>, <codeph>fromDelta</codeph>,
          <codeph>toData</codeph>, <codeph>fromData</codeph>, be sure to
          exclude any fields used to manage delta state, which do not need to
          be sent.</li>

          <li>Write <codeph>toDelta</codeph> to create a byte stream with the
          changes to the object and any other information
          <codeph>fromDelta</codeph> will need to apply the changes. Before
          returning from <codeph>toDelta</codeph>, reset your delta state to
          indicate that there are no delta changes waiting to be sent. </li>

          <li id="li_54F4533308754ED58C13604EC375D531">Write <codeph>fromDelta</codeph> to decode the byte stream that
          <codeph>toDelta</codeph> creates and update the object. </li>

          <li id="li_E755698CCE38462990510F1DD491054C">Make sure you provide adequate synchronization to your object to
          maintain a consistent object state. If you do not use cloning, you
          will probably need to synchronize on reads and writes to avoid
          reading partially written updates from the cache. This might involve
          <codeph>toDelta</codeph>, <codeph>fromDelta</codeph>, and other
          object access and update methods. Additionally, your implementation
          should take into account the possibility of concurrent invocations
          of <codeph>fromDelta</codeph> and one or more of the object's update
          methods. </li>
        </ol></li>
    </ol>
  </conbody>
</concept>
