<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE concept PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN"
"concept.dtd">
<concept id="security">
  <title id="title_9717E51087B346988389138843E158C4">Using an LDAP Server for
  Client Authentication</title>

  <shortdesc>An LDAP server can be used by a GemFire cache server using the
  sample LDAP implementation provided in GemFire server product. See the
  Security chapter in the GemFire User's Guide to verify authentication
  credentials for native clients attempting to connect to the GemFire servers
  and sending username and passwords using the sample UserPassword scheme.
  </shortdesc>

  <conbody id="conbody_D74C4342289846619E028149A8920946">
    <p><i>The username and password with this sample implementation is sent
    out in plaintext. For better security, either turn on credential
    encryption using Diffie-Hellman key exchange, or use a scheme like
    PKCS.</i></p>

    <p>When a client initiates a connection to a cache server, the client
    submits its credentials to the server and the server submits those
    credentials to the LDAP server. To be authenticated, the credentials for
    the client need to match one of the valid entries in the LDAP server. The
    credentials can consist of the entry name and the corresponding password.
    If the submitted credentials result in a connection to the LDAP server
    because the credentials match the appropriate LDAP entries, then the
    client is authenticated and granted a connection to the server. If the
    server fails to connect to the LDAP server with the supplied credentials
    then an AuthenticationFailedException is sent to the client and its
    connection with the cache server is closed.</p>

    <p><b>Configuration Settings</b></p>

    <p>In the gfcpp.properties file for the client, you need to specify the
    UserPasswordAuthInit callback, the username, and the password, like
    this:</p>

    <p><codeph>security-client-auth-library=securityImpl</codeph></p>

    <p><codeph>security-client-auth-factory=createUserPasswordAuthInitInstance</codeph></p>

    <p><codeph>security-username=&lt;username&gt;</codeph></p>

    <p><codeph>security-password=&lt;password&gt;</codeph></p>

    <p>For server side settings and LDAP server configuration, see the
    Security chapter in the <i><!--BEVLINK-->GemFire User's Guide</i>.</p>
  </conbody>
</concept>
