<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE concept PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN"
"concept.dtd">
<concept id="subscription-properties">
  <title>Subscription Properties</title>

  <conbody>
    <p>Each connection pool has a single subscription connection which could
    be to any server which matches the requirements of the connection pool.
    When a client registers interest for a region, if the connection pool does
    not already have a subscription channel, the connection pool sends a
    message to the server locator and the server locator chooses servers to
    host the queue and return those server names to the client. The client
    then contacts the chosen servers and asks them to create the queue. The
    client maintains at least one connection with each server hosting a queue
    - if the server does not detect any connections from a non-durable client,
    it drops the client queue and closes all artifacts for the client. For
    information about durable client subscriptions, see <xref
    href="???">Durable Client Messaging</xref>.</p>

    <section><title>Requesting a Subscription Region Queue</title><p>The
    client to server locator request is a short lived TCP request. The client
    sends a message with:</p><ul>
        <li>The client ID</li>

        <li>(Optional) target server group</li>

        <li>Number of redundant copies</li>

        <li>Servers to exclude from the results. This is used if the client
        was unable to connect to a server and needs to request a new one.</li>
      </ul><p>The server locator responds with a list of servers. The client
    is responsible for contacting the primary and secondaries and asking them
    to host the queue.</p><p>For durable subscriptions, the server locator
    must be able to locate the servers that host the queues for the durable
    client. When a durable client sends a request, the server locator queries
    all the available servers to see if they are hosting the subscription
    region queue for the durable client. If the server is located, the client
    is connected to the server hosting the subscription region
    queue.</p></section>
  </conbody>
</concept>
