<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE concept PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN"
"concept.dtd">
<concept id="security">
  <title id="title_9717E51087B346988389138843E158C4">System Properties for
  Authentication</title>

  <shortdesc>The native client uses system properties to configure
  authentication. These properties are defined in
  the<codeph>gfcpp.properties</codeph> file, which the native client accesses
  during startup.</shortdesc>

  <conbody id="conbody_D74C4342289846619E028149A8920946">
    <section
    id="section_E1835A3B22D44D47A4C9DB54A3590B71"><title>security-client-auth-factory</title><p>This
    is the system property for the factory function of the class implementing
    the AuthInitialize interface (IAuthInitialize in .NET). The .NET clients
    can load both C++ and .NET implementations. For .NET implementations, this
    property is the fully qualified name of the static factory function
    (including the namespace and class). </p></section>

    <section
    id="section_15C6689C363B469B947B177E1DE73208"><title>security-client-auth-library</title><p>This
    is the system property for the library where the factory methods reside.
    The library is loaded explicitly and the factory functions are invoked
    dynamically, returning an object of the class implementing the
    AuthInitialize interface. </p><p>Other implementations of the
    <codeph>AuthInitialize</codeph> interface may be required to build
    credentials using properties that are also passed as system properties.
    These properties also start with the security- prefix. For example, the
    PKCS implementation requires an alias name and the corresponding keystore
    path, which are specified as <codeph>security-alias</codeph> and
    <codeph>security-keystorepath</codeph>, respectively. Similarly,
    <codeph>UserPasswordAuthInit </codeph>requires a username specified in
    <codeph>security-username</codeph>, and the corresponding password is
    specified in the <codeph>security-password</codeph> system property.
    </p><p>The <codeph>getCredentials</codeph> function for the
    <codeph>AuthInitialize</codeph> interface is called to obtain the
    credentials. All system properties starting with security- are passed to
    this callback as the first argument to the <codeph>getCredentials</codeph>
    function, as shown in the following code snippet: </p><p>
    <codeph>PropertiesPtr getCredentials(PropertiesPtr&amp; securityprops,
    const char *server);</codeph> </p><p> <xref/>The following example shows
    how to implement the factory method in both C++ and .NET: </p><fig
        id="fig_F7BBA12DA07343A79896E40D2187B0CE">
        <title>Implementing the Factory Method for Authentication (C++ and
        .NET)</title>

        <codeblock id="codeblock_E8BA26FFF5AB4038AFB9AC1FA64B4694"><b>C++ Implementation</b>
LIBEXP AuthInitialize* createPKCSAuthInitInstance()
{
return new PKCSAuthInit( );
}
<b>.NET Implementation</b>
public static IAuthInitialize Create()
{
return new UserPasswordAuthInit();
}</codeblock>
      </fig><p>Implementations of the factory method are user-provided.
    Credentials in the form of properties returned by this function are sent
    by the client to the server for authentication during the client’s
    handshake process with the server. </p><p>The GemFire native client
    installation provides sample security implementations in its
    <codeph>templates/security</codeph> folder. </p></section>
  </conbody>
</concept>
