<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE concept PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN" "concept.dtd">
<concept
	id="suspend-resume-xacts">
	<title
		id="title_052F77DEF74948C68171854261C49C95">Suspending and Resuming Transactions</title>
	<shortdesc>The ability to suspend and resume transactions is useful when a thread must perform
		operations that should not be part of the transaction before the transaction can complete. </shortdesc>
	<conbody
		id="conbody_4774A70126D34E6B9A79C33C1C0A9F55">
		<p
			id="p_F4B322265890421FB03569E78A317021">When a transaction is suspended, it loses the
			transactional view of the cache. None of the previous operations (before calling
			suspend) are visible to the thread. Subsequently any operations that are performed by
			the thread do not participate in the suspended transaction. </p>
		<p
			id="p_716E172661CC44A98BDA5EE78EA881F0">When a transaction is resumed, the resuming
			thread assumes the transactional view. A transaction that is suspending on a member must
			be resumed on the same member. Before resuming a transaction, you may want to check if
			the transaction exists on the member and whether it is suspended. You may optionally use
			the <codeph>tryResume</codeph> method. </p>
		<p
			id="p_A0566600603045EFB17DD9D894D23990">If the member with the primary copy of the data
			crashes, the transactional view that applied to that data is lost. The secondary member
			for the data cannot resume transactions suspended on the crashed member. You need to
			take remedial steps to retry the transaction on a new primary copy of the data. </p>
		<p>If a suspended transaction is not touched for a period of time, <keyword keyref="product_name"
			/> cleans it up automatically. By default, the timeout for a suspended transaction is 30
			minutes and can be configured by using the <codeph>suspended-tx-timeout</codeph>
			property of the <codeph>gfcpp.properties</codeph> file. The suspended transaction
			timeout value is specified in milliseconds. </p>
		<p
			id="p_393151BE74D8461B8176E1068F6033E4">See <xref
				href="running-native-client-xact.xml">Running a Native Client Transaction</xref> for
			code examples of how to suspend and resume a transaction. </p>
	</conbody>
</concept>
