<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE concept PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN" "http://docs.oasis-open.org/dita/v1.1/OS/dtd/concept.dtd">
<concept id="rec_network_crash">
	<title>Understanding and Recovering from Network Outages</title>
	<shortdesc>The safest response to a network outage is to restart all the processes and bring up
		a fresh data set. </shortdesc>
	<conbody>
		<p> However, if you know the architecture of your system well, and you are sure you won’t be
			resurrecting old data, you can do a selective restart. At the very least, you must
			restart all the members on one side of the network failure, because a network outage
			causes separate distributed systems that can’t rejoin automatically. </p>
		<ul id="ul_DD35E62B1A494483ACCCB90D2107B590">
			<li id="li_57288D8C46BE4CB587C145F82C4DCD6E">
				<xref
					href="recovering_from_network_outages.xml#rec_network_crash/section_900657018DC048EE9BE6A8064FAE48FD"
					type="section" format="dita" scope="local"
					><?xm-replace_text What Happens During a Network Outage?></xref>
			</li>
			<li id="li_77CC4B2143A244FB8F401BCAC004CC59">
				<xref
					href="recovering_from_network_outages.xml#rec_network_crash/section_F9A0C31AE25C4E7185DF3B1A8486BDFA"
					type="section" format="dita" scope="local"
					><?xm-replace_text Recovery Procedure?></xref>
			</li>
			<li id="li_C5216ADC0217402A9EC72FCD0908E202">
				<xref
					href="recovering_from_network_outages.xml#rec_network_crash/section_9914A63673E64EA1ADB6B6767879F0FF"
					type="section" format="dita" scope="local"
					><?xm-replace_text Effect of Network Failure on Partitioned Regions?></xref>
			</li>
			<li id="li_FF50598836EF45158ABCEC3394E7AFD8">
				<xref
					href="recovering_from_network_outages.xml#rec_network_crash/section_7AD5624F3CD748C0BC163562B26B2DCE"
					type="section" format="dita" scope="local"
					><?xm-replace_text Effect of Network Failure on Distributed Regions?></xref>
			</li>
			<li>
				<xref href="#rec_network_crash/section_arm_pnr_3q" format="dita"/>
			</li>
			<li id="li_BB338E887B4046869878E42A8D1C5041">
				<xref
					href="recovering_from_network_outages.xml#rec_network_crash/section_18AEEB6CC8004C3388CCB01F988B0422"
					type="section" format="dita" scope="local"
					><?xm-replace_text Effect of Network Failure on Client/Server Installations?></xref>
			</li>
		</ul>
		<section id="section_900657018DC048EE9BE6A8064FAE48FD">
			<title>What Happens During a Network Outage</title>
			<p>When the network connecting members of a distributed system goes down, system members
				treat this like a machine crash. Members on each side of the network failure respond
				by removing the members on the other side from the membership list. If network
				partitioning detection is enabled, the partition that contains sufficient quorum (>
				51% based on member weight) will continue to operate, while the other partition with
				insufficient quorum will shut down. See <xref
					href="../network_partitioning/chapter_overview.xml#network_partitioning"/> for a
				detailed explanation on how this detection system operates.</p>
			<p>In addition, members that have been disconnected either via network partition or due
				to unresponsiveness will automatically try to reconnect to the distributed system
				unless configured otherwise. See <xref
					href="../autoreconnect/member-reconnect.xml"
				/>.</p>
		</section>
		<section id="section_F9A0C31AE25C4E7185DF3B1A8486BDFA">
			<title>Recovery Procedure</title>
			<p>For deployments that have network partition detection and/or auto-reconnect disabled,
				to recover from a network outage: </p>
			<ol id="ol_8D95EAE70719491197B227E2D0B3E156">
				<li id="li_463C0E10D3A2419A8756D616B7C74BDC">Decide which applications and cache
					servers to restart, based on the architecture of the distributed system. Assume
					that any process other than a data source is bad and needs restarting. For
					example, if an outside data feed is coming in to one member, which then
					redistributes to all the others, you can leave that process running and restart
					the other members. </li>
				<li id="li_1AC0666FC1604075B810F9F24E835172">Shut down all the processes that need
					restarting. </li>
				<li id="li_E68880BF05524D52A5FB1EF0053AD770">Restart them in the usual order. </li>
			</ol>
			<p>The members recreate the data as they return to active work. For details, see <xref
					href="recovering_from_app_crashes.xml#rec_app_crash" type="concept"
					format="dita" scope="local"
					><?xm-replace_text Recovering from Application and Cache Server Crashes?></xref>.
			</p>
		</section>
		<section id="section_9914A63673E64EA1ADB6B6767879F0FF">
			<title>Effect of Network Failure on Partitioned Regions</title>
			<p>Both sides of the distributed system continue to run as though the members on the
				other side were not running. If the members that participate in a partitioned region
				are on both sides of the network failure, both sides of the partitioned region also
				continue to run as though the data stores on the other side did not exist. In
				effect, you now have two partitioned regions. </p>
			<p>When the network recovers, the members may be able to see each other again, but they
				are not able to merge back together into a single distributed system and combine
				their buckets back into a single partitioned region. You can be sure that the data
				is in an inconsistent state. Whether you are configured for data redundancy or not,
				you don’t really know what data was lost and what wasn’t. Even if you have redundant
				copies and they survived, different copies of an entry may have different values
				reflecting the interrupted workflow and inaccessible data. </p>
		</section>
		<section id="section_7AD5624F3CD748C0BC163562B26B2DCE">
			<title>Effect of Network Failure on Distributed Regions</title>
			<p>By default, both sides of the distributed system continue to run as though the
				members on the other side were not running. For distributed regions, however, the
				regions’s reliability policy configuration can change this default behavior. </p>
			<p>When the network recovers, the members may be able to see each other again, but they
				are not able to merge back together into a single distributed system. </p>
		</section>
		<section id="section_arm_pnr_3q">
			<title>Effect of Network Failure on Persistent Regions</title>
			<p>A network failure when using persistent regions can cause conflicts in your persisted
				data. When you recover your system, you will likely encounter
					<codeph>ConflictingPersistentDataException</codeph>s when members start up.</p>
			<p>For this reason, you must configure
					<codeph>enable-network-partition-detection</codeph> to <codeph>true</codeph> if
				you are using persistent regions. </p>
			<p>For information on how to recover from
					<codeph>ConflictingPersistentDataException</codeph> errors should they occur,
				see <xref href="recovering_conflicting_data_exceptions.xml#topic_ghw_z2m_jq"/>.</p>
		</section>
		<section id="section_18AEEB6CC8004C3388CCB01F988B0422">
			<title>Effect of Network Failure on Client/Server Installations</title>
			<p>If a client loses contact with all of its servers, the effect is the same as if it
				had crashed. You need to restart the client. See <xref
					href="recovering_from_cs_crashes.xml#rec_app_cs_crash/section_24B1898202E64C1E808C59E39417891B"
					type="section" format="dita" scope="local"
					><?xm-replace_text Recovering from Client Failure?></xref>. If a client loses
				contact with some servers, but not all of them, the effect on the client is the same
				as if the unreachable servers had crashed. See <xref
					href="recovering_from_cs_crashes.xml#rec_app_cs_crash/section_2A598C85FAD44CDEA605646BF7BEE388"
					type="section" format="dita" scope="local"
					><?xm-replace_text Recovering from Server Failure ?></xref>. </p>
			<p>Servers, like applications, are members of a distributed system, so the effect of
				network failure on a server is the same as for an application. Exactly what happens
				depends on the configuration of your site. </p>
		</section>
	</conbody>
</concept>
