<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE concept PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN" "http://docs.oasis-open.org/dita/v1.1/OS/dtd/concept.dtd">
<concept id="managing_data_entries">
	<title>Managing Data Entries</title>
	<shortdesc id="shortdesc_5914A720095944E69BCABDBB49B187E1">Program your applications to create,
		modify, and manage your cached data entries. </shortdesc>
	<conbody>
		<section id="section_AACC36127F17411F86D1E409B86C6E5C">
			<note>
				<p>If you do not have the cache's <codeph>copy-on-read</codeph> attribute set to
				true, do not change the objects returned from the Java entry access methods.
				Instead, create a copy of the object, then modify the copy and pass it to the Java
					<codeph>put</codeph> method. Modifying a value in place bypasses the entire
				distribution framework provided by <keyword keyref="product_name"/>, including cache
				listeners and expiration activities, and can produce undesired results. 
				</p>
			</note>
		</section>
		<section id="section_B095A4073EFB4A3C91AF7C03632EEBFB">
			<title>Basic Create and Update</title>
			<p>To create or update an entry in the cache, use <codeph>Region.put</codeph>. For
				example:</p>
				<codeblock outputclass="language-java">String name = ... 
String value = ...  
this.currRegion.put(name,value); </codeblock>
			<note>
				<p>You
					can also use the <codeph>gfsh <cmdname>put</cmdname></codeph> command to add
					entries to a region, and the <cmdname>get</cmdname> command to retrieve entries
					from a region. See <xref
						href="../../tools_modules/gfsh/command-pages/get.xml"
					/> and <xref format="dita"
						href="../../tools_modules/gfsh/command-pages/put.xml"
						scope="local" type="concept"/> for more information. 
				</p>
			</note>
			<p>If you want only to create the entry (with a null value and with method failure if
				the entry already exists), use <codeph>Region.create</codeph> instead. </p>
		</section>
		<section id="section_7578349EA26A4621B732FE851D71A84F">
			<title>Batch Operations (getAll, putAll, removeAll)</title>
			<p><keyword keyref="product_name"/> provides three APIs to perform batch operations on
				multiple region entries:</p>
			<ul id="ul_uft_2vr_gq">
				<li>
					<codeph>Region.getAll</codeph>
				</li>
				<li>
					<codeph>Region.putAll</codeph>
				</li>
				<li>
					<codeph>Region.removeAll</codeph>
				</li>
			</ul>
			<p>The <codeph>getAll</codeph> method takes a collection of keys and returns a
					<codeph>Map</codeph> of values for the provided keys. If a given key does not
				exist in the region, then that key's value in the returned map will be null.</p>
			<p>The <codeph>putAll</codeph> method takes a <codeph>Map</codeph> of key-value pairs
				and puts them into the cache and distributes them in a single operation. </p>
			<p>
				<b>Example:</b></p>
				<codeblock outputclass="language-java">void putAll(String command) throws CacheException 
{ 
// Get Entry keys and values into Strings key1, ... keyN and value1, ... valueN 
  Map map = new LinkedHashMap(); 
  map.put(key1, value1)); 
  ...
  map.put(keyN, valueN));
  this.currRegion.putAll(map); 
}</codeblock>
			<p>The updates to the cache are done individually in the order in which they were placed
				in the <codeph>Map</codeph>. For partitioned regions, multiple events are sent as a
				single message to the primary buckets and then distributed to the secondary buckets.</p>
			<note>
				<p>The processing of maps with very many entries and/or very large data may
					affect system performance and cause cache update timeouts, especially if the
					region uses overflow or persistence to disk.
				</p>
			</note>
			<p>The <codeph>removeAll</codeph> method takes a collection of keys and removes all of
				the entries for the specified keys from this region. This call performs the
				equivalent of calling<codeph>destroy(Object)</codeph> on this region once for each
				key in the specified collection. If an entry does not exist, then that key is
				skipped. An <codeph>EntryNotFoundException</codeph> is not thrown. This operation
				will be distributed to other caches if the region's scope is not set to
					<codeph>Scope.LOCAL</codeph>.</p>
		</section>
		<section id="section_A0E0F889AC344EFA8DF304FD64418809">
			<title>Safe Entry Modification </title>
			<p>When you get an entry value from the cache, by default, the retrieval methods return
				a direct reference to the cached object. This provides the value as quickly as
				possible, but also opens the cache to direct, in-place changes. </p>
			<note>
				<p>Do not
					directly modify cached values. Modifying a value in place bypasses the <keyword keyref="product_name"/>
					distribution framework, including cache writers and listeners, expiration
					activities, and transaction management, and can produce undesired results.
				</p>
			</note>
			<p>Always change your entries using copies of the retrieved objects—never directly
				modify the returned objects. You can do this in one of two ways: </p>
				<ol
					id="ol_E5F0ED67E2D54C18BBA3473206E8C8C4">
					<li id="li_22EF5D6D349B44FD82173D996A7D5A0B">Change the entry retrieval behavior
						for your cache by setting the cache attribute,
						<codeph>copy-on-read</codeph>, to true (the default is false).
						<codeblock outputclass="language-xml">&lt;cache copy-on-read="true"&gt;
 ...
&lt;/cache&gt;</codeblock>When
							<codeph>copy-on-read</codeph> is true, the entry access methods return
						copies of the entries. This protects you from inadvertently modifying
						in-place, but negatively impacts performance and memory consumption when
						copying is not needed. <p>These entry access methods return an entry
							reference if <codeph>copy-on-read</codeph> is false and a copy of the
							entry if <codeph>copy-on-read</codeph> is true: </p>
							<table id="table_0A468474D80C4FA98E875C28915F4AB4">
								<tgroup cols="3">
									<colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="*"/>
									<colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="*"/>
									<colspec colname="3" colnum="3" colwidth="*"/>
									<tbody>
										<row>
											<entry>
												<codeph>Region.get</codeph>
											</entry>
											<entry>result of <codeph>Region.put</codeph>
											</entry>
											<entry>
												<codeph>EntryEvent.getNewValue</codeph>
											</entry>
										</row>
										<row>
											<entry>
												<codeph>Region.values</codeph>
											</entry>
											<entry>
												<codeph>Region.Entry.getValue</codeph>
											</entry>
											<entry>
												<codeph>EntryEvent.getOldValue</codeph>
											</entry>
										</row>
										<row>
											<entry>
												<codeph>Query.select</codeph>
											</entry>
										</row>
									</tbody>
								</tgroup>
							</table>
					</li>
					<li id="li_418252892B9241C1AF048E712450AE92">Create a copy of the returned
						object and work with that. For objects that are cloneable or serializable,
						you can copy the entry value to a new object using
							<codeph>com.gemstone.gemfire.CopyHelper.copy</codeph>. Example:
						<codeblock outputclass="language-java">Object o = (StringBuffer)region.get("stringBuf");
StringBuffer s = (StringBuffer) CopyHelper.copy(o);
s.append("Changes to value, added using put.");
region.put("stringBuf", s);</codeblock>
					</li>
				</ol>
		</section>
		<section id="section_78F6731642944DE594316B86ECB4E70F">
			<title>Retrieving Region Entries from Proxy Members </title>
			<p>The <codeph>Region.values</codeph> method call applies to the local region instance
				only. If you call the <codeph>values</codeph> method from a client region using the
				PROXY shortcut, the method call will not be redirected to the server region. To
				obtain a collection of all values in the Region from a client, you should use
				interest registration on ALL_KEYS, or use a query. </p>
			<p>If you use the <codeph>Region.get</codeph> method from a proxy member, the method
				call will redirect to the region on the server if it cannot find the key locally.
			</p>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Using gfsh to get and put </title>
			<p>You can use the gfsh <cmdname>get</cmdname> and <cmdname>put</cmdname> commands to
				manage data. See <xref
					href="../../tools_modules/gfsh/command-pages/get.xml"
				/> and <xref
					href="../../tools_modules/gfsh/command-pages/put.xml"
				/>.</p>
			<p>For example:</p>
				<codeblock outputclass="language-java">
get --key=('id':'133abg124') --region=region1

// Retrieving when key type is a wrapper(primitive)/String
get --key=('133abg124') --region=/region1/region12 --value-class=data.ProfileDetails

get --key=('100L') --region=/region1/region12 --value-class=data.ProfileDetails 
--key-class=java.lang.Long</codeblock>
				<codeblock outputclass="language-java">
put --key=('id':'133abg125') --value=('firstname':'James','lastname':'Gosling') 
--region=/region1 --key-class=data.ProfileKey --value-class=data.ProfileDetails

put --key=('133abg124') --value=('Hello World!!') --region=/region2

put --key=('100F') --value=('2146547689879658564')  --region=/region1/region12 
--key-class=java.lang.Float --value-class=java.lang.Long</codeblock>
		</section>
	</conbody>
</concept>
