<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE concept PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN" "concept.dtd">
<concept id="concept_3B9C6CE2F64841E98C33D9F6441DF487">
	<title>Configuring the gfsh Environment</title>
	<shortdesc> The <codeph>gfsh.bat</codeph> and <codeph>gfsh</codeph> bash script automatically
		append the required <keyword keyref="product_name_long"/> and JDK .jar libraries to your
		existing CLASSPATH. There are user-configurable properties you can set for security,
		environment variables, logging, and troubleshooting. </shortdesc>
	<conbody>
		<ul id="ul_0919656A8F934C79A71621A41A7603EE">
			<li id="li_2A538F8B747E41B1A22ED2E360BD051C">
				<xref format="dita"
					href="configuring_gfsh.xml#concept_3B9C6CE2F64841E98C33D9F6441DF487/section_0D2EEA7A9ED54DFDB2E1EE955E47921E"
					scope="local" type="section"/>
			</li>
			<li id="li_774BBB8DC2B04E30BFD7AC558C330645">
				<xref format="dita"
					href="configuring_gfsh.xml#concept_3B9C6CE2F64841E98C33D9F6441DF487/section_3FA4CD2B451B4A30A12D30DDE8DF8619"
					scope="local" type="section"/>
			</li>
			<li id="li_FD13CDB809694863B3C5B3FF054462CD">
				<xref format="dita"
					href="configuring_gfsh.xml#concept_3B9C6CE2F64841E98C33D9F6441DF487/section_C69A2711A7664A9091A5E634221053CB"
					scope="local" type="section"/>
			</li>
			<li id="li_195D497B81C94EC191954531C3311C4D">
				<xref format="dita"
					href="configuring_gfsh.xml#concept_3B9C6CE2F64841E98C33D9F6441DF487/section_BE7FB8B355E748FA8BEFE75B2C3CB86E"
					scope="local" type="section"/>
			</li>
			<li id="li_D1CEC0ADA48D438F824184C1E874BCE5">
				<xref format="dita"
					href="configuring_gfsh.xml#concept_3B9C6CE2F64841E98C33D9F6441DF487/section_72323A45E0064FD2982663F7AC2A2E07"
					scope="local" type="section"/>
			</li>
			<li id="li_60972AAC61FC42F6A85A396DF29294CE">
				<xref format="dita"
					href="configuring_gfsh.xml#concept_3B9C6CE2F64841E98C33D9F6441DF487/section_02EEF9A519094EAD9D6B5C8E896EBA27"
					scope="local" type="section"/>
			</li>
		</ul>
		<section id="section_0D2EEA7A9ED54DFDB2E1EE955E47921E">
			<title>JAR Libraries in CLASSPATH</title>
			<p>When you start up <codeph>gfsh</codeph>, it will automatically load required JAR
				files that have been packaged in the <codeph>gfsh-dependencies.jar</codeph> file.
				You do not need to modify your CLASSPATH to run gfsh. When starting servers and
				locators in gfsh, the start server and start locator commands will load
					<codeph>server-dependencies.jar</codeph> and
					<codeph>locator-dependencies.jar</codeph> files into the process CLASSPATH for
				you. </p>
			<p>These dependency JAR files are packaged in your <keyword keyref="product_name_long"/>
				installation in the <codeph>$GEMFIRE/lib</codeph> (or on Windows, the
					<codeph>%GEMFIRE%\lib</codeph>) directory. </p>
			<p>
				<note>The <codeph>gfsh</codeph> command-line utility also searches for
						<codeph>tools.jar</codeph> (included with JDK) and adds it to gfsh's
					CLASSPATH. If you do not have a JDK installed, gfsh uses file-based
					communication instead for the <codeph>status</codeph> and <codeph>stop</codeph>
					commands. If using a JRE instead of JDK, gfsh must have read-write permissions
					in the working directory of the server and locator processes.</note>
			</p>
		</section>
		<section id="section_02EEF9A519094EAD9D6B5C8E896EBA27">
			<title>Machine Hostname</title>
			<p>On some operating systems, you may need to ensure that the hostname of your machine
				is configured in your system hosts file. For example, on Mac OSX you may need to map
				your machine's hostname to your IP address in the <codeph>/etc/hosts</codeph> file
				in order for <codeph>gfsh</codeph> and Pulse to operate correctly. </p>
		</section>
		<section id="section_3FA4CD2B451B4A30A12D30DDE8DF8619">
			<title>Configuring gfsh Security</title>
			<p>Since <codeph>gfsh</codeph> must connect to a JMX Manager member to run certain
				commands (namely those commands that manage and monitor other members), JMX Manager
				configuration properties can affect <codeph>gfsh</codeph> security. In
					<codeph>gemfire.properties</codeph>, the following <keyword
					keyref="product_name"/> properties can affect <codeph>gfsh</codeph> connection
				settings to the JMX Manager: </p>
			<ul id="ul_C73F1EFE4FE6483A93AF39AC38FE6466">
				<li id="li_7541D481F36442C48CE2E40EC8715AED"><codeph>jmx-manager-ssl</codeph>
				</li>
				<li id="li_E330DEF44FD848FDAF7D1456167E4747"><codeph>jmx-manager-port</codeph>
				</li>
				<li id="li_53EC61ED236844478E711B1413603AE9"
						><codeph>jmx-manager-password-file</codeph>
				</li>
				<li id="li_919418BEB3AE4DAFAA3AEA3B369F2D2D"
						><codeph>jmx-manager-access-file</codeph>
				</li>
			</ul>
			<p>You may also need to verify that the ports are available and open to client
				connections. See <xref scope="local"
					href="../../managing/management/jmx_manager_operations.xml#topic_263072624B8D4CDBAD18B82E07AA44B6"
					type="topic" format="dita"><?xm-replace_text Configuring a JMX Manager?></xref>
				for details on these security properties. </p>
		</section>
		<section id="section_C69A2711A7664A9091A5E634221053CB"><title>Configuring gfsh Environment
				Variables</title><p> In addition, you can set several gfsh-specific preset SHELL
				variables by using the <codeph>set variable</codeph> command. For example, you can
				set <codeph>gfsh</codeph> to run in quiet mode. Not all <codeph>gfsh</codeph>
				variables are modifiable; user-configurable variables include: </p><ul
				id="ul_84A76C22977E4DF4B1FC855E9DECA6FC">
				<li id="li_C206E4CB2F7C4E00A49C626CADF950B0">APP_FETCH_SIZE </li>
				<li id="li_FA94186951244726BF88E47C58A3232C">APP_COLLECTION_LIMIT </li>
				<li id="li_4D19347D715E4AF5BCC2FBA4A77A56AF">APP_QUIET_EXECUTION </li>
			</ul> See <xref
				href="useful_gfsh_shell_variables.xml#concept_731ECA5E40E943CBA5C1198A0745D8EE"
				type="concept" format="dita" scope="local"
				><?xm-replace_text Useful gfsh Shell Variables?></xref> for more information. </section>
		<section id="section_BE7FB8B355E748FA8BEFE75B2C3CB86E">
			<title>Configuring gfsh Session Logging</title>
			<p>By default, <codeph>gfsh</codeph> session logging is disabled. To enable gfsh
				logging, you must set the Java system property
						<codeph>-Dgfsh.log-level=<i>desired_log_level</i>
				</codeph>where <i>desired_log _level</i> is one of the following values: severe,
				warning, info, config, fine, finer, finest. For example, in
				Linux:<codeblock>export JAVA_ARGS=-Dgfsh.log-level=info</codeblock></p>
			<p>Then, start <codeph>gfsh</codeph>. </p>
			<p>gfsh produces a log file named <b>gfsh-<i>%u</i>_<i>%g</i>.log</b>. This log file
				records the events of an individual gfsh session. It includes environment
				information, such as Java and system information, and detailed command execution.
				The variables are replaced as follows:</p>
			<ul id="ul_rtr_dpg_y4">
				<li><b>%u</b> - a unique number to resolve conflicts</li>
				<li><b>%g</b> - the generation number to distinguish rotated logs</li>
			</ul>
			<p>gfsh uses the JDK Logger to generate gfsh session log files. See <xref
					href="http://docs.oracle.com/javase/7/docs/api/java/util/logging/FileHandler.html"
					format="html" scope="external"
					>http://docs.oracle.com/javase/7/docs/api/java/util/logging/FileHandler.html</xref>
				for a description of how the variables are used in naming the log file. The default
				name of the generated gfsh log file cannot be changed.</p>
			<p>By default, the log file is written to the current working directory where you have
				executed the <codeph>gfsh</codeph> or <codeph>gfsh.bat</codeph> script. To modify
				the directory location where log files are written, use the
					<codeph>gfsh.log-dir</codeph> Java system property. For
				example:<codeblock>export JAVA_ARGS="-Dgfsh.log-level=info -Dgfsh.log-dir=/machinename/logs"</codeblock>Then,
				start <codeph>gfsh</codeph>.</p>
			<p>In addition, <codeph>gfsh</codeph> records a history of commands in the
					<codeph>${SYS_USER_HOME}/.gemfire/.gfsh.history</codeph> file, which you can use
				to create scripts or review past commands. </p>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Member Log Files</title>
			<p>gfsh writes several log files for any members that are started via gfsh. Useful
				member log files include: <ul id="ul_C2AC6DD6488D46B1BBF5F43BADDC0195">
					<li id="li_5E1BED21C6E34D558AAFC09DC2EB9038"><b>&lt;locator_name&gt;.log</b>.
						Details a locator's configuration (including all gemfire.properties) and all
						activity that occurs on the locator after startup. This log file is written
						to a directory that is named after the locator. For example, if you start a
						locator named locator1, the file is written as <codeph>locator1.log</codeph>
						in the <codeph>&lt;product_dir&gt;/locator1</codeph> directory. </li>
					<li id="li_BD578D2E24DC4E94B5C4E6D773668E39"><b>vf.gf.locator.pid</b>. Contains
						the process ID of the locator. You can use the PID to stop or view the
						status of this locator. This file is written to the same directory location
						as the locator's log file . </li>
					<li id="li_7B9E50F5FC71400688DEE43B47D41687"><b>&lt;server_name&gt;.log</b>.
						Details a server's configuration (including all gemfire.properties) and all
						activity that occurs on the server after startup. This log file is written
						to a directory that is named after the server. For example, if you start a
						server named server1, the file is written as <codeph>server1.log</codeph> in
						the <codeph>&lt;product_dir&gt;/server1</codeph> directory. If you stop and
						start the server with an identical name, the older log files are kept in the
						same directory but renamed for versioning purposes. </li>
					<li id="li_BBF76EF599CF4D3ABD9E551582646FBA"><b>vf.gf.server.pid</b>. Contains
						the process ID of the server. You can use the PID to stop or view the status
						of this server. This file is written to the same location as the server log
						file. </li>
				</ul>
			</p>
		</section>
		<section id="section_jcs_ltx_n4">
			<title>Tab Completion </title>
			<p>
				<i>This section applies only to UNIX installations.</i>
			</p>
			<p>When you run gfsh commands from a UNIX bash shell, you can enable automatic
				tab-completion in the shell by running the following command:</p>
			<codeblock>source &lt;gemfire-install-directory>/bin/gfsh-completion.bash</codeblock>
			<p>After running this command, you can use auto completion when running gfsh commands
				from the bash shell.</p>
			<p>See <xref
					href="getting_started_gfsh.xml#concept_45D28CC9710C4EAFB6EECFA0D651D439/p_sb2_ttx_n4"
					>Using Tab Completion</xref>.</p>
		</section>
		<section id="section_72323A45E0064FD2982663F7AC2A2E07">
			<title>Command History and gfsh.history</title>
			<p>A history of commands that have been executed successfully is logged in
					<codeph>.gfsh.history</codeph> file in a <codeph>.gemfire</codeph> directory
				under the home directory of the user running gfsh. You can also export a history
				file by using the <codeph>history --file=your_file_name</codeph> command. </p>
		</section>
		<section id="section_C84414FF16AB4279A43A41C6C8B61A7E">
			<title>JMX Manager Update Rate and System Monitoring</title>
			<p>When you perform data operations (such as put) and then monitor the state of the
				system (such as using the gfsh <codeph>show metrics</codeph> command or <keyword
					keyref="product_name_long"/> Pulse), the monitored system may not immediately
				reflect the most recent operations. For example, if you perform a put operation and
				then immediately execute the <codeph>show metrics</codeph> gfsh command, you may not
				see the correct number of entries in the region. The management layer updates every
				2 seconds. Wait a few seconds after performing operational activity to see the most
				accurate results. </p>
			<p>You can modify the <codeph>jmx-manager-update-rate</codeph> property in
					<codeph>gemfire.properties</codeph> to increase or decrease the rate (specified
				in milliseconds) at which updates are pushed to the JMX Manager. This property
				setting should be greater than or equal to the
					<codeph>statistic-sample-rate</codeph>. You may want to increase this rate if
				you are experiencing performance issues; however, setting this value too high will
				cause stale values to be seen in <codeph>gfsh</codeph> and <keyword
					keyref="product_name_long"/> Pulse. </p>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Formatting of Results</title>
			<p>
				<i>This section applies only to UNIX installations.</i>
			</p>
			<p>gfsh commands such as <codeph>query</codeph> produce output with wide columns that
				may become misaligned and require manual reformatting to view the output. If the
				output cannot fit in the available width of the terminal, gfsh automatically trims
				the columns widths to fit. You can disable this behavior by setting the gfsh
				environment variable <codeph>GFSH.TRIMSCRWIDTH</codeph> to <codeph>false</codeph>. </p>
			<p>You can set the <codeph>APP_RESULT_VIEWER</codeph> variable to
					<codeph>external</codeph> to enable viewing of the output using the UNIX
					<codeph>less</codeph> command.</p>
			<p>See <xref format="dita"
					href="#concept_3B9C6CE2F64841E98C33D9F6441DF487/section_C69A2711A7664A9091A5E634221053CB"
				/>.</p>
		</section>
	</conbody>
</concept>
