<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE concept PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN" "concept.dtd">
<concept
	id="security">
	<title
		id="title_9717E51087B346988389138843E158C4">FROM Clause</title>
	<shortdesc>The <codeph>FROM</codeph> clause establishes collections of objects that are iterated
		over by the remainder of the query. </shortdesc>
	<conbody>
		<p>The attributes of the objects in these collections are added to the name space scope for
			the remainder of the <codeph>FROM</codeph> clause as well as for the
				<codeph>WHERE</codeph> clause and the <codeph>SELECT</codeph> projection list. </p>
		<p>Each <codeph>FROM</codeph> clause expression must evaluate to a collection. The
			expression <codeph>/portfolios.keySet</codeph> is valid because it evaluates to a
				<codeph>Collection</codeph>, but <codeph>/portfolios.name</codeph>, which evaluates
			to a <codeph>String</codeph> , causes an exception to be thrown. </p>
		<p> Like the SQL query, which iterates over the tables named in its <codeph>FROM</codeph> clause,
			the <codeph>OQL</codeph> query iterates over the <codeph>Collections</codeph>
			established in its <codeph>FROM</codeph> clause. </p>
		<p> In the following query, <codeph>positions.values</codeph> evaluates to a
				<codeph>Collection</codeph> because <codeph>positions</codeph> is a Map, and the
			method values on <codeph>Map</codeph> returns a <codeph>Collection</codeph>. </p>
		<codeblock>IMPORT javaobject.Position;
SELECT DISTINCT "type"
FROM /portfolios, positions.values posnVal TYPE Position
WHERE posnVal.qty &gt; 1000.00</codeblock>
		<p>Every expression in the <codeph>FROM</codeph> clause must evaluate to a
				<codeph>Collection</codeph>. For a Map, the values method returns a
				<codeph>Collection</codeph>. </p>
		<p> If positions were a List instead of a Map , this query could be used to retrieve the
			data: </p>
		<codeblock>IMPORT javaobject.Position;
SELECT DISTINCT "type"
FROM /portfolios, positions posnVal TYPE Position
WHERE posnVal.qty &gt;= 1000.00</codeblock>
		<p>A List is a <codeph>Collection</codeph>, so you can access it directly or through its
				<codeph>toArray</codeph> method. </p>
		<p>For each object type accessed in your <codeph>FROM</codeph> clause, use the method that
			returns a <codeph>Collection</codeph> for that object. </p>
		<p>Each expression in the <codeph>FROM</codeph> clause can be any expression that evaluates
			to a <codeph>Collection</codeph>. An expression in the <codeph>FROM </codeph>clause is
			typically a path expression that resolves to a region in the cache so that the values in
			the region become the collection of objects to filter. </p>
		<p>For example, this is a simple <codeph>SELECT</codeph> statement that evaluates to a set
			of all the entry value objects of the <codeph>region /portfolios</codeph> with active
			status. The collection of entry values provided by the <codeph>FROM</codeph> clause is
			traversed by the <codeph>WHERE</codeph> clause, which accesses each element’s status
			attribute for comparison. </p>
		<codeblock>SELECT DISTINCT * FROM /portfolios WHERE status = 'active'</codeblock>
		<p>If the <codeph>FROM</codeph> clause has only one expression in it, the result of the
			clause is the single collection that the expression evaluates to. If the clause has more
			than one expression in it, the result is a collection of structs that contain a member
			for each of those collection expressions. For example, if the <codeph>FROM</codeph>
			clause contains three expressions that evaluate to collections <codeph>C1, C2,</codeph>
			and <codeph>C3</codeph>, the <codeph>FROM</codeph> clause generates a set of
				<codeph>struct(x1, x2, x3)</codeph> where <codeph>x1, x2</codeph>, and
				<codeph>x3</codeph> represent nested iterations over the collections specified. </p>
		<p>If the collections are independent of each other, this <codeph>struct</codeph> represents
			their cartesian 
product. </p>
		<p>In this query, the <codeph>FROM</codeph> clause produces a <codeph>struct</codeph> of
				<codeph>portfolio</codeph> and position pairs to be iterated. Each element in the
			struct contains the portfolio and one of its contained positions. </p>
		<codeblock>IMPORT javaobject.Position;
SELECT DISTINCT "type" FROM /portfolios, positions TYPE Position
WHERE qty &gt; 1000.00</codeblock>
		<p>To understand the effects of <codeph>FROM</codeph> expressions on query scope, see <xref
				href="../92-querylanguage/22-drilldown-modify-query-scope.xml#security"
				type="concept"
				format="dita"
				scope="local"> Drilling Down for Modifying Query Scope</xref>. </p>
	</conbody>
</concept>
