<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic
	id="topic_849581E507544E63AF23793FBC47D778">
	<title>Advantages of Gemcached over Memcached</title>
	<shortdesc>The standard memcached architecture has inherent architectural challenges that make
		memcached applications difficult to write, maintain, and scale. Using Gemcached with Pivotal
		<keyword keyref="product_name"/> addresses these challenges. </shortdesc>
	<body>
		<p><b>Data consistency</b>. Memcached clients must maintain a list of servers where the
			distributed data is stored. Each client must maintain an identical list, with each list
			ordered in the same way. It is the responsibility of the application logic to maintain
			and propagate this list. If some clients do not have the correct list, the client can
			retrieve stale data. In <keyword keyref="product_name"/> clusters, all members communicate with each other to
			maintain data consistency, which eliminates the need to code these behaviors in the
			memcached clients. </p>
		<p><b>High availability</b>. When a memcached server becomes unavailable, memcached clusters are
			subject to failures or degraded performance because clients must directly query the
			backend database. Memcached-based applications must be coded to handle these failures,
			while <keyword keyref="product_name"/> clusters handle such failures natively. </p>
		<p><b>Faster cluster startup time</b>. When a memcached cluster fails and a restart is
			required, the data must be reloaded and distributed to the cluster members while
			simultaneously processing requests for data. These startup activities can be
			time-consuming. When a <keyword keyref="product_name"/> cluster restarts, data can be reloaded from other
			in-memory, redundant copies of the data or from disk, without having to query the back
			end database. </p>
		<p><b>Better handling of network segmentation</b>. Large deployments of memcached can use
			hundreds of servers to manage data. If, due to network segmentation, some clients cannot
			connect to all nodes of a partition, the clients will have to fetch the data from the
			backend database to avoid hosting stale data. <keyword keyref="product_name"/> clusters handle network
			segmentation to ensure that client responses are consistent. </p>
		<p><b>Automatic scalability</b>. If you need to add capacity to a memcached cluster, you
			must propagate a new server list to all clients. As new clients come on line with the
			new list, older clients may not have a consistent view of the data in the cluster, which
			can result in inconsistent data in the servers. Because new <keyword keyref="product_name"/> cache server members
			automatically discover each other, memcached clients do not need to maintain a complete
			server list. You can add capacity simply by adding servers. </p>
		<p><b>Scalable client connections</b>. A memcached client may need to access multiple pieces
			of data stored on multiple servers, which can result in clients having a TCP connection
			open to every server. When a memcached client accesses a Gemcached server, only a single
			connection to a Gemcached server instance is required. The Gemcached server manages the
			distribution of data using <keyword keyref="product_name"/>'s standard features. </p>
	</body>
</topic>
