<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE dita PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Composite//EN" "ditabase.dtd">
<dita>
	<topic id="transactions_by_region_type">
		<title>Client Transactions</title>
		<body>
			<p>The syntax for writing client transactions is the same on the Java client as with any
				other <keyword keyref="product_name"/> member, but the underlying behavior in a
				client-run transaction is different from general transaction behavior. </p>
			<p>For general information about running a transaction, refer to <xref
					href="run_a_cache_transaction.xml#task_f15_mr3_5k"/>. </p>
		</body>
	</topic>
	<concept id="how_gemfire_runs_clients">
		<title>How <keyword keyref="product_name"/> Runs Client Transactions</title>
		<conbody>
			<p>When a client performs a transaction, the transaction is delegated to a server that
				acts as the transaction initiator in the server system. As with regular, non-client
				transactions, this server delegate may or may not be the transaction host. </p>
			<p>In this figure, the application code on the client (M1) makes changes to data entries
				Y and Z within a transaction. The delegate performing the transaction (M2) does not
				host the primary copy of the data being modified. The transaction takes place on the
				server containing this data (M3). </p>
			<p>
				<image placement="break" id="image_5DCA65F2B88F450299EFD19DAAA93D4F"
					href="../../images_svg/transactions_client_1.svg"/>
			</p>
		</conbody>
	</concept>
	<concept id="client_cache_access">
		<title>Client Cache Access During a Transaction</title>
		<conbody>
			<p>To maintain cache consistency, <keyword keyref="product_name"/> blocks access to the
				local client cache during a transaction. The local client cache may reflect
				information inconsistent with the transaction in progress. When the transaction
				completes, the local cache is accessible again. </p>
		</conbody>
	</concept>
	<concept id="client_app_plugins">
		<title>Client Transactions and Client Application Plug-Ins</title>
		<conbody>
			<p>Any plug-ins installed in the client are not invoked by the client-run transaction.
				The client that initiates the transaction receives changes from its server based on
				transaction operations the same as any other client - through mechanisms like
				subscriptions and continuous query results. The client transaction is performed by
				the server delegate, where application plug-ins operate the same as if the server
				were the sole initiator of the transaction. </p>
		</conbody>
	</concept>
	<concept id="client_transaction_failures">
		<title>Client Transaction Failures</title>
		<conbody>
			<p>In addition to the failure conditions common to all transactions, client transactions
				can fail if the transaction delegate fails. If the delegate performing the
				transaction fails, the transaction code throws a transaction exception. See <xref
					href="monitor_troubleshoot_transactions.xml#monitor_troubleshoot_transactions/section_8942ABA6F23C4ED58877C894B13F4F21"
				/>. </p>
		</conbody>
	</concept>
</dita>
