<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE concept PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN" "http://docs.oasis-open.org/dita/v1.1/OS/dtd/concept.dtd">
<concept id="monitor_troubleshoot_transactions">
	<title>Monitoring and Troubleshooting Transactions</title>
	<shortdesc>This topic covers errors that may occur when running transactions in
		<keyword keyref="product_name"/>.</shortdesc>
	<conbody>
		<section id="section_881D2FF6761B4D689DDB46C650E2A2E1">
			<p>Unlike database transactions, <keyword keyref="product_name"/> does not write a
				transaction log to disk. To get the full details about committed operations, use a
				transaction listener to monitor the transaction events and their contained cache
				events for each of your transactions. </p>
		</section>
		<section id="section_2B66338C851A4FF386B60CC5CF4DCF77">
			<title>Statistics on Cache Transactions</title>
			<p>During the operation of <keyword keyref="product_name"/> cache transactions, if
				statistics are enabled, transaction-related statistics are calculated and accessible
				from the CachePerfStats statistic resource. Because the transaction’s data scope is
				the cache, these statistics are collected on a per-cache basis. </p>
		</section>
		<section id="section_EA9277E6CFD7423F95BA4D04955FDE2A">
			<title>Commit</title>
			<p>In a failed commit, the exception lists the first conflict that caused the failure.
				Other conflicts can exist, but are not reported. </p>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Capacity Limits</title>
			<p>A transaction can create data beyond the capacity limit set in the region’s eviction
				attributes. The capacity limit does not take effect until commit time. Then, any
				required eviction action takes place as part of the commit. </p>
		</section>
		<section id="section_C7588E4F143B4D7FAFAEDCF5AE4FF2C8">
			<title>Interaction with the Resource Manager</title>
			<p>The <keyword keyref="product_name"/> resource manager, which controls overall heap use, either allows all
				transactional operations or blocks the entire transaction. If a cache reaches the
				critical threshold in the middle of a commit, the commit is allowed to finish before
				the manager starts blocking operations. </p>
		</section>
		<section id="section_8942ABA6F23C4ED58877C894B13F4F21">
			<title> Transaction Exceptions</title>
			<p>The following sections list possible transaction exceptions. </p>
			<p>
				<b>Exceptions Indicating Transaction Failure</b>
				<ul id="ul_11226257B29A4CDE9C7F8B352372B228">
					<li id="li_E4F2A4A84B8C457C8F5AD5339E4F984C"
								><b><codeph>TransactionDataNodeHasDepartedException</codeph></b>.
						This exception means the transactional data host has departed unexpectedly.
						Clients and members that run transactions but are not the transactional data
						hosts can get this exception. You can avoid this by working to ensure your
						transactional data hosts are stable and remain running when transactions are
						in progress. </li>
					<li id="li_6438DF05FBB14F95B0A8A78C8E97F331"
								><b><codeph>TransactionDataNotColocatedException</codeph></b>. You
						will get this error if you try to run a transaction on data that is not all
						located in the same member. Partition your data so it is all located in a
						single member. See <xref
							href="cache_transactions_by_region_type.xml#concept_ysk_xj1_wk"/> and
							<xref
							href="../partitioned_regions/custom_partitioning_and_data_colocation.xml#custom_partitioning_and_data_colocation"
							type="concept" format="dita" scope="local"
							><?xm-replace_text How Custom Partitioning and Data Collocation Work?></xref>. </li>
					<li id="li_C7ABE52052774421A578B5E7F783CC07"
								><b><codeph>TransactionDataRebalancedException</codeph></b>. You get
						this error if your transactional data is moved to another member for
						rebalancing during the transaction. Manage your partitioned region data to
						avoid rebalancing during a transaction. See <xref scope="local"
							href="../partitioned_regions/rebalancing_pr_data.xml#rebalancing_pr_data"
							type="concept" format="dita"
							><?xm-replace_text Rebalancing Partitioned Region Data?></xref>. </li>
				</ul>
			</p>
			<p>
				<b>Exceptions Indicating Unknown Transaction Outcome</b>
				<ul id="ul_406ACAAB6E3849C29A4F6697D65555EB">
					<li id="li_B947F5CE88FD46EF85635BE8F0FCBE4C"
								><b><codeph>TransactionInDoubtException</codeph></b>. Some of the
						transactional operations may have succeeded and some may have failed. This
						can happen to clients and to any member running a transaction on another
						data host. To manage this, you may want to install cache listeners in the
						members running the transaction code. Use the listeners to monitor and
						record the changes you receive from your transactions so you can recover as
						needed if you get this exception. </li>
				</ul>
			</p>
		</section>
	</conbody>
</concept>
