<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE concept PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN" "http://docs.oasis-open.org/dita/v1.1/OS/dtd/concept.dtd">
<concept id="run_a_transaction"> 
  <title>Running a Transaction in vFabric GemFire</title> 
  <prolog><metadata><keywords><keyword>gemfire running
			 transactions</keyword><keyword>gemfire transactions</keyword><keyword>gemfire
			 UnsupportedOperationInTransaction</keyword></keywords></metadata>
  </prolog> 
  <conbody> 
	 <section id="section_BE483D79B81C49EE9855F506ED5AB014"> 
		<p>Before you begin, have your members and regions defined where you want
		  to run transactions. If you will use JTA transactions, know how to use them.
		  See 
		  <xref
			href="JTA_transactions_with_GemFire.xml#JTA_transactions_with_GemFire"
			type="concept" format="dita" scope="local"><?xm-replace_text Using JTA Transactions with vFabric GemFire?></xref>
		  for more information on using JTA. 
		</p> 
		<p>You can run transactions on the application’s distributed system or on
		  a server distributed system. If you run your transaction inside a function in
		  the server distributed system, the steps given here apply to the server system.
		  
		<ol id="ol_61EDD679C23F42BFBF3BD6135D8355F4"> 
		  <li id="li_2C9D602F261F4912A3B344836EA43C60">Choose whether to run
			 using the GemFire
			 cache transaction manager or using the JTA transaction manager. The JTA
			 manager, obtained through the JTA 
			 <codeph>UserTransaction</codeph> interface, manages the GemFire
			 transaction and any configured JDBC connection. 
		  </li> 
		  <li id="li_A7C9CE38D8F34DF3930933C947D0C4EB">Configure the cache 
			 <codeph>copy-on-read</codeph> behavior in the members hosting the
			 transactional data, or perform cache updates that avoid in-place changes. This
			 allows the transaction manager to control when your cache updates are visible
			 outside the transaction. 
		  </li> 
		  <li id="li_A539C20E9DAD432CA7BC9710BC4850AA">In the members hosting the
			 transactional data, configure your regions for your transactions: 
			 <ol id="ol_334FF4E9D13541FBB9C69992591BE439"> 
				<li id="li_6ADAD3E5D5D44D8D9416AF92D2E8C8FF">For replicated
				  regions, use 
				  <codeph>distributed-ack</codeph> scope. The region shortcuts
				  specifying 
				  <codeph>REPLICATE</codeph> use 
				  <codeph>distributed-ack</codeph> scope. This is particularly
				  important if you have more than one data producer. With one data producer, you
				  can safely use 
				  <codeph>distributed-no-ack</codeph>. 
				</li> 
				<li id="li_9C35A9732ACB4DB19A25176FDEC487EE">For partitioned
				  regions, custom partition and colocate data between regions so all the data for
				  any single transaction is hosted by a single data store. If you run the
				  transaction from another member, it will run by proxy in the member hosting the
				  data. The partitioned region must be defined for the application that runs the
				  transaction, but the data can be hosted in a remote member. 
				</li> 
				<li id="li_7B99D30902F5467293AADFF31B95675C">For mixed partition
				  and replicated region transactions, make sure your replicated regions are
				  hosted in every member that hosts the partitioned region data. All data for a
				  single transaction must reside in a single host. 
				</li> 
				<li id="li_4F56475DC827470BB0B1E91B0A80353F">If you use delta
				  propagation, set the region attribute 
				  <codeph>cloning-enabled</codeph> to true. This lets GemFire
				  do conflict checks at commit. Without this, when you run the transaction,
				  you'll get this exception: 
				  <codeblock>UnsupportedOperationInTransactionException("Delta without 
cloning cannot be used in transaction");</codeblock> 
				</li> 
				<li id="li_A56830CB1814491CAE37C4A477868316">If you use JTA and
				  want any regions to not participate in the transactions, set the region
				  attribute 
				  <codeph>ignore-jta</codeph> to true. It is false by default. 
				</li> 
			 </ol> 
		  </li> 
		  <li id="li_79F342421DA643B8A3C4434EB7C65C33">Update your event handler
			 implementations in your data stores to handle your transactions. 
			 <ol id="ol_FEBB841FBDDF469FA19AB972FA1F4005"> 
				<li id="li_D4B653ED09D64D298B645AC2473E5122">Cache event handlers
				  are all used for transactions. Cache listeners are called after the commit,
				  instead of after each cache operation, and they receive the conflated
				  transaction events. Cache writers and loaders are called as usual, as the
				  operations are done. Follow these additional guidelines when writing your
				  callbacks: 
				  <ul id="ul_0786C96FA4A841D7A8743065330BB9F1"> 
					 <li id="li_348436A0BD0B449B996F167C0D515241">Make sure cache
						callbacks are transactionally aware. A transactional operation can launch
						callbacks that are not transactional. 
					 </li> 
					 <li id="li_06F79EEEA4534824A5DBD59CCECCB20A">Make sure cache
						listeners will operate properly with the entry event conflation done for
						transactional operations. Two entry events for the same key are conflated by
						removing the existing event and adding the new event to the end of the list. 
					 </li> 
				  </ul> 
				</li> 
				<li id="li_AB5410FC58804224810B2B9A70C40A0D">Transaction event
				  handlers are cache-wide. You can install one transaction writer and any number
				  of transaction listeners. 
				  <ul id="ul_D244D90A636A44AEB9FACCB320E98147"> 
					 <li id="li_A93E770B30AC4BF6955AE80D8D8C2C1E">Program with
						synchronization for thread-safety. Your listener and writer methods may be
						called simultaneously by different threads for different transactions. 
					 </li> 
					 <li id="li_70A37FF10271479FAC43DA4C4825D140">Keep your
						transactional callback implementations lightweight and avoid doing anything
						that might cause them to block. 
					 </li> 
				  </ul> 
				</li> 
			 </ol> 
		  </li> 
		  <li id="li_393BAF270C62421182D27C07E4CB372C">Program to retrieve the
			 transaction manager. 
			 <ul id="ul_A770CE71D4DB4325B115947DC8D7028F"> 
				<li id="li_550C3B7B311646E88C4C17B25467EF78">GemFire
				  cache transaction manager: 
				  <codeblock>CacheTransactionManager txManager =
		  custRegion.getCache().getCacheTransactionManager();</codeblock> 
				</li> 
				<li id="li_3E46C8FB3B1F451C85C5BDC4E4CD4FB4">JTA transaction
				  manager: 
				  <codeblock>Context ctx = cache.getJNDIContext(); 
UserTransaction txManager = 
		  (UserTransaction)ctx.lookup("java:/UserTransaction");</codeblock> 
				</li> 
			 </ul> 
		  </li> 
		  <li id="li_A362B16AB53444AC908EEFF403142711">Program to run your
			 transaction. 
			 <codeblock>try {
		txManager.begin();
		// ... do work
		txManager.commit();
} catch (CommitConflictException conflict) 
</codeblock> 
			 <ol id="ol_78FFB47BA9684E238CC13E8AE4B96735"> 
				<li id="li_EA1F9BCEE77B48C1B5C5F2522308E497">Start each transaction
				  with a begin operation. 
				</li> 
				<li id="li_E1D4CD60A00F4E1CB288349305344A79">Run the GemFire
				  function and other operations that you want included in the transaction. 
				  <ul id="ul_6E38A7601D6D437BA6D2DF007A41E5AE"> 
					 <li id="li_883ED03ABE394D2DA9275ACE4A5AC61B">Consider whether
						you will want to suspend and resume the transaction. If some operations should
						not be part of the transaction, you may want to suspend the transaction while
						performing non-transactional operations. After the non-transactional operations
						are complete, you can resume the transaction. See 
						<xref
						href="transaction_suspend_resume_example.xml#concept_40AAC4332DCE4E4EB60C4BA141B729A4"
						type="concept" format="dita" scope="local"><?xm-replace_text Basic Suspend and Resume Transaction Example?></xref>
						for an example. 
					 </li> 
					 <li id="li_ECD16D53C0654072882274DC4169FFA5">If your
						transaction runs on a mix of partitioned and replicated regions, perform your
						first transaction operation on a partitioned region. This sets the host for the
						entire transaction. 
					 </li> 
					 <li id="li_374C1139316148A9B6A5D7DE36D441A3">If you did not
						configure 
						<codeph>copy-on-read</codeph> to true, be sure your cache
						updates avoid in-place changes. 
					 </li> 
					 <li id="li_5733C57F7F86417F836F5B9DC9DCA947">Take into account
						the behavior of transactional and non-transactional operations. All
						transactional operations that are run after the begin and before the commit or
						rollback are included in the transaction. 
					 </li> 
				  </ul> 
				</li> 
				<li id="li_7E7F811732C54BF6A45663B14F39D539">End each transaction
				  with a commit or a rollback. 
				  <note>Do not leave any transaction in an uncommitted and unrolled
					 back state. Transactions do not time out, so will remain in the system for the
					 life of your application. 
				  </note> 
				</li> 
			 </ol> 
		  </li> 
		  <li id="li_2AE6D7C5391A49AF9C7FF2D4AC95F5F6">Review all of your code
			 for compatibility with transactions. 
			 <p>When you commit a transaction, while the commit is taking place,
				the changes are visible in the distributed cache. This capability is a
				transition commit. This provides better performance than locking everything to
				do the transaction updates, but it means that another process accessing data
				used in the transaction might get some data in the pre-transaction state and
				some in the post-transaction state. For example, suppose key 1 and 2 are
				written to in a transaction so both of their values change from A to B. In
				another thread, it is possible to read key 1 with value B and key 2 with value
				A, while the transaction is being committed. This is possible due to the nature
				of GemFire
				reads. This choice sacrifices atomic visibility in favor of performance; reads
				do not block writes, and writes do not block reads. 
			 </p>
		  </li> 
		</ol> 
		</p> 
	 </section> 
  </conbody> 
</concept> 
