<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE concept PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN" "concept.dtd">
<!-- Created with XMetaL (http://www.xmetal.com) -->
<concept id="concept_358B057798FB4DFCB60F5C54ADC98776"> 
  <title>Suspending and Resuming Transactions</title> 
  <shortdesc>
  </shortdesc> 
  <prolog><metadata><keywords><keyword>gemfire suspend
			 transactions</keyword><keyword>gemfire resume
			 transactions</keyword></keywords></metadata>
  </prolog> 
  <conbody> 
	 <section id="section_FFED162EEF8E4B04BFEC7C0495CEEA2F"> 
		<p> vFabric GemFire APIs provide the ability to suspend and resume
		  transactions. The ability to suspend and resume is useful when a thread must
		  perform some operations that should not be part of the transaction before the
		  transaction can complete. 
		</p> 
		<p>When a transaction is suspended, it loses the transactional view of
		  the cache. None of the previous operations (before calling suspend) are visible
		  to the thread. Subsequently any operations that are performed by the thread do
		  not participate in the suspended transaction. 
		</p> 
		<p> When a transaction is resumed, the resuming thread assumes the
		  transactional view. A transaction that is suspending on a member must be
		  resumed on the same member. Before resuming a transaction, you may want to
		  check if the transaction exists on the member and whether it is suspended. You
		  may optionally use the 
		  <codeph>tryResume</codeph> method. 
		</p> 
		<p>If the member with the primary copy of the data crashes, the
		  transactional view that applied to that data is lost. The secondary member for
		  the data will not be able to resume any transactions suspended on the crashed
		  member. You will need to take remedial steps to retry the transaction on a new
		  primary copy of the data. 
		</p> 
		<p>If a suspended transaction is not touched for a period of time,
		  GemFire cleans it up automatically. By default, the timeout for a suspended
		  transaction is 30 minutes and can be configured using the system property 
		  <codeph>gemfire.suspendedtxTimeout</codeph>. For example, to modify the
		  default, you could set 
		  <codeph>gemfire.suspendedtxTimeout=60</codeph> (time in minutes). 
		</p> 
		<p>See 
		  <xref
			href="transaction_suspend_resume_example.xml#concept_40AAC4332DCE4E4EB60C4BA141B729A4"
			type="concept" format="dita" scope="local"><?xm-replace_text Basic Suspend and Resume Transaction Example?></xref>
		  for an example of how to suspend and resume a transaction. 
		</p> 
	 </section> 
  </conbody>
</concept>
