<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE concept PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN" "http://docs.oasis-open.org/dita/v1.1/OS/dtd/concept.dtd">
<concept id="transaction_semantics">
	<title><keyword keyref="product_name"/> Cache Transaction Semantics</title>
	<conbody>
		<p><keyword keyref="product_name"/> transaction semantics differs in some ways from the
			semantics of traditional relational databases. </p>
		<section id="section_8362ACD06C784B5BBB0B7E986F760169">
			<title>Atomicity</title>
			<p>A common database technique to achieve atomicity is two-phase locking on rows. This
				provides coordination between the current transaction and other transactions with
				overlapping changes. Holding write locks prevents reads of transactional changes
				until all changes are complete, providing all or nothing behavior. If problems occur
				during a transaction, perhaps due to relational constraints or storage limitations,
				the locks protect other processes from reading until the problems can be resolved.
				The resolution often involves reverting data back to the original pre-transaction
				state. Rolling back a database transaction in this case would require releasing
				write locks. </p>
			<p>A common distributed technique for all or nothing behavior is the Two Phase Commit
				Protocol, which requires all processes participating in the transaction to agree to
				commit or abort the transaction. </p>
			<p>The all or nothing behavior of <keyword keyref="product_name"/> transactions is
				implemented using a per thread transaction state which collects all transactional
				changes. The set of Entry changes are atomically reserved by a reservation system.
				The reservation blocks other, intersecting transactions from proceeding, allowing
				the commit to check for conflicts and reserve resources in an all-or-nothing fashion
				prior to making changes to the data. </p>
			<p>Since <keyword keyref="product_name"/> is distributed, the transaction state is
				distributed to the appropriate members and processed in a batch, to protect against
				application failure in the middle of the commit. After all changes have been made,
				locally and remotely, the reservation is released. </p>
			<p>Rolling back the transaction is as simple as discarding the transaction state. </p>
			<p>Reads do not use the reservation system and so are very fast. </p>
			<p>This system has traits similar to the Multiversion Concurrency Control algorithm: <ul
					id="ul_93036FFA8B3D4543AEE40C101171CF89">
					<li id="li_48B918945E7B44F4B1586575B53BA0DA">Each thread can write new versions
						of entry data without impacting read performance </li>
					<li id="li_0C58F6573FD64C928E5FAE04BFFAA221">Reads view only the most recent
						committed version of an entry </li>
				</ul>
			</p>
		</section>
		<section id="section_7C287DA4A5134780B3199CE074E3F890">
			<title>Consistency</title>
			<p>Database consistency is often described in terms of referential integrity. References
				between tables are often described in terms of primary and foreign key constraints.
				A database transaction that updates multiple columns, potentially in different
				tables, must ensure that all updates are completed to maintain consistency in an
				atomic fashion. </p>
			<p>For <keyword keyref="product_name"/> the application controls the consistency between
				regions and their entries. <keyword keyref="product_name"/> transactions use the
				reservation system to ensure that changes to all entries in all regions are
				committed. Once a reservation is obtained, <keyword keyref="product_name"/> does a
				conflict check to ensure that the entries scheduled for change are in the same state
				as they were when the transaction first accessed them. </p>
		</section>
		<section id="section_126A24EC499D4CF39AE766A0B526A9A5">
			<title>Isolation</title>
			<p><keyword keyref="product_name"/> isolates transactions at the process thread level.
				So while a transaction is in progress, its changes are only visible inside the
				thread that is running the transaction. Threads inside the same process and in other
				processes do not see the changes until after the commit finishes. Relational
				database transactions often isolate changes per JDBC connection. </p>
			<p><keyword keyref="product_name"/> reads, like get and getEntry, are volatile, meaning
				they do not use locks. This makes reads very fast with respect to other entry
				operations. It also allows transactional writes to proceed without being slowed down
				by in-progress reads. </p>
			<p>Visibility, related to isolation, is the atomic nature in which committed writes are
				viewable by read operations. Reads during a <keyword keyref="product_name"/>
				transaction have repeatable read isolation, so once the committed value reference is
				read for a given key, it always returns the same reference. If a transaction write,
				like put or invalidate, deletes a value for a key that has already been read,
				subsequent reads return the transactional reference. </p>
		</section>
		<section id="section_F092E368724945BCBF8E5DCB36B97EB4">
			<title>Durability</title>
			<p>Relational databases provide durability by using disk storage for recovery and
				transaction logging. <keyword keyref="product_name"/> does not support on-disk or
				in-memory durability for transactions. </p>
		</section>
	</conbody>
</concept>
