<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE concept PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN" "concept.dtd">
<concept
	id="subscription-properties">
	<title>Subscription Properties</title>
	<shortdesc>Each connection pool has a single subscription connection that can be to any server
		that matches the requirements of the connection pool. </shortdesc>
	<conbody>
		<p>When a client registers interest for a region, if the connection pool does not already
			have a subscription channel, the connection pool sends a message to the server locator,
			and the server locator chooses servers to host the queue and return those server names
			to the client. The client then contacts the chosen servers and asks them to create the
			queue. </p>
		<p>The client maintains at least one connection with each server hosting a queue. If the
			server does not detect any connections from a non-durable client, it drops the client
			queue and closes all artifacts for the client. For information about durable client
			subscriptions, see <xref
				href="../preserving-data/durable-client-messaging.xml#concept_F88B659FB4324F599924F3F2933452B4"
				type="concept"
				format="dita"
				scope="local">Durable Client Messaging</xref>. </p>
		<section
			id="section_294BD33FBDC6454FAD9C5118829EBBA4">
			<title>Requesting a Subscription Region Queue</title>
			<p>The client-to-server locator request is a short lived TCP request. The client sends a
				message with: </p>
				<ul
					id="ul_FB17074E2A644B348E7E4A57CAF59947">
					<li
						id="li_6BC48DC8477E4622BE14EA0F6BE9EDA0">The client ID. </li>
					<li
						id="li_1A2F8F17EE30479E90AA7ABCA0B1CE06">(Optional) target server group. </li>
					<li
						id="li_1C77F0DD667F4D588198E0F16DEBF09A">Number of redundant copies. </li>
					<li
						id="li_94DC2B68E6E4494C81E6F60742AA1B69">Servers to exclude from the
						results. This list is used if the client cannot connect to a server and
						needs to request a new one. </li>
				</ul>
			<p>The server locator responds with a list of servers. The client is responsible for
				contacting the primary and secondaries and asking them to host the queue. </p>
			<p>For durable subscriptions, the server locator must be able to locate the servers that
				host the queues for the durable client. When a durable client sends a request, the
				server locator queries all the available servers to see if they are hosting the
				subscription region queue for the durable client. If the server is located, the
				client is connected to the server hosting the subscription region queue. </p>
		</section>
	</conbody>
</concept>
