<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE concept PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN" "concept.dtd">
<concept
    id="concept_i5g_3d5_m4">
    <title>Prerequisites and Limitations for Writing REST Applications</title>
    <shortdesc>Before development, understand the prerequisites and limitations of the current REST
        implementation in <keyword keyref="product_name"/>. </shortdesc>
    <conbody>
        <p><keyword keyref="product_name"/> and REST-enabled applications accessing <keyword keyref="product_name"/> are subject to the following
            rules and limitations:</p>
        <ul
            id="ul_wtz_ccv_44">
            <li>All domain objects, functions and function-arg classes must be properly configured
                and registered in the <keyword keyref="product_name"/> deployment. Any functions that you wish to execute
                through the REST API must be available on the target member’s CLASSPATH. </li>
            <li>The current implementation only supports the <b>application/json</b> MIME type. At
                time of publication, any other return types (XML, objects, and so on) are not
                supported. Plain text is supported as a return type for some error messages.</li>
            <li>Keys are strictly of type String for this release. For example, the request
                    <codeph>PUT http://localhost:8080/gemfire-api/v1/customers/123.456</codeph> will
                add entry for key ("123.456") of type String.</li>
            <li>Some special formats of JSON documents are not supported in <keyword keyref="product_name"/> REST. See <xref
                    href="troubleshooting.xml#concept_gsv_zd5_m4"/> for examples.</li>
            <li>To achieve interoperability between <keyword keyref="product_name"/> Java clients (or <keyword keyref="product_name"/> native clients)
                and REST clients, the following rules must be followed:<ul
                    id="ul_vxs_lcp_p4">
                    <li>All <keyword keyref="product_name"/> Java and native client classes operating on data also accessed
                        by the REST interface must be PDX serialized either via PDX
                        autoserialization or by implementing <codeph>PdxSerializable</codeph>.</li>
                    <li><keyword keyref="product_name"/> Java clients and native clients can retrieve REST-enabled data
                        either as a <codeph>PdxInstance</codeph> or as an actual object by using the
                            <codeph>PdxInstance.getObject</codeph> method. If you use the latter
                        method, first you must declare the object type (@type) in your POST or PUT
                        request payload when creating the object in REST; and secondly, the Java
                        client must have the actual domain class in its CLASSPATH.</li>
                </ul></li>
            <li>Objects returned by REST-invoked functions must be returned as PdxInstance objects
                or other data types that can be written to JSON. You cannot return Java
                objects.</li>
            <li>REST client applications do not support single hop access or notification
                features.</li>
            <li>Specifying subregions as endpoints is not currently supported. </li>
        </ul>
    </conbody>
</concept>
