<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE concept PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN" "http://docs.oasis-open.org/dita/dtd/concept.dtd">
<concept id="changing_gemfire_default_cfg">
	<title>Changing <keyword keyref="product_name_long"/> Default Configuration (Hibernate Cache
		Module)</title>
	<shortdesc>To edit <keyword keyref="product_name"/> configuration information (such as how
		members locate each other), you can add <keyword keyref="product_name"/> properties to
		Hibernate's <codeph>hibernate.cfg.xml</codeph> file. </shortdesc>
	<conbody>
		<p>When adding properties, use the following syntax: </p>
		<codeblock>&lt;property name="gemfire.PROPERTY_NAME"&gt;PROPERTY_VALUE&lt;/property&gt;</codeblock>
		<p>In the preceding code snippet, <codeph>PROPERTY_NAME</codeph> is the property name and
				<codeph>PROPERTY_VALUE</codeph> is the property value. The list of configurable
			system properties include any of the properties that can be specified in <keyword
				keyref="product_name"/>'s <codeph>gemfire.properties</codeph> file. The property
			changes associated with the most common configurations are described below. </p>
		<section id="changing_gemfire_topology">
			<title>Changing the <keyword keyref="product_name"/> Topology</title>
			<p>By default, the topology is set for a peer-to-peer configuration rather than a
				client/server configuration. To use the peer-to-peer configuration, you don't have
				to make any changes. If you want to change the configuration to a client/server
				topology, edit the Hibernate configuration file: </p>
			<codeblock>&lt;property name="gemfire.cache-topology"&gt;client-server&lt;/property&gt;</codeblock>
			<p>Since the Hibernate process operates as a <keyword keyref="product_name"/> client in
				this configuration, you must manually launch a <keyword keyref="product_name"/>
				cache server. You can do this with the following script (which should be installed
				into the <b>bin</b> subdirectory wherever <keyword keyref="product_name"/> is
				located): </p>
			<codeblock>In Unix: 
  prompt$ ./cacheserver.sh start
  
In Windows:
  prompt&gt; cacheserver.bat start</codeblock>
			<note>When running the cache server, make sure the Hibernate jar and the <keyword
					keyref="product_name"/> modules jar are in the classpath, along with any
				dependencies. You can use the CLASSPATH environment variable or you can set the
					<codeph>-classpath &lt;classpath&gt;</codeph> command line argument when
				launching the cache server. </note>Without making any further configuration changes,
			the client and server attempt to locate each other on the same system using a default
			port (40404). Though useful for testing purposes, you would not normally deploy a
			client/server configuration in this way. Refer to "Using <keyword keyref="product_name"
			/> Locators with a Client/Server Configuration" for information on creating and using
			Locators, which provide both discovery and load balancing services. </section>
		<section id="changing_p2p_region_atts">
			<title>Changing Peer-to-Peer Region Attributes</title>
			<p>You can change the region attributes from within the
					<codeph>hibernate.cfg.xml</codeph> file using the same region shortcuts
				specified in <xref
					href="../../basic_config/data_regions/region_shortcuts.xml#region_shortcuts"
					type="concept" format="dita" scope="local"
					><?xm-replace_text Region Shortcuts and Custom Named Region Attributes?></xref>.
				<codeblock>&lt;property name="gemfire.default-region-attributes-id"&gt;
  REGION_ATTRIBUTE
&lt;/property&gt; </codeblock>
			</p>
			<p>In this example, <codeph>REGION_ATTRIBUTE</codeph> can be any of the pre-defined
				region shortcuts. By default, this is REPLICATE_HEAP_LRU. Other available region
				shortcuts include: REPLICATE, REPLICATE_PERSISTENT, PARTITION, PARTITION_PERSISTENT,
				PARTITION_REDUNDANT, PARTITION_REDUNDANT_PERSISTENT. If you plan to configure a
				region for persistence, refer to <xref format="dita"
					href="changing_gemfire_default_cfg.xml#changing_gemfire_default_cfg/turning_on_persistence"
					scope="local">Turning On Persistence</xref>. </p>
			<p>You can also control the region type on a per-entity basis using the following code: </p>
			<codeblock>&lt;property name="gemfire.region-attributes-for: com.foo.Bar"&gt;
  REGION_ATTRIBUTE
&lt;/property&gt; </codeblock>
			<p>In this example, com.foo.Bar is the name of your class and REGION_ATTRIBUTE can be
				one of the region shortcuts. </p>
		</section>
		<section id="using_diff_mc_port_with_pp">
			<title>Using a Different Multicast Port with a Peer-to-Peer Configuration</title>
			<p>For a <keyword keyref="product_name"/> peer-to-peer member to communicate on a
				different multicast port than the default (10334), use the
					<codeph>mcast-port</codeph> property. </p>
			<codeblock>&lt;property name="gemfire.mcast-port"&gt;10445&lt;/property&gt; </codeblock>This
			example uses port 10445 as the multicast port. </section>
		<section id="using_locators_with_pp_cfg">
			<title>Using <keyword keyref="product_name"/> Locators with a Peer-to-Peer
				Configuration</title>
			<p>By default, <keyword keyref="product_name"/> peers discover each other using
				multicast communication on a known port (as specified by the
					<codeph>mcast-port</codeph> property). Alternatively, you can configure member
				discovery using one or more dedicated locators. A locator provides both discovery
				and load balancing services. </p>
			<p>To run <keyword keyref="product_name"/> with one or more locators instead of a
				multicast port, use the <codeph>locators </codeph>property. </p>
			<codeblock>&lt;property name="gemfire.locators"&gt;host1[port1],host2[port2]&lt;/property&gt; </codeblock>
			<p>In this example, <codeph>host1</codeph> and <codeph>host2 </codeph>are the hostnames
				(or IP addresses) for each of the locators; <codeph>port1</codeph> and <codeph>port2
				</codeph>are the ports for each of the locators. </p>
			<p>Although this code will tell the peer to look for a locator, it does not
				automatically start the locator. To launch a locator automatically within the same
				application as the one running the Hibernate process, use this code, with your
				hostname (or IP address) and port settings: </p>
			<codeblock>&lt;property name="gemfire.start-locator"&gt;host[port]&lt;/property&gt; </codeblock>
			<p>Alternatively, you can start a locator in a separate process using the
					<codeph>gemfire</codeph> command-line tool found in the <codeph>bin
				</codeph>subdirectory wherever <keyword keyref="product_name"/> is located. </p>
			<codeblock>In Unix:
  ./gemfire.sh start-locator -port=10334
  
In Windows:
  gemfire.bat start-locator -port=10334</codeblock>
			<p>This example starts a locator that listens on port 10334. </p>
		</section>
		<section id="section_1AB292DC8D0B420DABFD2120A38FEDB4">
			<title>
				<b>Changing Region Names</b>
			</title>
			<p> By default, the <keyword keyref="product_name"/> Hibernate module puts entities in a
				region whose name is the fully qualified path of the entity. The module uses these
				region names to eagerly prefetch related entities. Therefore, we recommend that you
				do not change the default names of the regions that are created by Hibernate. </p>
		</section>
		<section id="changing_cs_region_atts">
			<title>Changing Client/Server Region Attributes</title>
			<p>When using a client/server configuration, the default region attribute for the
					<keyword keyref="product_name"/> servers is a PARTITION region. This means that
				the data is partitioned across the pool of <keyword keyref="product_name"/> servers.
				You can modify this behavior using the same instructions specified in <xref
					format="dita"
					href="changing_gemfire_default_cfg.xml#changing_gemfire_default_cfg/changing_p2p_region_atts"
					scope="local">Changing Peer-to-Peer Region Attributes</xref>. </p>
			<p>In addition to the region attribute of the servers, you can also modify the region
				attributes for the <keyword keyref="product_name"/> client, which is the process
				running Hibernate. By default this region is set to PROXY. This means that the
				client will not cache data. </p>
			<p>You can change the client region attributes from within the hibernate.cfg.xml file
				using the same client region shortcuts specified in <xref
					href="../../basic_config/data_regions/region_shortcuts.xml#region_shortcuts"
					type="concept" format="dita" scope="local"
					><?xm-replace_text Region Shortcuts and Custom Named Region Attributes?></xref>. </p>
			<codeblock>&lt;property name="gemfire.default-client-region-attributes-id"&gt;
  CLIENT_REGION_ATTRIBUTE
&lt;/property&gt; </codeblock>
			<p>In this example, CLIENT_REGION_ATTRIBUTE can be any of the pre-defined region
				shortcuts. By default, this is PROXY. If you would like the client to keep a local
				cache of recently used data, change the region to CACHING_PROXY. </p>
			<p>You can also control the client region type on a per-entity basis using the following
				code: </p>
			<codeblock>&lt;property name="gemfire.client-region-attributes-for: com.foo.Bar"&gt;
  CLIENT_REGION_ATTRIBUTE
&lt;/property&gt; </codeblock>
			<p>In this example, com.foo.Bar is the name of your class and CLIENT_REGION_ATTRIBUTE
				can be one of the client region shortcuts. </p>
		</section>
		<section id="section_57B3FEAFF926487DAF368D67FFE59E1B">
			<title id="using_locators_with_cs_cfg">Using <keyword keyref="product_name"/> Locators
				with a Client/Server Configuration</title>
			<p>By default, <keyword keyref="product_name"/> clients and servers discover each other
				on a pre-defined port (40404) on the localhost. This is not typically the way you
				would deploy a client/server configuration. A preferred solution is to use one or
				more dedicated locators. A locator provides both discovery and load balancing
				services. </p>
			<p>To run <keyword keyref="product_name"/> with one or more locators, use the
					<codeph>locators</codeph> property. </p>
			<codeblock>&lt;property name="gemfire.locators"&gt;host1[port1],host2[port2]&lt;/property&gt; </codeblock>
			<p>In this example, <codeph>host1</codeph> and <codeph>host2</codeph> are the hostnames
				(or IP addresses) for each of the locators; <codeph>port1</codeph> and
					<codeph>port2</codeph> are the ports for each of the locators. </p>
			<p>Although this code will tell the <b>client</b> to look for a locator, it does not
				automatically start the locator. You can start a locator using the
					<codeph>gemfire</codeph> command-line tool found in the <codeph>bin</codeph>
				subdirectory wherever <keyword keyref="product_name"/> is located. </p>
			<codeblock>In Unix:
  ./gemfire.sh start-locator -port=10334
  
In Windows:
  gemfire.bat start-locator -port=10334</codeblock>
			<p>This example starts a locator that listens on port 10334. </p>
			<p>You also need to tell the <keyword keyref="product_name"/>
				<b>server</b> to use a locator when you launch the server. You can do this through a
				command-line argument when you start up the server with the script provided in the
					<codeph>bin</codeph> subdirectory wherever <keyword keyref="product_name"/> is
				located: </p>
			<codeblock>In Unix: 
  prompt$ ./cacheserver.sh start locators=hostname[port]
  
In Windows:
  prompt&gt; cacheserver.bat start locators=hostname[port]</codeblock>
			<p>If you are running more than one locator, use a comma-separated list of locators.
				Refer to <xref
					href="../../configuring/running/running_the_cacheserver.xml#running_the_cacheserver"
					type="concept" format="dita" scope="local"/> for more information on using this
				script. </p>
			<note>When running the cache server, make sure the Hibernate jar and the <keyword
					keyref="product_name"/> modules jar are in the classpath, along with any
				dependencies. You can use the CLASSPATH environment variable or you can set the
					<codeph>-classpath &lt;classpath&gt;</codeph> command line argument when
				launching the cache server. </note>
		</section>
		<section id="turning_on_persistence">
			<title>Turning On Persistence</title>
			<p>If you change the region type to any one of the persistent modes (such as
				PARTITION_PERSISTENT and REPLICATE_PERSISTENT), cache data will get stored into the
				current working directory. To change this location, supply disk storage information
				in <keyword keyref="product_name"/>'s <codeph>cache.xml</codeph> configuration file.
				For example: </p>
			<codeblock>&lt;cache&gt;
  &lt;!-- define a disk store with a couple of directories. --&gt;
  &lt;!-- All data logs are stored here --&gt;
 &lt;disk-store name="CacheDataRepository"&gt;
  &lt;disk-dirs&gt;
    &lt;disk-dir&gt;c:\cache_data&lt;/disk-dir&gt;
    &lt;disk-dir dir-size="20480"&gt;d:\cache_data&lt;/disk-dir&gt;
  &lt;/disk-dirs&gt;
 &lt;/disk-store&gt;

 &lt;!-- now change the predefined region attributes to use this disk store --&gt; 
 &lt;region-attributes id="MYAPP_PARTITION_PERSISTENT" 
      ref-id="PARTITION_PERSISTENT"&gt;
   &lt;disk-store&gt;CacheDataRepository&lt;/disk-store&gt;
 &lt;/region-attributes&gt;
&lt;/cache&gt; 
</codeblock>
			<p>This example creates a 20480 MB data repository in the <codeph>d:\cache_data</codeph>
				subdirectory. It also defines a region attribute called MYAPP_PARTITION_PERSISTENT,
				which is derived from the PARTITION_PERSISTENT region definition. </p>
			<p>You must also change Hibernate's <codeph>hibernate.cfg.xml</codeph> file to point to
				this xml file and to reference this particular region definition: </p>
			<codeblock>&lt;property name="gemfire.default-region-attributes-id"&gt;  
  MYAPP_PARTITION_PERSISTENT
&lt;/property&gt; 
&lt;property name="gemfire.cache-xml-file"&gt;
  c:\gemfire_cache.xml
&lt;/property&gt; </codeblock>
		</section>
		<section id="section_6F67CECB091948129081FDD34B892F91">
			<title>
				<b>Caching Query Results</b>
			</title>
			<p> In a Hibernate application, the caching of query results is recommended for queries
				that are run frequently with the same parameters. However, most applications using
				Hibernate do not benefit from query results caching because Hibernate will
				invalidate cached results when even a single entity involved in the query is
				updated. For example, suppose that a query on the Person entity is cached. As soon
				as any instance of Person is updated, created or deleted, Hibernate will invalidate
				this query because it cannot predict the impact of the change on the cached query
				results. Therefore, the <keyword keyref="product_name"/> Hibernate Cache Module does
				not distribute query results to other <keyword keyref="product_name"/> member
				caches. The query results are always cached only in the <keyword
					keyref="product_name"/> cache local to the Hibernate session. </p>
		</section>
		<section id="section_E884BF4251D6494695408B30D1F350B1">
			<title>Remapping the Hibernate EnumType with the <keyword keyref="product_name"/>
				EnumType</title>
			<p> Due to an issue with Hibernate in a client-server topology, application classes must
				be present on the <keyword keyref="product_name"/> cache server when a Hibernate
				application uses annotations. If you do not want to place the application classes on
				the <keyword keyref="product_name"/> cache server, you can modify the Hibernate
				configuration to use the
					<codeph>com.gemstone.gemfire.modules.hibernate.EnumType</codeph> in place of
					<codeph>org.hibernate.type.EnumType</codeph>. </p>
			<p>To configure Hibernate to use the <keyword keyref="product_name"/> EnumType, modify
					<codeph>hibernate.cfg.xml</codeph> to add a property for the mapping. For
				example:
				<codeblock>&lt;property name="myEnum"&gt;
    &lt;type name="<b>com.gemstone.gemfire.modules.hibernate.EnumType</b>"&gt;
    &lt;param name="enumClass"&gt;com.mycompany.MyEnum&lt;/param&gt;
   &lt;/type&gt;
&lt;/property&gt;
</codeblock>
			</p>
		</section>
	</conbody>
</concept>
