<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE concept PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN" "http://docs.oasis-open.org/dita/v1.1/OS/dtd/concept.dtd">
<concept id="querying_with_oql">
	<title>Basic Querying</title>
	<shortdesc>This section provides a high-level introduction to <keyword keyref="product_name"/>
		querying such as building a query string and describes query language features. </shortdesc>
	<conbody>
		<section id="section_828A9660B5014DCAA883A58A45E6B51A">
			<p><keyword keyref="product_name"/> provides a SQL-like querying language that allows
				you to access data stored in <keyword keyref="product_name"/> regions. Since
					<keyword keyref="product_name"/> regions are key-value stores where values can
				range from simple byte arrays to complex nested objects, <keyword
					keyref="product_name"/> uses a query syntax based on OQL (Object Query Language)
				to query region data. OQL and SQL have many syntactical similarities, however they
				have significant differences. For example, while OQL does not offer all of the
				capabilities of SQL like aggregates, OQL does allow you to execute queries on
				complex object graphs, query object attributes and invoke object methods. </p>
			<p>The syntax of a typical <keyword keyref="product_name"/> OQL query is:</p>
				<codeblock>[IMPORT package]
SELECT [DISTINCT] projectionList
FROM collection1, [collection2, …]
[WHERE clause]
[ORDER BY order_criteria [desc]]
</codeblock>
			<p>Therefore,
				a simple <keyword keyref="product_name"/> OQL query resembles the following:
			</p>
				<codeblock>SELECT DISTINCT * FROM /exampleRegion WHERE status = ‘active’</codeblock>
			<p> An important characteristic of <keyword keyref="product_name"/> querying to note is
				that by default, <keyword keyref="product_name"/> queries on the values of a region
				and not on keys. To obtain keys from a region, you must use the keySet path
				expression on the queried region. For example,
					<codeph>/exampleRegion.keySet</codeph>. </p>
			<p>For those new to the <keyword keyref="product_name"/> querying, see also the <xref
					href="../../getting_started/querying_quick_reference.xml"
					type="reference" format="dita" scope="local"/>. </p>
		</section>
	</conbody>
</concept>
