<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE concept PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN" "http://docs.oasis-open.org/dita/v1.1/OS/dtd/concept.dtd">
<concept id="ha_event_messaging_whats_next">
	<title>Highly Available Client/Server Event Messaging</title>
	<conbody>
		<section id="section_F163917311E8478399D1DD273E8BCDF5">
			<p>With server redundancy, each pool has a primary server and some number of
				secondaries. The primaries and secondaries are assigned on a per-pool basis and are
				generally spread out for load balancing, so a single client with multiple pools may
				have primary queues in more than one server. </p>
			<p>The primary server pushes events to clients and the secondaries maintain queue
				backups. If the primary server fails, one of the secondaries becomes primary to
				provide uninterrupted event messaging. </p>
			<p>For example, if there are six servers running and
					<codeph>subscription-redundancy</codeph> is set to two, one server is the
				primary, two servers are secondary, and the remaining three do not actively
				participate in HA for the client. If the primary server fails, the system assigns
				one of the secondaries as the new primary and attempts to add another server to the
				secondary pool to retain the initial redundancy level. If no new secondary server is
				found, then the redundancy level is not satisfied but the failover procedure
				completes successfully. As soon as another secondary is available, it is added. </p>
			<p>When high availability is enabled: <ul id="ul_97B98AED705E4EB4AD216A71C4808A90">
					<li id="li_7741681B34E54790A5CC73B37C0FB908">The primary server sends event
						messages to the clients. </li>
					<li id="li_2789F9B8E8314DA692AFA144338772AD">Periodically, the clients send
						received messages to the server and the server removes the sent messages
						from its queues. </li>
					<li id="li_63CB25B503CB4995914479BF607BF988">Periodically, the primary server
						synchronizes with its secondaries, notifying them of messages that can be
						discarded because they have already been sent and received. There is a lag
						in notification, so the secondary servers remain only roughly synchronized
						with the primary. Secondary queues contain all messages that are contained
						in the primary queue plus possibly a few messages that have already been
						sent to clients. </li>
					<li id="li_71A128F57B554BCE874266AC8B5B10A7">In the case of primary server
						failure, one of the secondaries becomes the primary and begins sending event
						messages from its queues to the clients. Immediately after failover, the new
						primary usually resends some messages that were already sent by the old
						primary. The client recognizes these as duplicates and discards them. </li>
				</ul>In stage 1 of this figure, the primary sends an event message to the client and
				a synchronization message to its secondary. By stage 2, the secondary and client
				have updated their queue and message tracking information. If the primary failed at
				stage two, the secondary would start sending event messages from its queue beginning
				with message A10. The client would discard the resend of message A10 and then
				process subsequent messages as usual. </p>
			<p>
				<image href="../../images/ClientServerAdvancedTopics-5.gif"
					alt="High Availability Messaging: Server to Client and Primary Server to Secondary Server"
					id="image_8947A42EDEF74911BAB55B79ED8DA984" placement="break"/>
			</p>
		</section>
		<section id="section_741052B413F24F47A14F5B7D7955F0AA">
			<title>Change Server Queue Synchronization Frequency</title>
			<p>By default, the primary server sends queue synchronization messages to the
				secondaries every second. You can change this interval with the <codeph>gfsh alter
					runtime</codeph> command </p>
			<p>Set the interval for queue synchronization messages as follows: </p>
			<ul id="ul_BF63BA84CCF74310A18C94BF554582A1">
				<li>gfsh:<codeblock>gfsh>alter runtime --message-sync-interval=2</codeblock></li>
				<li id="li_9695D0561380430482FE7264F35ABAEB">XML:
					<codeblock>&lt;!-- Set sync interval to 2 seconds --&gt; 
&lt;cache ... message-sync-interval="2" /&gt;</codeblock>
				</li>
				<li id="li_CB0E3AE90D974CC0BCDE30A44CC9C84A">Java:
					<codeblock>cache = CacheFactory.create();
cache.setMessageSyncInterval(2);  </codeblock>
				</li>
			</ul>
			<p>The ideal setting for this interval depends in large part on your application
				behavior. These are the benefits of shorter and longer interval settings: <ul
					id="ul_EC8220F5CA01411B85C02505235E4081">
					<li id="li_F77BBE69BAE7467BBDD3416B0B1629CB">A shorter interval requires less
						memory in the secondary servers because it reduces queue buildup between
						synchronizations. In addition, fewer old messages in the secondary queues
						means reduced message re-sends after a failover. These considerations are
						most important for systems with high data update rates. </li>
					<li id="li_2F301F187AEE4D9185BA1B569F8296E5">A longer interval requires fewer
						distribution messages between the primary and secondary, which benefits
						overall system performance. </li>
				</ul>
			</p>
		</section>
		<section id="section_DF51950D30154A58818F6AD777BB3090">
			<title>Set Frequency of Orphan Removal from the Secondary Queues</title>
			<p>Usually, all event messages are removed from secondary subscription queues based on
				the primary's synchronization messages. Occasionally, however, some messages are
				orphaned in the secondary queues. For example, if a primary fails in the middle of
				sending a synchronization message to its secondaries, some secondaries might receive
				the message and some might not. If the failover goes to a secondary that did receive
				the message, the system will have secondary queues holding messages that are no
				longer in the primary queue. The new primary will never synchronize on these
				messages, leaving them orphaned in the secondary queues. </p>
			<p>To make sure these messages are eventually removed, the secondaries expire all
				messages that have been enqueued longer than the time indicated by the servers'
					<codeph>message-time-to-live</codeph>. </p>
			<p>Set the time-to-live as follows: <ul id="ul_41860924D45C444383EBD09EBCF43890">
					<li id="li_CA83ABB6908E4BF392DBB1D3724E77A6">XML:
						<codeblock>&lt;!-- Set message ttl to 5 minutes --&gt; 
&lt;cache-server port="41414" message-time-to-live="300" /&gt;</codeblock>
					</li>
					<li id="li_3788ECE600DD48AF9128D3DDE499629A">Java:
						<codeblock>Cache cache = ...;
CacheServer cacheServer = cache.addCacheServer();
cacheServer.setPort(41414);
cacheServer.setMessageTimeToLive(200);
cacheServer.start();                </codeblock>
					</li>
				</ul>
			</p>
		</section>
	</conbody>
</concept>
