<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE concept PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN" "http://docs.oasis-open.org/dita/v1.1/OS/dtd/concept.dtd">
<concept id="tune_client_message_tracking_timeout">
	<title>Tune the Client's Subscription Message Tracking Timeout</title>
	<conbody>
		<section id="section_C655A41D47694BDC9164E5D83C23FA7C">
			<p>If the client pool's <codeph>subscription-message-tracking-timeout</codeph> is set
				too low, your client will discard tracking records for live threads, increasing the
				likelihood of processing duplicate events from those threads. </p>
			<p>This setting is especially important in systems where it is vital to avoid or greatly
				minimize duplicate events. If you detect that duplicate messages are being processed
				by your clients, increasing the timeout may help. Setting
					<codeph>subscription-message-tracking-timeout</codeph> may not completely
				eliminate duplicate entries, but careful configuration can help minimize
				occurrences. </p>
			<p>Duplicates are monitored by keeping track of message sequence IDs from the source
				thread where the operation originated. For a long-running system, you would not want
				to track this information for very long periods or the information may be kept long
				enough for a thread ID to be recycled. If this happens, messages from a new thread
				may be discarded mistakenly as duplicates of messages from an old thread with the
				same ID. In addition, maintaining this tracking information for old threads uses
				memory that might be freed up for other things. </p>
			<p>To minimize duplicates and reduce the size of the message tracking list, set your
				client <codeph>subscription-message-tracking-timeout</codeph> higher than double the
				sum of these times: </p>
				<ul id="ul_2DB0700345D94F73AFD093FCEADA92EE">
					<li id="li_44ED5D0E2FBA4A509D656DE0048BFCF9">The longest time your originating
						threads might wait between operations </li>
					<li id="li_4B0FA9973FBD42FC8C834124408AB705">For redundant servers add: <ul
							id="ul_58E5E023D8A64E57A6AF8A5AA89F838B">
							<li id="li_D4FE51416576488995E331FD94EB5757">The server’s
									<codeph>message-sync-interval</codeph>
							</li>
							<li id="li_537647A5EA8C4BEF98C539C6A3311E59">Total time required for
								failover (usually 7-10 seconds, including the time to detect
								failure) </li>
						</ul>
					</li>
				</ul>You risk losing live thread tracking records if you set the value lower than
				this. This could result in your client processing duplicate event messages into its
				cache for the associated threads. It is worth working to set the
					<codeph>subscription-message-tracking-timeout</codeph> as low as you reasonably
				can.
			<p>
				<codeblock>&lt;!-- Set the tracking timeout to 70 seconds --&gt;
&lt;pool name="client" subscription-enabled="true" subscription-message-tracking-timeout="70000"&gt; 
    ...
&lt;/pool&gt;</codeblock>
			</p>
		</section>
	</conbody>
</concept>
