<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE concept PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN" "http://docs.oasis-open.org/dita/v1.1/OS/dtd/concept.dtd">
<concept id="writing_callbacks_that_modify_the_cache">
	<title>How to Safely Modify the Cache from an Event Handler Callback</title>
	<shortdesc>Event handlers are synchronous. If you need to change the cache or perform any other
		distributed operation from event handler callbacks, be careful to avoid activities that
		might block and affect your overall system performance. </shortdesc>
	<conbody>
		<section id="section_98E49363C91945DEB0A3B2FD9A209969">
			<title>Operations to Avoid in Event Handlers</title>
			<p>Do not perform distributed operations of any kind directly from your event handler.
					<keyword keyref="product_name"/> is a highly distributed system and many
				operations that may seem local invoke distributed operations. </p>
			<p>These are common distributed operations that can get you into trouble: <ul
					id="ul_E3B41D3231DB4CFCB9873485DEA0B92D">
					<li id="li_DDE87E9BE39541B0ACB342E501D8779C">Calling <codeph>Region</codeph>
						methods, on the event's region or any other region. </li>
					<li id="li_794199ECF1A9448B9FE855884466F628">Using the <keyword
							keyref="product_name"/>
						<codeph>DistributedLockService</codeph>. </li>
					<li id="li_E2EFB47E16B046FE844C3424B2012096">Modifying region attributes. </li>
					<li id="li_A44D404555644F21B5E7016701DDB64D">Executing a function through the
							<keyword keyref="product_name"/>
						<codeph>FunctionService</codeph>. </li>
				</ul>
			</p>
			<p>To be on the safe side, do not make any calls to the <keyword keyref="product_name"/>
				API directly from your event handler. Make all <keyword keyref="product_name"/> API
				calls from within a separate thread or executor. </p>
		</section>
		<section id="section_78648D4177E14EA695F0B059E336137C">
			<title>How to Perform Distributed Operations Based on Events</title>
			<p>If you need to use the <keyword keyref="product_name"/> API from your handlers, make your work
				asynchronous to the event handler. You can spawn a separate thread or use a solution
				like the <codeph>java.util.concurrent.Executor</codeph> interface. </p>
			<p>This example shows a serial executor where the callback creates a
					<codeph>Runnable</codeph> that can be pulled off a queue and run by another
				object. This preserves the ordering of events.
				<codeblock>public void afterCreate(EntryEvent event) {
  final Region otherRegion = cache.getRegion("/otherRegion");
  final Object key = event.getKey();
  final Object val = event.getNewValue();

  serialExecutor.execute(new Runnable() {
    public void run() {
      try {
        otherRegion.create(key, val);
      }
      catch (com.gemstone.gemfire.cache.RegionDestroyedException e) {
        ...
      }
      catch (com.gemstone.gemfire.cache.EntryExistsException e) {
        ...
      }
    }
  });
  }</codeblock>
			</p>
			<p>For additional information on the <codeph>Executor</codeph>, see the
					<codeph>SerialExecutor</codeph> example on the Oracle Java web site. </p>
		</section>
	</conbody>
</concept>
