<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE concept PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN" "http://docs.oasis-open.org/dita/v1.1/OS/dtd/concept.dtd">
<concept id="multicast">
	<title>Configuring Multicast Speed Limits</title>
	<shortdesc>After you determine the maximum transmission rate, configure and tune your production
		system. </shortdesc>
	<conbody>
		<section id="section_8E225FC6829946C287552BC7996F2765">
			<p> For best performance, the producer and the consumers should run on different
				machines and each process should have at least one CPU dedicated to it. The
				following is a list of configuration changes that can improve multicast performance.
				Check with your system administrator about changing any of the limits discussed
				here.</p>
				<ul id="ul_EFB8774E9797404BA78E2CD4246A5D89">
					<li id="li_3544A1CF2CCD4B7E8092C1A11E476BD3">Increase the default datagram size
						for systems running Microsoft Windows from 1024 bytes to a value that
						matches your network’s maximum transmission unit (MTU), which is typically
						1500 bytes. The higher setting should improve the system’s network
						performance. </li>
					<li id="li_F3B13B4429C8448D9984A0D117F0E88E">Distribution statistics for stack
						time probes are disabled by default to increase multicast performance. To
						reduce multicast speed, you can enable time statistics by setting the
							gemfire.<codeph>enable-time-statistics</codeph> property to true.
						<p>This enables time statistics for a Java application:</p>
							<codeblock>-Dgemfire.enable-time-statistics=true</codeblock> The time
							statistics properties are passed to the cache server on the
								<codeph>gfsh</codeph> the command line:
							<codeblock>gfsh&gt;start server --name=<varname>server_name</varname> --enable-time-statistics=true</codeblock>
					</li>
					<li id="li_6F09E7D5F35349208CE0B92E34AAFFEB">Monitor the members that receive data for signs of
						data loss. A few data loss messages can happen normally during region
						creation. Multicast retransmit requests and unicast retransmits can also be
						monitored to detect data loss. Even when you see data loss, the cause of the
						problem may have nothing to do with the network. However, if it happens
						constantly then you should try testing the flow control rate again </li>
					<li id="li_E7811457826D443D86C10EB240EA3D53">If necessary, reconfigure all the
							<codeph>gemfire.properties</codeph> files and repeat with lower flow
						control maximum credits until you find the maximum useful rate for your
						installation. </li>
					<li id="li_4F05C926DA0D4FEDA92CF3A1C4BC280A">Slow system performance might be
						helped by reducing how far your multicast messaging goes in your network. </li>
					<li id="li_B1162DF983EB42E8A74A2832E98FC931">Reduce multicast latency by
						disabling batching. By default, <keyword keyref="product_name"/> uses
						batching for operations when the region’s scope is distributed-no-ack. Set
						the <codeph>disableBatching</codeph> property to true on the application or
						when starting a cache server process through the <codeph>gfsh</codeph>
						command line:
						<codeblock>gfsh&gt;start server --name=<varname>server_name</varname> --J=-Dp2p.disableBatching=true</codeblock>
					</li>
				</ul>
		</section>
	</conbody>
</concept>
