<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE concept PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN" "http://docs.oasis-open.org/dita/v1.1/OS/dtd/concept.dtd">
<concept id="slow_recv">
	<title>Preventing Slow Receivers</title>
	<shortdesc>During system integration, you can identify and eliminate potential causes of slow
		receivers in peer-to-peer communication. </shortdesc>
	<conbody>
		<p>Work with your network administrator to eliminate any problems you identify. </p>
		<p>Slowing is more likely to occur when applications run many threads, send large messages
			(due to large entry values), or have a mix of region configurations. The problem can
			also arise from message delivery retries caused by intermittent connection problems. </p>
		<p><b>Host Resources</b>
		</p>
		<p>Make sure that the machines that run <keyword keyref="product_name"/> members have enough
			CPU available to them. Do not run any other heavyweight processes on the same machine. </p>
		<p>The machines that host <keyword keyref="product_name"/> application and cache server
			processes should have comparable computing power and memory capacity. Otherwise, members
			on the less powerful machines tend to have trouble keeping up with the rest of the
			group. </p>
		<p><b>Network Capacity</b>
		</p>
		<p>Eliminate congested areas on the network by rebalancing the traffic load. Work with your
			network administrator to identify and eliminate traffic bottlenecks, whether caused by
			the architecture of the distributed <keyword keyref="product_name"/> system or by
			contention between the <keyword keyref="product_name"/> traffic and other traffic on
			your network. Consider whether more subnets are needed to separate the <keyword
				keyref="product_name"/> administrative traffic from <keyword keyref="product_name"/>
			data transport and to separate all the <keyword keyref="product_name"/> traffic from the
			rest of your network load. </p>
		<p>The network connections between hosts need to have equal bandwidth. If not, you can end
			up with a configuration like the multicast example in the following figure, which
			creates conflicts among the members. For example, if app1 sends out data at 7Mbps, app3
			and app4 would be fine, but app2 would miss some data. In that case, app2 contacts app1
			on the TCP channel and sends a log message that it’s dropping data. <image
				placement="break" id="image_F8C424AB97C444298993294000676150"
				href="../../images_svg/unbalanced_network_capacity_probs.svg"/>
		</p>
		<p><b>Plan for Growth</b>
		</p>
		<p>Upgrade the infrastructure to the level required for acceptable performance. Analyze the
			expected <keyword keyref="product_name"/> traffic in comparison to the network’s
			capacity. Build in extra capacity for growth and high-traffic spikes. Similarly,
			evaluate whether the machines that host <keyword keyref="product_name"/> application and
			cache server processes can handle the expected load. </p>
	</conbody>
</concept>
