<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE concept PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN" "http://docs.oasis-open.org/dita/v1.1/OS/dtd/concept.dtd">
<concept id="slow_mess">
	<title>Slow distributed-ack Messages</title>
	<shortdesc>In systems with distributed-ack regions, a sudden large number of distributed-no-ack
		operations can cause distributed-ack operations to take a long time to complete. </shortdesc>
	<conbody>
		<p> The <codeph>distributed-no-ack</codeph> operations can come from anywhere. They may be
			updates to <codeph>distributed-no-ack</codeph> regions or they may be other
				<codeph>distributed-no-ack</codeph> operations, like destroys, performed on any
			region in the cache, including the <codeph>distributed-ack</codeph> regions. </p>
		<p>The main reasons why a large number of <codeph>distributed-no-ack</codeph> messages may
			delay <codeph>distributed-ack</codeph> operations are: <ul
				id="ul_1E9AC8B4FE4541089FC01563BE1B311E">
				<li id="li_BBF734BBD09242EEBA3B06921DD64F28">For any single socket connection, all
					operations are executed serially. If there are any other operations buffered for
					transmission when a <codeph>distributed-ack</codeph> is sent, the
						<codeph>distributed-ack</codeph> operation must wait to get to the front of
					the line before being transmitted. Of course, the operation’s calling process is
					also left waiting. </li>
				<li id="li_B6D320FA31FB4F5995096B9F5234BDA3">The <codeph>distributed-no-ack</codeph>
					messages are buffered by their threads before transmission. If many messages are
					buffered and then sent to the socket at once, the line for transmission might be
					very long. </li>
			</ul>
		</p>
		<p>You can take these steps to reduce the impact of this problem: <ol
				id="ol_F5575615E6FF47DCBF7B1C4B75EAEBF5">
				<li id="li_1E6481CA853A46C0AC664D1187360B27">If you’re using TCP, check whether you
					have socket conservation enabled for your members. It is configured by setting
					the <keyword keyref="product_name"/> property <codeph>conserve-sockets</codeph> to true. If enabled, each
					application’s threads will share sockets unless you override the setting at the
					thread level. Work with your application programmers to see whether you might
					disable sharing entirely or at least for the threads that perform
						<codeph>distributed-ack</codeph> operations. These include operations on
						<codeph>distributed-ack</codeph> regions and also
						<codeph>netSearches</codeph> performed on regions of any distributed scope.
					(Note: <codeph>netSearch</codeph> is only performed on regions with a
					data-policy of empty, normal and preloaded.) If you give each thread that
					performs <codeph>distributed-ack</codeph> operations its own socket, you
					effectively let it scoot to the front of the line ahead of the
						<codeph>distributed-no-ack</codeph> operations that are being performed by
					other threads. The thread-level override is done by calling the
						<codeph>DistributedSystem.setThreadsSocketPolicy(false)</codeph> method. </li>
				<li id="li_76CECDDCC81447B9901629ED0F05C3C9">Reduce your buffer sizes to slow down
					the distributed-no-ack operations. These changes slow down the threads
					performing distributed-no-ack operations and allow the thread doing the
					distributed-ack operations to be sent in a more timely manner. <ul
						id="ul_F158F2306B414EB4BE700CBBBFC5D1E0">
						<li id="li_2BEFCCC0B82844FB8A91616540EEFBD9">If you're using UDP (you either
							have multicast enabled regions or have set <codeph>disable-tcp</codeph>
							to true in gemfire.properties), consider reducing the byteAllowance of
							mcast-flow-control to something smaller than the default of 3.5
							megabytes. </li>
						<li id="li_7B57960230BF4FF28C4A232A60AE581D">If you're using TCP/IP, reduce
							the <codeph>socket-buffer-size</codeph> in gemfire.properties. </li>
					</ul>
				</li>
			</ol>
		</p>
	</conbody>
</concept>
