<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE concept PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN" "http://docs.oasis-open.org/dita/v1.1/OS/dtd/concept.dtd">
<concept id="client_server_whats_next">
	<title>Fine-Tuning Your Client/Server Configuration</title>
	<shortdesc id="shortdesc_8F72196792BE483F8025EF12BD5B9684">You can fine-tune your client/server
		system with server load-balancing and client thread use of pool connections. For example,
		you can configure how often the servers check their load with the cache server
			<codeph>load-poll-interval</codeph> property, or configure your own server load metrics
		by implementing the <codeph>com.gemstone.gemfire.cache.server</codeph> package. </shortdesc>
	<conbody>
		<section id="section_64AD4CBC253B4C309E3D592D0CED2A6B">
			<title>How Server Load Conditioning Works</title>
			<p>When the client pool requests connection information from the server locator, the
				locator returns the least-loaded server for the connection type. The pool uses this
				"best server" response to open new connections and to condition (rebalance) its
				existing pool connections. <ul id="ul_22DF825FDD8941CC842F572E8356B338">
					<li id="li_02683DCE613B45A7933822873119C83E">The locator tracks server
						availability and load according to information that the servers provide.
						Each server probes its load metrics periodically and, when it detects a
						change, sends new information to the locator. This information consists of
						current load levels and estimates of how much load would be added for each
						additional connection. The locator compares the load information from its
						servers to determine which servers can best handle more connections. </li>
					<li id="li_48E3AB998869405C934D7962AB17ACE2">You can configure how often the
						servers check their load with the cache server’s
							<codeph>load-poll-interval</codeph>. You might want to set it lower if
						you find your server loads fluctuating too much during normal operation. The
						lower you set it, however, the more overhead your load balancing will use. </li>
					<li id="li_97E71CF01D8C43869DD466469FDD3660">Between updates from the servers,
						the locators estimate which server is the least loaded by using the server
						estimates for the cost of additional connections. For example, if the
						current pool connection load for a server’s connections is 0.4 and each
						additional connection would add 0.1 to its load, the locator can estimate
						that adding two new pool connections will take the server’s pool connection
						load to 0.6. </li>
					<li id="li_C07974E78F624FC39753359718D3A8EC">Locators do not share connection
						information among themselves. These estimates provide rough guidance to the
						individual locators for the periods between updates from the servers. </li>
				</ul> <keyword keyref="product_name"/> provides a default utility that probes the server and its resource
				usage to give load information to the locators. The default probe returns the
				following load metrics: <ul id="ul_F7A47D856B8E4E18BFA6B2B9062D5418">
					<li id="li_EA9A97BF1FA34183BC9E0153A2DC5A4F">The pool connection load is the
						number of connections to the server divided by the server’s
							<codeph>max-connections</codeph> setting. This means that servers with a
						lower <codeph>max-connections</codeph> setting receives fewer connections
						than servers with a higher setting. The load is a number between 0 and 1,
						where 0 means there are no connections, and 1 means the server is at
							<codeph>max-connections</codeph>. The load estimate for each additional
						pool connection is 1/<codeph>max-connections</codeph>. </li>
					<li id="li_B6615B42D9FB4AEF86299EDF669F2247">The subscription connection load is
						the number of subscription queues hosted by this server. The load estimate
						for each additional subscription connection is 1. </li>
				</ul>
			</p>
			<p>To use your own server load metrics instead of the default, implement the
					<codeph>ServerLoadProbe</codeph> or <codeph>ServerLoadProbeAdapter</codeph> and
				related interfaces and classes in the
					<codeph>com.gemstone.gemfire.cache.server</codeph> package. The load for each
				server is weighed relative to the loads reported by other servers in the system.
			</p>
		</section>
		<section id="section_CE66DA4747BC4870893DB93690DAB95B">
			<title>Client Thread Use of Pool Connections</title>
			<p>By default, a client thread retrieves a connection from the open connection pool for
				each forwarded operation and returns the connection to the pool as soon as the
				request is complete. If your client thread runs a <codeph>put</codeph> on a client
				region, for example, that operation grabs a server connection, sends the
					<codeph>put</codeph> to the server, and then returns the connection to the pool.
				This action keeps the connections available to the most threads possible. </p>
		</section>
		<section id="section_7CC2BB7D03D8466D881888127F7A06A9">
			<title>Set Up a Thread-Local (Dedicated) Connection</title>
			<p>You configure threads to use dedicated connections by setting
					<codeph>thread-local-connections</codeph> to true. In this case the thread holds
				its connection either until the thread explicitly releases the connection, or the
				connection expires based on <codeph>idle-timeout</codeph> or
					<codeph>load-conditioning-interval</codeph>. </p>
		</section>
		<section id="section_396E1207E2E84590B9557D449F0846FD">
			<title>Release a Thread-Local Connection</title>
			<p>If you use thread-local connections, you should release the connection as soon as
				your thread finishes its server activities. <ul
					id="ul_2F26B35DFAFB405A844D3773FBD53C0C">
					<li id="li_CB5A687D94124E1E8D1AA6CF35FB334E">Call
							<codeph>releaseThreadLocalConnection</codeph> on the
							<codeph>Pool</codeph> instance you are using for the region:
						<codeblock>Region myRegion ...
PoolManager.find(myRegion).releaseThreadLocalConnection();</codeblock>
					</li>
				</ul>
			</p>
		</section>
	</conbody>
</concept>
