<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE concept PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN" "http://docs.oasis-open.org/dita/v1.1/OS/dtd/concept.dtd">
<concept id="setting_cache_properties">
	<title>Options for Configuring the Cache and Data Regions </title>
	<shortdesc id="shortdesc_9062678E79CE4DDAAA71FCA3FE6C2DB7">To populate your <keyword
			keyref="product_name_long"/> cache and fine-tune its storage and distribution behavior,
		you need to define cached data regions and provide custom configuration for the cache and
		regions. </shortdesc>
	<conbody>
		<section id="section_FB536C90C219432D93E872CBD49D66B1">
			<p>Cache configuration properties define:</p>
				<ul id="ul_6A38FAC0D0564FC4A2211783795A3C9A">
					<li id="li_CACA6C694BF146C5BAAF4B93986026D8">Cache-wide settings such as disk
						stores, communication timeouts, and settings designating the member as a
						server </li>
					<li id="li_EE0636CD2C3B4D00A8F61DE0B923D631">Cache data regions </li>
				</ul>
			<p>Configure the cache and its data regions through one or more of these methods:</p>
				<ul
					id="ul_783EFE93A76748FC88F04540AC195CD4">
					<li>Through a persistent configuration that you define when issuing commands
						that use the gfsh command line utility. <codeph>gfsh</codeph> supports the
						administration, debugging, and deployment of <keyword
							keyref="product_name_long"/> processes and applications. You can use
						gfsh to configure regions, locators, servers, disk stores, event queues, and
						other objects. <p>As you issue commands, gfsh saves a set of configurations
							that apply to the entire cluster and also saves configurations that only
							apply to defined groups of members within the cluster. You can re-use
							these configurations to create a distributed system. See <xref
								href="../../configuring/cluster_config/gfsh_persist.xml"
							/>.</p></li>
					<li id="li_F0B7F989BA9247EB997AC0A78D3650B1">Through declarations in the XML
						file named in the <codeph>cache-xml-file</codeph>
						<codeph>gemfire.properties</codeph> setting. This file is generally referred
						to as the <codeph>cache.xml</codeph> file, but it can have any name. See
							<xref
							href="../../reference/topics/chapter_overview_cache_xml.xml#cache_xml"
						/>. </li>
					<li id="li_D8F6569457CA4E4CAA8F749AE8A49229">Through application calls to the
							<codeph>com.gemstone.gemfire.cache.CacheFactory</codeph>,
							<codeph>com.gemstone.gemfire.cache.Cache</codeph> and
							<codeph>com.gemstone.gemfire.cache.Region</codeph> APIs. </li>
				</ul>
		</section>
	</conbody>
</concept>
