<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE concept PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN" "http://docs.oasis-open.org/dita/v1.1/OS/dtd/concept.dtd">
<concept id="starting_up_shutting_down">
	<title>Starting Up and Shutting Down Your System</title>
	<shortdesc>Determine the proper startup and
		shutdown procedures, and write your startup and shutdown scripts. </shortdesc>
	<conbody>
	<p>Well-designed procedures for starting and stopping your system can speed startup and
			protect your data. The processes you need to start and stop include server and locator processes and
			your other <keyword keyref="product_name"/> applications, including clients. The
			procedures you use depend in part on your system’s configuration and the
			dependencies between your system processes. </p>
		<p>Use the following guidelines to create startup and shutdown procedures and scripts.
			Some of these instructions use <xref
				href="../../tools_modules/gfsh/chapter_overview.xml" type="concept"
				format="dita" scope="local"/>. </p>
		<section id="section_3D111558326D4A38BE48C17D44BB66DB">
			<title>Starting Up Your System</title>
			<p>You should follow certain order guidelines when starting your <keyword
				keyref="product_name"/> system. </p>
			<p>Start server-distributed systems before you start their client applications. In each
				distributed system, follow these guidelines for member startup: </p>
				<ul
					id="ul_5863AF9CB6DB436E81D974ACA90A4C11">
					<li id="li_FD023619751949E883BE95DFA93888FF">Start locators first. See <xref
							href="running_the_locator.xml" type="concept" format="dita"
							scope="local"/> for examples of locator start up commands. </li>
					<li id="li_F6AFBB5A5A954FCAB0AEDD40C5B13B66">Start cache servers before the rest of your
						processes unless the implementation requires that other processes be started
						ahead of them. See <xref href="running_the_cacheserver.xml" type="concept"
							format="dita" scope="local"/> for examples of server start up commands. </li>
					<li id="li_533E8FB3517845899892FCD816A3A6A4">If your distributed system uses
						both persistent replicated and non-persistent replicated regions, you should
						start up all the persistent replicated members in parallel before starting
						the non-persistent regions. This way, persistent members will not delay
						their startup for other persistent members with later data. </li>
					<li>For a system that includes persistent regions, see <xref
							href="../../managing/disk_storage/starting_system_with_disk_stores.xml"
						 format="dita" type="concept"/>.</li>
					<li id="li_BCFA0D08977B49CB84928EBEE322764D">If you are running producer processes and consumer
						or event listener processes, start the consumers first. This ensures the
						consumers and listeners do not miss any notifications or updates. </li>
					<li>If you are starting up your locators and peer members all at once, you can
						use the <codeph>locator-wait-time</codeph> property (in seconds) upon
						process start up. This timeout allows peers to wait for the locators to
						finish starting up before attempting to join the distributed system. If a
						process has been configured to wait for a locator to start, it will log an
						info-level message<lq><codeph>GemFire startup was unable to contact a
							locator. Waiting for one to start. Configured locators are
							frodo[12345],pippin[12345]. </codeph></lq>The process will then
						sleep for a second and retry until it either connects or the number of
						seconds specified in <codeph>locator-wait-time</codeph> has elapsed. By
						default, <codeph>locator-wait-time</codeph> is set to zero meaning that a
						process that cannot connect to a locator upon startup will throw an
						exception.</li>
				</ul>
			<note>
				<p>You can optionally override the default timeout period for shutting down individual
				processes. This override setting must be specified during member startup. See <xref
					href="#starting_up_shutting_down/section_mnx_4cp_cv" format="dita">Shutting Down
					the System</xref> for details.
				</p>
			</note>
		</section>
		<section id="section_2F8ABBFCE641463C8A8721841407993D">
			<title>Starting Up After Losing Data on Disk </title>
			<p>This information pertains to catastrophic loss of <keyword keyref="product_name"/>
				disk store files. If you lose disk store files, your next startup may hang, waiting
				for the lost disk stores to come back online. If your system hangs at startup, use
				the <codeph>gfsh</codeph> command <codeph>show missing-disk-store</codeph> to list
				missing disk stores and, if needed, revoke missing disk stores so your system
				startup can complete. You must use the Disk Store ID to revoke a disk store. These
				are the two commands:</p>
				<codeblock>
gfsh&gt;show missing-disk-stores

Disk Store ID             |   Host    |               Directory                                           
------------------------------------ | --------- | -------------------------------------
60399215-532b-406f-b81f-9b5bd8d1b55a | excalibur | /usr/local/gemfire/deploy/disk_store1 

gfsh&gt;revoke missing-disk-store --id=60399215-532b-406f-b81f-9b5bd8d1b55a</codeblock>
				<note>
					<p>This gfsh commands require that you are connected to the distributed system
					via a JMX Manager node. 
					</p>
				</note>
		</section>
		<section id="section_mnx_4cp_cv">
			<title>Shutting Down the System</title>
			<p>Shut down your <keyword keyref="product_name"/> system by using either
					<codeph>gfsh</codeph>'s <codeph>shutdown</codeph> command or by shutting down
				individual members one at a time.</p>
		</section>
		<section id="section_0EB4DDABB6A348BA83B786EEE7C84CF1">
			<title>Using the shutdown Command</title>
			<p>If you are using persistent regions, (members are persisting data to disk), you
				should use the <codeph>gfsh</codeph>
				<codeph>shutdown</codeph> command to stop the running system in an orderly fashion.
				This command synchronizes persistent partitioned regions before shutting down, which
				makes the next startup of the distributed system as efficient as possible. </p>
			<p>If possible, all members should be running before you shut them down so
				synchronization can occur. Shut down the system using the following
				<codeph>gfsh</codeph> command:</p>
			<codeblock>gfsh&gt;shutdown</codeblock> By
				default, the shutdown command will only shut down data nodes. If you want to shut
				down all nodes including locators, specify the
				<codeph>--include-locators=true</codeph> parameter. For example:
				<codeblock>gfsh>shutdown --include-locators=true</codeblock>
			<p>This will shut down all
				locators one by one, shutting down the manager last.</p>
			<p>To shutdown all data members after a grace period, specify a time-out option (in
				seconds).</p>
				<codeblock>gfsh&gt;shutdown --time-out=60</codeblock>
			<p> To shutdown all
				members including locators after a grace period, specify a time-out option (in
				seconds).</p>
			<codeblock>gfsh>shutdown --include-locators=true --time-out=60</codeblock>
		</section>
		<section id="section_A07D40BC118544D0984860A3B4A5CB29">					
			<title>Shutting Down System Members Individually</title>
			<p>If you are not using persistent regions, you can shut down the distributed system by shutting
				down each member in the reverse order of their startup. (See <xref
					href="#starting_up_shutting_down/section_3D111558326D4A38BE48C17D44BB66DB"
					format="dita">Starting Up Your System</xref> for the recommended order of member
				startup.) </p>
			<p>Shut down the distributed system members according to the type of member. For
				example, use the following mechanisms to shut down members:</p>
				<ul
					id="ul_12CC69DA7B8047AFA69CC5F120B66E0F">
					<li id="li_0C4894CD078B469A869B008331A4FF99">Use the appropriate mechanism to
						shut down any <keyword keyref="product_name"/>-connected client applications
						that are running in the distributed system. </li>
					<li id="li_534EF2BF81C74B2EB40A3322AD9B8BB3">Shut down any cache servers. To shut down a
						server, issue the following <codeph>gfsh</codeph> command:
						<codeblock>gfsh&gt;stop server --name=&lt;...&gt;</codeblock>or
						<codeblock>gfsh>stop server --dir=&lt;server_working_dir></codeblock>
					</li>
					<li id="li_3BA78A549F184817943F53786FF2CEDE">Shut down any locators. To shut down a locator,
						issue the following <codeph>gfsh</codeph> command:
						<codeblock>gfsh&gt;stop locator --name=&lt;...&gt;</codeblock>
						or<codeblock>gfsh>stop locator --dir=&lt;locator_working_dir></codeblock></li>
				</ul>
			
		</section>
		<section id="section_7CF680CF8A924C57A7052AE2F975DA81">					
			<title>Option for System Member Shutdown Behavior</title>
			<p>The <codeph>DISCONNECT_WAIT</codeph> command line argument sets the maximum time for
				each individual step in the shutdown process. If any step takes longer than the
				specified amount, it is forced to end. Each operation is given this grace period, so
				the total length of time the cache member takes to shut down depends on the number
				of operations and the <codeph>DISCONNECT_WAIT</codeph> setting. During the shutdown
				process, <keyword keyref="product_name"/> produces messages such as:</p>
				<codeblock>Disconnect listener still running</codeblock>
			<p>The <codeph>DISCONNECT_WAIT</codeph> default is 10000 milliseconds. </p>
			<p>To change it, set this system property on the Java command line used for member
				startup. For example:</p>
				<codeblock>gfsh&gt;start server --J=-DDistributionManager.DISCONNECT_WAIT=&lt;milliseconds&gt;</codeblock>
				<p>Each process can have different <codeph>DISCONNECT_WAIT</codeph> settings. </p>
		</section>
	</conbody>
</concept>
