<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE concept PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN" "concept.dtd">
<concept id="concept_dxv_zb5_m4">
    <title><keyword keyref="product_name"/> REST API Overview</title>
    <shortdesc id="shortdesc_A39702FB462C4E80B8BF09C0A8391683">By using the <keyword
            keyref="product_name"/> REST application interface, you can immediately access <keyword
            keyref="product_name"/>'s data management capabilities in languages other than the
        natively supported Java language. </shortdesc>
    <conbody>
        <p dir="ltr">You can write REST-enabled client applications for <keyword
                keyref="product_name"/> in a variety of languages that use the open and standard
            HTTP protocol-- for example, Ruby, Python, JavaScript and Scala, as well as already
            supported languages such as Java.</p>
        <p dir="ltr">When you access <keyword keyref="product_name"/> through the REST interface,
            objects are stored in <keyword keyref="product_name"/> as PdxInstances. A PdxInstance is
            a light-weight wrapper around PDX serialized bytes. It provides applications with
            run-time access to fields of a PDX serialized object. This interoperable format allows
            your Java applications to operate on the same data as your REST applications. </p>
        <p dir="ltr">As an added benefit, because <keyword keyref="product_name"/>'s REST interface
            stores objects as PdxInstances, you do not need to write corresponding Java classes to
            translate JSON data (which you must do with other REST interface providers such as
            Oracle Coherence.) For example, consider the use case where a non-Java REST client
            application (Python, Ruby or Scala) performs <keyword keyref="product_name"/> region
            operations with JSON data that represents employee data. Since the object is stored in
                <keyword keyref="product_name"/> as a PdxInstance that can be automatically mapped
            to JSON, the user does not need to write a corresponding Employee.java class and also
            does not need to worry about related issues such as keeping the Employee object in the
            CLASSPATH. </p>
        <p>See <xref
                href="../developing/data_serialization/gemfire_pdx_serialization.xml"
            /> for more information on PDX serialization.</p>
    </conbody>
</concept>
