<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE task PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Task//EN" "task.dtd">
<task id="topic_e21_qc5_m4">
  <title>Setup and Configuration</title>
  <shortdesc>The <keyword keyref="product_name_long"/> developer REST interface runs as an embedded
    HTTP or HTTPS service (Jetty server) within a <keyword keyref="product_name"/> data node. </shortdesc>
  <taskbody>
    <prereq>
      <p>All <keyword keyref="product_name"/> REST interface classes and required JAR files are
        distributed as a WAR file with the <keyword keyref="product_name"/> product distribution.
        You can locate the file in the following
        location:<codeblock>$GEMFIRE/tools/Extensions/gemfire-api.war</codeblock></p>
      <p dir="ltr">To enable the developer REST API service in <keyword keyref="product_name_long"
        />, set the <codeph>start-dev-rest-api</codeph>
        <keyword keyref="product_name"/> property to <codeph>true</codeph> when starting a data node
        using either <codeph>gfsh</codeph> or the ServerLauncher API. Setting this property to true
        on a data node will start up an embedded Jetty server and deploy the REST developer API WAR
        file.</p>
      <p dir="ltr">
        <note>The REST API service for application development can only be started on servers; you
          cannot use locators to host the developer <keyword keyref="product_name"/> REST API
          services. </note>
      </p>
      <p dir="ltr">You can have multiple REST enabled data nodes in a single distributed system.
        Each data node should have a separate host name and unique end point. To ensure that the
        data node is reachable on a machine with multiple NIC addresses, you can use
          <codeph>http-service-bind-address</codeph> to bind an address to the REST API service (as
        well as the other embedded web services such as Pulse.)</p>
      <p>You can also configure the Developer REST API service to run over HTTPS by configuring the
        following <keyword keyref="product_name"/> properties in
          <filepath>gemfire.properties</filepath> or <filepath>gfsecurity.properties</filepath> or
        on server startup:</p>
      <ul id="ul_hl4_rqq_kq">
        <li>http-service-ssl-enabled</li>
        <li>http-service-ssl-require-authentication</li>
        <li>http-service-ssl-protocols</li>
        <li>http-service-ssl-ciphers</li>
        <li>http-service-ssl-keystore</li>
        <li>http-service-ssl-keystore-password</li>
        <li>http-service-ssl-keystore-type</li>
        <li>http-service-ssl-truststore</li>
        <li>http-service-ssl-truststore-password</li>
      </ul>
      <p dir="ltr">See <xref href="../managing/security/ssl_overview.xml"/> for details on
        configuring these parameters.</p>
      <p dir="ltr">The above parameters apply to all HTTP services hosted on the configured server,
        which can include the following:</p>
      <ul id="ul_vnp_vrq_kq">
        <li>Developer REST API service</li>
        <li>Management REST API service (for remote cluster management)</li>
        <li>Pulse monitoring tool</li>
      </ul>
      <p>The following procedure starts up a REST API service-enabled <keyword keyref="product_name"
        /> deployment:</p>
    </prereq>
    <steps id="steps_twp_yc5_m4">
      <step>
        <cmd>Configure PDX for your cluster. You must configure PDX if either or both of the
          following conditions apply: </cmd>
        <info>
            <ul id="ul_shp_4qx_dp">
              <li>Application peer member caches will access REST-accessible Regions (resources)
                with the <codeph>Region.get(key)</codeph>.</li>
              <li>Your deployment has persistent regions that must be available as resources to the
                REST API. </li>
            </ul>
          <p>To configure PDX in your cluster, perform the following steps:</p></info>
        <substeps id="substeps_pgr_x5p_y4">
          <substep>
            <cmd>Start up a locator running the <xref
                href="../configuring/cluster_config/gfsh_persist.xml">cluster configuration
                service</xref> (enabled by default). For example: </cmd>
            <info>
              <codeblock>gfsh>start locator --name=locator1</codeblock>
            </info>
          </substep>
          <substep>
            <cmd>If your deployment has application peer member caches (for example, Java clients)
              that must also access REST-accessible Regions (resources), use the following gfsh
              command:</cmd>
            <info>
              <codeblock>gfsh>configure pdx --read-serialized=true</codeblock>
              <note>You do not need to configure <codeph>--read-serialized=true</codeph> if no
                application peer member caches are accessing the REST-accessible regions (resources)
                in your deployment.</note>
            </info>
          </substep>
          <substep>
            <cmd>If your deployment contains <b>persistent regions</b> that must be REST-accessible,
              use the following gfsh command:</cmd>
            <info><codeblock>gfsh>configure pdx --disk-store</codeblock>This command sets
                <codeph>pdx</codeph>
              <codeph>persistent</codeph> equal to true and sets the disk-store-name to DEFAULT. If
              desired, specify an existing disk store name as the value for
                <codeph>--disk-store</codeph>. </info>
          </substep>
          <substep>
            <cmd>If both of the above cases apply to your deployment, then configure PDX with the
              following single command:</cmd>
            <info>
              <codeblock>gfsh>configure pdx --read-serialized=true --disk-store</codeblock>
            </info>
          </substep>
        </substeps>
        <stepresult>After you have configured PDX for your caches, then proceed with starting up
          your REST-enabled servers and other data nodes.</stepresult>
      </step>
      <step>
        <cmd>Start a server node with the <keyword keyref="product_name"/> property
            <codeph>start-dev-rest-api</codeph> set to <codeph>true</codeph>. For example:</cmd>
        <info>
          <codeblock>gfsh>start server --name=server1 <b>--J=-Dgemfire.start-dev-rest-api=true</b> \
--J=-Dgemfire.http-service-port=8080 --J=-Dgemfire.http-service-bind-address=localhost</codeblock>
          <p>Optionally, you can also configure a <codeph>http-service-bind-address</codeph> and
              <codeph>http-service-port</codeph> to identify the cache server and specific port that
            will host REST services. If you do not specify the <codeph>http-service-port</codeph>,
            the default port is 7070. If you do not specify
              <codeph>http-service-bind-address</codeph>, the HTTP service will bind to all local
            addresses by default. </p>
          <p>Any server that hosts data, even a server acting as a JMX manager, can start the
            developer REST API service. For example, to start the service on a server that is also a
            JMX manager, you would
            run:<codeblock>gfsh>start server --name=server1  <b>--J=-Dgemfire.start-dev-rest-api=true</b> \
--J=-Dgemfire.http-service-port=8080 --J=-Dgemfire.http-service-bind-address=localhost \
<b>--J=-Dgemfire.jmx-manager=true --J=-Dgemfire.jmx-manager-start=true</b></codeblock>Note
            that when started as a JMX Manager, the server will also host the Pulse web application
            in the same HTTP service.</p>
        </info>
      </step>
      <step>
        <cmd>You may also need to specify a CLASSPATH to load any functions that need to be made
          available to your REST services. For example:</cmd>
        <info>
          <codeblock>gfsh>start server --name=server1 --J=-Dgemfire.start-dev-rest-api=true \
--J=-Dgemfire.http-service-port=8080 --J=-Dgemfire.http-service-bind-address=localhost \<b>
--classpath=/myapps/testfunctions.jar</b></codeblock>
        </info>
      </step>
      <step>
        <cmd>You can also specify these properties either upon server startup or in the server’s
          gemfire.properties configuration file.</cmd>
        <info><codeblock>gfsh>start server --name=serverX --server-port=40405 --cache-xml-file=cache-config.xml \<b>
--properties-file=gemfire.properties</b> --classpath=/myapps/testfunctions.jar</codeblock>where
          gemfire.properties contains:
          <codeblock>http-service-port=8080
http-service-bind-address=localhost
start-dev-rest-api=true</codeblock></info>
      </step>
      <step>
        <cmd>Verify that the <keyword keyref="product_name"/> REST API service is up and running. To
          validate this, you can perform the following checks:</cmd>
        <substeps id="substeps_grb_j1v_44">
          <substep>
            <cmd>Test the list resources endpoint (this step assumes that you have regions defined
              on your cluster):</cmd>
            <info>
              <codeblock>curl -i http://localhost:8080/gemfire-api/v1</codeblock>
            </info>
          </substep>
          <substep>
            <cmd>Examine the server logs for the following messages:</cmd>
            <info>
              <codeblock>[info 2014/06/12 14:56:52.431 PDT rest-test &lt;localhost-startStop-1> tid=0x4d] 
(tid=11 msgId=8) Initializing Spring FrameworkServlet 'gemfire-api'[info 2014/06/12 
14:56:52.432 PDT rest-test &lt;localhost-startStop-1> tid=0x4d] (tid=11 msgId=9) 
FrameworkServlet 'gemfire-api': initialization started</codeblock>
            </info>
          </substep>
          <substep>
            <cmd>Open a browser and enter the following URL to browse the Swagger-enabled REST
              APIs:</cmd>
            <info><codeblock>http://&lt;<i>http-service-bind-address</i>>:&lt;<i>http-service-port</i>>/gemfire-api/docs/index.html</codeblock>where
                <i>http-service-bind-address</i> is the address and <i>http-service-port</i> is the
              port number that you specified when starting the Development REST API service on the
              server. For example, based on the server started in step 2, you would
                enter:<codeblock>http://localhost:8080/gemfire-api/docs/index.html</codeblock><p>If
                you did not specify these properties upon server startup or in
                  <codeph>gemfire.properties</codeph>, then use the default of localhost and port
                7070. See <xref href="using_swagger.xml#concept_rlr_y3c_54"/> for more
                information.</p></info>
          </substep>
        </substeps>
      </step>
    </steps>
    <example><title>Programmatic Startup</title>You can also start up and configure <keyword
        keyref="product_name"/> REST services programmatically. For
      example:<codeblock outputclass="language-java">import com.gemstone.gemfire.distributed.ServerLauncher;

 public class MyEmbeddedRestServer {

    public static void main(String[] args){
        ServerLauncher serverLauncher  = new ServerLauncher.Builder()
          .set("start-dev-rest-api", "true")
          .set("http-service-port", "8080")
          .set("http-service-bind-address", "localhost")
          .setPdxReadSerialized(true)
          .build();

          serverLauncher.start();  

          System.out.println("REST server successfully started");
        }
    }
</codeblock></example>
    <postreq>
      <p>You can then verify that the developer REST API service has been started programmatically
        by visiting the following
        URL:<codeblock>http://localhost:8080/gemfire-api/docs/index.html</codeblock></p>
    </postreq>

  </taskbody>
</task>
