<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE concept PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN" "concept.dtd">
<concept
	id="security">
	<title
		id="title_9717E51087B346988389138843E158C4">Using an LDAP Server for Client
		Authentication</title>
	<shortdesc>An LDAP server can be used by a <keyword keyref="product_name"/> cache server using the
		sample LDAP implementation provided in <keyword keyref="product_name"/> server product. </shortdesc>
	<conbody
		id="conbody_D74C4342289846619E028149A8920946">
		<p> See the <xref href="../../managing/security/chapter_overview.xml#security" type="concept"
				format="dita" scope="local">Security</xref> to verify authentication credentials for
			native clients attempting to connect to the <keyword keyref="product_name"/> servers and
			sending user name and passwords using the sample UserPassword scheme. </p>
			<note>
				<p>The user name and password with this sample implementation is sent out in plaintext. For
				better security, either turn on credential encryption using Diffie-Hellman key
				exchange, or use a scheme like PKCS. </p>
			</note>
		<p>When a client initiates a connection to a cache server, the client submits its credentials to
			the server and the server submits those credentials to the LDAP server. To be
			authenticated, the credentials for the client need to match one of the valid entries in
			the LDAP server. The credentials can consist of the entry name and the corresponding
			password. If the submitted credentials result in a connection to the LDAP server because
			the credentials match the appropriate LDAP entries, then the client is authenticated and
			granted a connection to the server. If the server fails to connect to the LDAP server
			with the supplied credentials then an <codeph>AuthenticationFailedException</codeph> is
			sent to the client and its connection with the cache server is closed. </p>
		<p>
			<b>Configuration Settings</b>
		</p>
		<p>In the <codeph>gfcpp.properties</codeph> file for the client, specify the
				<codeph>UserPasswordAuthInit</codeph> callback, the user name, and the password,
			like this:</p>
			<codeblock>security-client-auth-library=securityImpl
security-client-auth-factory=createUserPasswordAuthInitInstance
security-username=&lt;username&gt;
security-password=&lt;password&gt;</codeblock>
		<p>For server side settings and LDAP server configuration, see <xref
				href="../../managing/security/chapter_overview.xml#security" type="concept"
				format="dita" scope="local">Security</xref>. </p>
	</conbody>
</concept>
