<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE concept PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN" "concept.dtd">
<concept
	id="concept_6DC3DD288F6C4190AEA07DEDE76DD867">
	<title>Data Serialization Options</title>
	<shortdesc>Built-in .NET types are serialized automatically into the cache and can be retrieved by
		Java servers and other <keyword keyref="product_name"/> clients. For domain objects that are
		not simple types, you have three <keyword keyref="product_name"/> serialization options. </shortdesc>
	<conbody>
		<p> The options give good performance and flexibility for data storage, transfers, and language
			types. The <keyword keyref="product_name"/> options can also improve performance in
			serializing and deserializing built-in types. </p>
		<p>The simplest option is to use perform automatic serialization by registering the <keyword
				keyref="product_name"/> .NET PDX reflection-based autoserializer in your
			application. When you have this registered, <keyword keyref="product_name"/> uses it for
			all domain objects that are not custom serialized. </p>
		<p>You can also custom serialize your objects by implementing one of the <keyword
				keyref="product_name"/> .NET interfaces,
				<codeph>GemStone::GemFire::Cache::Generic::IPdxSerializable</codeph> or
				<codeph>GemStone::GemFire::Cache::IGFSerializable</codeph>. </p>
		<p>You also have the option of using default .NET serialization, but you cannot use it
			unless you also use helper classes. The helper classes you must use are
				<codeph>CacheableObject</codeph> and <codeph>CacheableObjectXml</codeph>. </p>
		<p><keyword keyref="product_name"/> .NET PDX serialization has more bytes in overhead than
				<keyword keyref="product_name"/> .NET Data serialization, but using PDX
			serialization helps you avoid the performance costs of deserialization when performing
			queries. Applications can use <codeph>PdxInstances</codeph> in functions to avoid the
			deserialization of entire objects. </p>
			<table
				id="table_D61A94C4BFBE4712835F632F30BB488E">
				<title>Serialization Options—Comparison of Features</title>
				<tgroup
					cols="3"><colspec
						colnum="1"
						colname="col1"
						colwidth="*"/><colspec
						colnum="2"
						colname="col2"
						colwidth="*"/><colspec
						colname="col3"
						colnum="3"
						colwidth="1.50*"/><thead>
						<row>
							<entry
								colname="col1">Capability </entry>
							<entry
								colname="col2">IGFSerializable </entry>
							<entry
								colname="col3">IPdxSerializable and PDX reflection-based
								autoserializer </entry>
						</row></thead>
					<tbody>
						<row>
							<entry
								colname="col1">
								<p>Handles multiple versions of domain objects* </p>
							</entry>
							<entry
								colname="col2"> </entry>
							<entry
								colname="col3">X </entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry
								colname="col1">
								<p>Provides single field access on servers of serialized data,
									without full deserialization. Supported also for OQL queries.
								</p>
							</entry>
							<entry
								colname="col2"> </entry>
							<entry
								colname="col3">X </entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry
								colname="col1">
								<p>Automatically ported to other languages by <keyword keyref="product_name"/> - no need to
								program Java-side implementation </p>
							</entry>
							<entry
								colname="col2"> </entry>
							<entry
								colname="col3">X </entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry
								colname="col1">
								<p>Works with <keyword keyref="product_name"/> delta propagation </p>
							</entry>
							<entry
								colname="col2">X </entry>
							<entry
								colname="col3">X (See explanation below.) </entry>
						</row>
					</tbody>
				</tgroup>
			</table>
		<p>*You can mix domain object versions where the differences between versions are the
			addition and removal of object fields. </p>
		<p>By default, you can use <keyword keyref="product_name"/> delta propagation with PDX
			serialization. However, delta propagation will not work if you have set the <keyword
				keyref="product_name"/> property read-serialized to "true". In terms of
			deserialization, to apply a change delta propagation requires a domain class instance
			and the <codeph>fromDelta</codeph> method. If you have set read-serialized to true, you
			will receive an <codeph>IPdxInstance</codeph> instead of a domain class instance and
				<codeph>IPdxInstance</codeph> does not have the <codeph>fromDelta</codeph> method
			required for delta propagation. You will also require the Java domain class on the
			server similar to the you would need the .NET PDX Delta domain class. </p>
		<p>For detailed information on the interfaces, see the online API documentation. </p>
	</conbody>
</concept>
