<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE concept PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN" "concept.dtd">
<concept
 id="concept_k2t_lzr_3q">
 <title>Removing an Entry</title>
 <shortdesc>The standard <codeph>Region::Remove</codeph> API removes the entry with specified key
  and provides a user-defined parameter object to any <codeph>CacheWriter</codeph> or
   <codeph>CacheListener</codeph> invoked in the process. </shortdesc>
 <conbody>
  <p>The <codeph>Remove</codeph> call not only removes the value, but also the key and entry from
      this region. The remove operation is propagated to the <keyword keyref="product_name"/> cache
      server that the native client is connected to. If the destroy operation fails due to an
      exception on the server (for example, a <codeph>CacheServerException</codeph> or security
      exception), then the local entry is still removed. </p>
  <p>The <codeph>Remove</codeph> operation updates
    <codeph>CacheStatistics::LastAccessedTime</codeph>, <codeph>CacheStatistics::HitCount</codeph>,
   and <codeph>CacheStatistics::MissCount</codeph> for this region and the entry.</p>
  <p>The <codeph>Remove</codeph> API returns true if the entry (key, value) has been removed or
   false if the entry (key, value) has not been removed.</p>
  <section>
   <title>Bulk Remove Operations Using removeAll</title>
   <p>You can use the <codeph>Region::removeAll</codeph> API  to remove all entries for a colleciton
    of specified keys from the region. The effect of this call is equivalent to that of calling
     <codeph>destroy</codeph> on this region once for each key in the specified collection. If an
    entry does not exist, then that key is skipped. Note that an
     <codeph>EntryNotFoundException</codeph> is not thrown.</p>
   <p>The <codeph>RemoveAll</codeph> operation updates
     <codeph>CacheStatistics::LastAccessedTime</codeph>, <codeph>CacheStatistics::HitCount</codeph>,
    and <codeph>CacheStatistics::MissCount</codeph> for this region and the entries that are
    removed.</p>
   <p>The <codeph>RemoveAll</codeph> API also supports providing a callback argument to any cache
    loaders or cache writers that are invoked in the operation. See the Region online API
    documentation for more information about using <codeph>RemoveAll</codeph>. </p>
  </section>
 </conbody>
</concept>
