<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE concept PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN" "http://docs.oasis-open.org/dita/v1.1/OS/dtd/concept.dtd">
<concept
	id="invalidating-region">
	<title>Invalidating and Destroying Regions</title>
	<shortdesc>Invalidation marks all entries contained in the region as invalid (with null values).
		Destruction removes the region and all of its contents from the cache. </shortdesc>
	<conbody>
		<section
			id="section_6F7E304D1D5743F1B53FCBD4F82651D0">
			<p>
				
You can execute these operations explicitly in the local cache in
				the following ways: </p>
			<ul
				id="ul_184BF582FCC9469C8C2255B3D01AB39C">
				<li
					id="li_071971EF0C60489B814C6C4C3706D8D8">Through direct API calls from the
					native client. </li>
				<li
					id="li_29E20B6CB3F447B1B3E460E5B215C5E7">Through expiration activities based on
					the region's statistics and attribute settings. </li>
			</ul>
			<p>In either case, you can perform invalidation and destruction as a local or a distributed
				operation.  </p>
			<ul
				id="ul_C58AA857F021466BB603667E8D4302F3">
				<li
					id="li_1147568D0E5E45D79DD750D14CD39F87">A local operation affects the region
					only in the local cache. </li>
				<li
					id="li_89194864AFF5410C808F9795F0CC8CFD">A distributed operation works first on
					the region in the local cache and then distributes the operation to all other
					caches where the region is defined. This is the proper choice when the region is
					no longer needed, or valid, for any application in the distributed system. </li>
				<li
					id="li_DB59467843144D97897A3C548CCE5361">If the region on the server is
					configured as a partitioned region, it cannot be cleared using API calls from
					the native client. </li>
			</ul>
			<p>A user-defined cache writer can abort a region destroy operation. Cache writers are
				synchronous listeners with the ability to abort operations. If a cache writer is
				defined for the region anywhere in the distributed system, it is invoked before the
				region is explicitly destroyed. </p>
			<p>Region invalidation and destruction can cause other user-defined application plug-ins
				to be invoked as well. These plug-ins are described in detail in <xref
					scope="local"
					href="application-plugins.xml#application-plugins"
					type="concept"
					format="dita">Application Plug-Ins</xref>. </p>
			<p>Whether carried out explicitly or through expiration activities, invalidation and
				destruction cause event notification. </p>
		</section>
	</conbody>
</concept>
