<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE concept PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN" "http://docs.oasis-open.org/dita/v1.1/OS/dtd/concept.dtd">
<concept id="distributed_system_member_configuration">
	<title>Distributed System Members</title>
	<shortdesc id="shortdesc_CCB358DE4836432785185F5482665F97">Distributed system members are
		programs that connect to a <keyword keyref="product_name_long"/> distributed system. You
		configure members to belong to a single distributed system, and you can optionally configure
		them to be clients or servers to members in other distributed systems. </shortdesc>
	<conbody>
		<section id="section_326B2609B67E4FBE9BF2074C3B211E50">
			<title>Member Overview</title>
			<p>Distributed system members (or simply "members") connect to the <keyword
					keyref="product_name"/> system when they create the <keyword
					keyref="product_name"/> data cache. The members' distributed system is
				configured through <keyword keyref="product_name"/> properties. See <xref
					href="../../reference/topics/gemfire_properties.xml#gemfire_properties"
					type="concept" format="dita" scope="local"/>. <keyword keyref="product_name"/>
				properties specify all necessary information for system member startup,
				initialization, and communication. </p>
			<note>You cannot change a member's properties while the member is connected to the
				distributed system. </note>
			<p>Use the properties to define: <ul id="ul_bf5a420b-1732-49c5-b999-1630e74e7ef9">
					<li id="li_37BB8C96F9524F7988629333A6136DD5">How to find and communicate with
						other system members </li>
					<li id="li_A201D1C9F9D74F77AB841D2C434D3150">How to perform logging and
						statistics activities </li>
					<li id="li_1DCD0A06D34C4F689092022A96C1D011">Which persistent configuration or
							<codeph>cache.xml</codeph> file to use for cache and data region
						initialization </li>
					<li id="li_3A3D51B3B95444C988F61FD70A99F2B9">Other options, including event
						conflation, how to handle network loss, and security settings </li>
				</ul>
			</p>
		</section>
		<section id="section_E755E9E4A31149C980561D617A99A002">
			<title>Distributed System Membership and System Topologies</title>
			<p>Every <keyword keyref="product_name"/> process is a member of a distributed system,
				even if the distributed system is defined as standalone, with just one member. You
				can run an individual distributed system in isolation or you can combine systems for
				vertical and horizontal scaling. See <xref
					href="../../topologies_and_comm/topology_concepts/chapter_overview.xml"/>. <ul
					id="ul_D86A9A00CCBA4217BFF3E60948BC0A8B">
					<li id="li_D26747B1FB3947279105414165979447"><b>Peer-to-Peer Distributed
							Systems</b>. Members that define the same member discovery properties
						belong to the same distributed system and are peers to one another. </li>
					<li id="li_58030CD703274E5AB4D1FA032D8F4042"><b>Client/Server Installations</b>.
						The client/server topology uses relationships that you configure between
						members of multiple distributed systems. You configure some or all of the
						peers in one distributed system to act as cache servers to clients
						connecting from outside the system. Each server can host many client
						processes, managing cache access for all in an efficient, vertically
						hierarchical cache configuration. You configure the client applications to
						connect to the servers, using a client cache configuration. Clients run as
						members of standalone <keyword keyref="product_name"/> distributed systems,
						with no peers, so all data updates and requests go to the servers. </li>
				</ul>
			</p>
		</section>
	</conbody>
</concept>
