<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE concept PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN" "http://docs.oasis-open.org/dita/v1.1/OS/dtd/concept.dtd">
<concept id="how_server_discovery_works">
	<title>How Server Discovery Works</title>
	<shortdesc id="shortdesc_6F29E22AC25A437E97FA8F9DE7065353"><keyword keyref="product_name_long"/>
		locators provide reliable and flexible server discovery services for your clients. You can
		use all servers for all client requests, or group servers according to function, with the
		locators directing each client request to the right group of servers. </shortdesc>
	<conbody>
		<section id="section_91AC081D4C48408B9ABA40430F161E73">
			<p>By default, <keyword keyref="product_name"/> clients and servers discover each other
				on a predefined port (40404) on the localhost. This works, but is not typically the
				way you would deploy a client/server configuration. The recommended solution is to
				use one or more dedicated locators. A locator provides both discovery and load
				balancing services. With server locators, clients are configured with a locator list
				and locators maintain a dynamic server list. The locator listens at an address and
				port for connecting clients and gives the clients server information. The clients
				are configured with locator information and have no configuration specific to the
				servers. </p>
		</section>
		<section id="section_95B62F09EF954A99ABBDEBC2756812E3">
			<title>Basic Configuration</title>
			<p>In this figure, only one locator is shown, but the recommended configuration uses
				multiple locators for high availability. </p>
			<p>
				<image href="../../images_svg/server_discovery.svg"
					alt="Locators track server availability and send clients to the most available servers. Clients send updates and requests to servers. Servers respond and send server events to clients. "
					id="image_6DD8320AF78C42F89CFC665F2AF1BEA3" placement="break"/>
			</p>
			<p>The locator and servers have the same peer discovery configured in their
					<codeph>gemfire.properties</codeph>:  </p>
			<codeblock>locators=lucy[41111] </codeblock>
			<p>The servers, run on their respective hosts, have this <codeph>cache-server</codeph>
				configuration in their <codeph>cache.xml</codeph>:  </p>
			<codeblock>&lt;cache-server port="40404" ...</codeblock>
			<p>The client’s <codeph>cache.xml</codeph>
				<codeph>pool</codeph> configuration and <codeph>region-attributes</codeph>:  </p>
			<codeblock>&lt;pool name="PoolA" ...
  &lt;locator host="lucy" port="41111"&gt;

&lt;region ...
&lt;region-attributes pool-name="PoolA" ...    </codeblock>
		</section>
		<section id="section_7C4C60F40936432899CE86619B8D6CBF">
			<title>Using Member Groups</title>
			<p>You can control which servers are used with named member groups. Do this if you want
				your servers to manage different data sets or to direct specific client traffic to a
				subset of servers, such as those directly connected to a back-end database. </p>
			<p>To split data management between servers, configure some servers to host one set of
				data regions and some to host another set. Assign the servers to two separate member
				groups. Then, define two separate server pools on the client side and assign the
				pools to the proper corresponding client regions. </p>
			<p>In this figure, the client use of the regions is also split, but you could have both
				pools and both regions defined in all of your clients. </p>
			<p>
				<image href="../../images_svg/server_grouping.svg" alt=" "
					id="image_AB77DA6DB7EA49FD8864F39C6C64E056" placement="break"/>
			</p>
			<p>This is the <codeph>gemfire.properties</codeph> definition for Server 1:  </p>
			<codeblock>#gemfire.properties
groups=Portfolios</codeblock>
			<p>And the <codeph>pool</codeph> declaration for Client 1:  </p>
			<codeblock>&lt;pool name="PortfolioPool" server-group="Portfolios"...
  &lt;locator host="lucy" port="41111"&gt;</codeblock>
		</section>
	</conbody>
</concept>
