<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE concept PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN" "concept.dtd">
<concept id="membership_and_communication">
	<title>Planning Topology and Communication </title>
	<shortdesc id="shortdesc_3D09792BB7F54D7886BB78605D7D02FD">Create a topology plan and a detailed
		list of machines and communication ports that your members will use. Configure your <keyword
			keyref="product_name_long"/> systems and the communication between systems. </shortdesc>
	<conbody>
		<section id="section_AC0D7685A2CA4999A40BCEFD514BF599">
			<title>Determine Protocols and Addresses</title>
			<p>Your configuration governs how your applications find each other and distribute
				events and data among themselves.</p>
			<p> Work with your system administrator to determine the protocols and addresses you will use for
				membership and communication.<ol
					id="ol_4AD248AF77904667BAE4A8248896D109">
					<li id="li_E6D9546817224CE1B7B41A18628E9BF3">For each host machine with more
						than one network adapter card, decide whether to use the default address or
						one or more non-default bind addresses. You can use different cards for peer
						and server. </li>
					<li id="li_618EB76434254A44984E62B3ED8D0C97">Identify any members you want to
						run as standalone, isolated members with no member discovery. This can be
						a good option for clients, because it has faster startup but no peer-to-peer
						distribution of any kind. </li>
					<li id="li_AA27A370B606409A9A4E4DF688DBF274">For all non-standalone members: <ul
							id="ul_02422E597F444E70B28489278A193999">
							<li id="li_9F09DF00CDCE48ADA21ED7140A809022">Decide how many locators
								you will use and where they will run. To ensure the most stable
								startup and availability, use multiple locators on multiple
								machines.</li>
							<li id="li_lrw_lh1_2v">Create a list of your locators' address and port pairs. You will use
								the list to configure your system members, any clients, and the
								locators themselves. </li>
							<li id="li_85FB8AE15B30494A811F301171087EA1">If you will use
								multicasting for communication, note the addresses and ports. Select
								both unique multicast ports and unique addresses for your
								distributed systems. <note>Use different port numbers for different
									systems, even if you use different multicast addresses. Some
									operating systems do not keep communication separate between
									systems that have unique addresses but the same port number.
								</note></li>
						</ul></li>
				</ol></p>
		</section>
		<section id="section_vy1_cg1_2v">
			<title>Set Up Membership and Communication</title>
			<p>Using the protocols and addresses you determined above, do the following: <ul
					id="ol_1E6289A025014087B9DFC894A5B3F175">
					<li id="li_884B6067FDF141579042360D07AEBE9D">Set up membership in your systems. </li>
					<li id="li_FF878A26723941B39A02CD496E2C5380">Set up communication between system
						members. See <xref
							href="../p2p_configuration/setting_up_peer_communication.xml"
							type="concept" format="dita" scope="local"/>. </li>
					<li id="li_ECB41DC09D5148DE8BB80DC0A10FC312">As needed, set up communication
						between your systems. See <xref
							href="../cs_configuration/setting_up_a_client_server_system.xml#setting_up_a_client_server_system"
							type="task" format="dita" scope="local"/>. </li>
				</ul>
			</p>
		</section>
	</conbody>
</concept>