<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE concept PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN" "concept.dtd">
<concept id="concept_7628F498DB534A2D8A99748F5DA5DC94">
	<title>Topology Types</title>
	<shortdesc id="shortdesc_52FC7E83EEB241B2BB0E517FE66FF8DE">The <keyword
			keyref="product_name_long"/> topology options allow you to scale horizontally and
		vertically. </shortdesc>
	<conbody>
		<p><keyword keyref="product_name_long"/> provides a variety of cache topologies: <ul
				id="ul_6dda387c-55b4-4629-adf7-82828d360412">
				<li id="li_4DEF4FFCC28A4AB1A671AD4B45DEB68C">At the core of all systems is the
					single, peer-to-peer distributed system. </li>
				<li id="li_39A6DB5543774EC78DFD67CBCF867823">For horizontal and vertical scaling, you can
					combine individual systems into client/server and multi-site (WAN) topologies:
						<ul id="ul_4feacf96-0b93-4e01-97ce-3928651058b4">
						<li id="li_1F08C2C65A06435AA05D6B9A2AB7F714">In client/server systems, a
							small number of server processes manage data and event processing for a
							much larger client group. </li>
						<li id="li_55C12610D91D4F599E8C99FCE9254776">In multi-site systems, several
							geographically disparate systems are loosely coupled into a single,
							cohesive processing unit. </li>
					</ul>
				</li>
			</ul>
		</p>
		<section id="section_333142A36A3E4AF7A1EC31856ED99FCA">
			<title>Peer-to-Peer Configuration</title>
			<p>The peer-to-peer distributed system is the building block for all <keyword
					keyref="product_name"/> installations. Peer-to-peer alone is the simplest
				topology. Each cache instance, or member, directly communicates with every other
				member in the distributed system. This cache configuration is primarily designed for
				applications that need to embed a cache within the application process space and
				participate in a cluster. A typical example is an application server cluster in
				which the application and the cache are co-located and share the same heap. </p>
			<p><image href="../../images_svg/p2p_topology.svg" id="image_vzs_qwn_4r"/></p>
		</section>
		<section id="section_38F7D763AE32466299DC5B7DB9E71C61">
			<title>Client/Server Configuration</title>
			<p>The client/server topology is the model for vertical scaling, where clients typically
				host a small subset of the data in the application process space and delegate to the
				server system for the rest. Compared to peer-to-peer by itself, the client/server
				architecture provides better data isolation, high fetch performance, and more
				scalability. If data distribution will put a very heavy load on the network, a
				client/server architecture usually gives better performance. In any client/server
				installation, the server system is itself a peer-to-peer system, with data
				distributed between servers. A client system has a connection pool, which it uses to
				communicate with servers and other <keyword keyref="product_name"/> members. A
				client may also contain a local cache. </p>
			<p>
				<image href="../../images_svg/cs_topology.svg" placement="break"
					id="image_073094D7ED05419A9EE8E6AE552BE3F3"/>
			</p>
		</section>
		<section id="section_566EC05894D6461AA0E7DD7B065D457B">
			<title>Multi-site Configuration</title>
			<p>For horizontal scaling, you can use a loosely coupled multi-site topology. With
				multi-site, multiple <keyword keyref="product_name"/> systems are loosely coupled,
				generally across geographical distances with slower connections, such as with a WAN.
				This topology provides better performance than the tight coupling of a single
				system, and greater independence between locations, so that each site can function
				on its own if the connection or remote site become unavailable. In a multi-site
				installation, each individual site is a peer-to-peer or Client/Server system. </p>
			<p>
				<image href="../../images/multisite_topology.png"
					id="image_6501FD66F0F94273A1F7EEE5747B3925" placement="break"/>
			</p>
		</section>
	</conbody>
</concept>
