<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE concept PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN" "http://docs.oasis-open.org/dita/v1.1/OS/dtd/concept.dtd">
<concept id="transient_region_and_entry_statistics">
	<title>Transient Region and Entry Statistics</title>
	<shortdesc>For replicated, distributed, and local regions, <keyword keyref="product_name"/>
		provides a standard set of statistics for the region and its entries. </shortdesc>
	<conbody>
		<p><keyword keyref="product_name"/> gathers these statistics when the
				<codeph>--enable-statistics</codeph> parameter of the <codeph>create region</codeph>
			command of <codeph>gfsh</codeph> is set to true or in cache.xml the region attribute
				<codeph>statistics-enabled</codeph> is set to true.</p>
		<note>Unlike other <keyword
					keyref="product_name"/> statistics, these region and entry statistics are not
				archived and cannot be charted. </note>
			<note>Enabling these statistics requires extra memory per entry. See <xref
					href="../../reference/topics/memory_requirements_for_cache_data.xml#calculating_memory_requirements"
					type="concept" format="dita" scope="local"/>. </note>
		<p>These are the transient statistics gathered for all but partitioned regions: </p>
			<ul
				id="ul_47DF1DCBACA34E3ABBFC788B242DEE12">
				<li id="li_361B89FB8D0D461F976D8BCC383BC6A6"><b>Hit and miss counts</b>. For the
					entry, the hit count is the number of times the cached entry was accessed
					through the <codeph>Region.get</codeph> method and the miss count is the number
					of times these hits did not find a valid value. For the region these counts are
					the totals for all entries in the region. The API provides <codeph>get</codeph>
					methods for the hit and miss counts, a convenience method that returns the
					hit-to-miss ratio, and a method for zeroing the counts. </li>
				<li id="li_D30D723874264B10BA3373CDCBC6FC4B"><b>Last accessed time</b>. For the
					entry, this is the last time a valid value was retrieved from the locally cached
					entry. For the region, this is the most recent "last accessed time" for all
					entries contained in the region. This statistic is used for idle timeout
					expiration activities. </li>
				<li id="li_897E2785C5DA40A89BD68D3FCC42EC86"><b>Last modified time</b>. For the
					entry, this is the last time the entry value was updated (directly or through
					distribution) due to a load, create, or put operation. For the region, this is
					the most recent "last modified time" for all entries contained in the region.
					This statistic is used for time to live and idle timeout expiration activities.
				</li>
			</ul>
		<p>The hit and miss counts collected in these statistics can be useful for fine-tuning your
			system’s caches. If you have a region’s entry expiration enabled, for example, and see a
			high ratio of misses to hits on the entries, you might choose to increase the expiration
			times. </p>
		<p>Retrieve region and entry statistics through the <codeph>getStatistics</codeph> methods
			of the <codeph>Region</codeph> and <codeph>Region.Entry</codeph> objects. </p>
	</conbody>
</concept>
