<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="topic_06B28974C3D34C019418C92B1FC189C8">
	<title>Setting Up JMX Authentication for <keyword keyref="product_name"/> Management and Monitoring</title>
	<shortdesc> To force JMX clients such as <codeph>gfsh</codeph> and <keyword keyref="product_name"/> Pulse to authenticate
		into the <keyword keyref="product_name"/> management system, you must configure the JMX Manager node. </shortdesc>
	<body>
		<p>By default, the JMX manager allows clients without credentials to connect. To set up JMX
			authentication for the management system: <ol id="ol_0F67C8B1EE584E8BAFA1B52D0EF3FBEC">
				<li id="li_13A1A9F3E2DE476BA88374EAA4E66634">Verify that the
					<codeph>jmx-manager</codeph> <keyword keyref="product_name"/> property is set to true on any node
					that you want to be able to become a JMX Manager and authenticate clients. If
					this property is set to false or not specified, then all other jmx-manager-*
					properties are ignored. </li>
				<li id="li_4ED6801E01B74845AC22AAF1817B8AD4">Create a password file that contains
					entries for the user names and passwords you want to grant access to <keyword keyref="product_name"/>'s
					management and monitoring system. For example:
					<codeblock>
#the gemfiremonitor user has password Abc!@#
#the gemfiremanager user has password 123Gh2!

gemfiremonitor Abc!@#
gemfiremanager 123Gh2!</codeblock>
				</li>
				<li id="li_7E8ADDFB522746D9A99A731EF3ED7022">On each of your JMX Manager-enabled
					nodes, set the property <codeph>jmx-manager-password-file</codeph> to
					the name of the file you created in step 2. This will require clients to
					authenticate when connecting to a JMX Manager node in <keyword keyref="product_name"/>. </li>
				<li id="li_EE1534A8603841F89EDDB2DDA3448865">If you wish to further restrict access
					to system operations, you can also set up an access file for the JMX Manager.
					The access file indicates whether the users listed in the password file have the
					ability to read system MBeans (monitor the system) or whether they can
					additionally modify MBeans (perform operations). For example, you can define the
					following:
					<codeblock>
#the gemfiremonitor user has readonly access
#the gemfiremanager user has readwrite access

gemfiremonitor readonly
gemfiremanager readwrite</codeblock>
				</li>
				<li id="li_DC1623D94F8A4FA0B0A8CB8673EBCCAC">On each of your JMX Manager-enabled
					nodes, set the <keyword keyref="product_name"/> property <codeph>jmx-manager-access-file</codeph> to the
					name of the file you created in step 4. This will associate MBean permissions to
					the users who authenticate to the JMX Manager node in <keyword keyref="product_name"/>. </li>
				<li id="li_09F5231FD0BE4A7FBAC9AAE0E79E4644">If desired, enable SSL for your JMX
					Manager connections. If you enable SSL for <keyword keyref="product_name"/> peer-to-peer connections,
					then by default the same SSL configuration is applied to the JMX manager. You
					can override the SSL configuration for JMX clients by configuring JMX manager
					configuration properties (such as <codeph>jmx-manager-ssl</codeph>) in the
						<codeph>gfsecurity.properties</codeph> file. See <xref
						href="implementing_ssl.xml#implementing_ssl" type="concept" format="dita"
						scope="local"/>. </li>
			</ol>
		</p>
		<p> </p>
		<p>For more information on the format of the password and access file, see <xref
				href="http://docs.oracle.com/javase/6/docs/technotes/guides/management/agent.html"
				scope="external" format="html"
				><?xm-replace_text http://docs.oracle.com/javase/6/docs/technotes/guides/management/agent.html?></xref>.
		</p>
	</body>
</topic>
