<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE concept PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN" "http://docs.oasis-open.org/dita/v1.1/OS/dtd/concept.dtd">
<concept id="setting_up_logging">
	<title>Set Up Logging</title>
	<shortdesc>You configure logging in a member's <codeph>gemfire.properties</codeph> or at startup
		with <codeph>gfsh</codeph>. </shortdesc>
	<conbody>
		<section id="section_35F8A9028A91441785BCACD6CD40A498">
			<p>Before you begin, make sure you understand <xref
					href="../../basic_config/book_intro.xml" type="concept"
					format="dita" scope="local"/>. <ol id="ol_BA9F16EB6E5A4D2D8CB65E26B9DDA306">
					<li id="li_203ADCB6282B4D93B3CC1ECB8066DB31">Run a time synchronization service
						such as NTP on all <keyword keyref="product_name"/> host machines. This is the only way to produce
						logs that are useful for troubleshooting. Synchronized time stamps ensure
						that log messages from different hosts can be merged to accurately reproduce
						a chronological history of a distributed run. </li>
					<li id="li_75478AD436E7452C96C7632746692168">Use a sniffer to monitor your logs
					Look for  new or unexpected warnings, errors, or severe
						messages. The logs output by your system
						have their own characteristics, indicative of your system configuration and
						of the particular behavior of your applications, so you must become familiar
						with your applications' logs to use them effectively. </li>
					<li id="li_F7DDE6F7549C43F2A42C6E314CB14E13">Configure member logging in each
						member's <codeph>gemfire.properties</codeph> as needed: <codeblock># Default <codeph>gemfire.properties</codeph> log file settings
log-level=config
log-file=
log-file-size-limit=0
log-disk-space-limit=0</codeblock>
						<note>You can also specify logging parameters when you start up members
							(either locators or servers) using the <codeph>gfsh</codeph>
							command-line utility. See <xref
								href="../../tools_modules/gfsh/command-pages/start.xml#topic_3151ACDA3677431BB5059EB7FCB47D87"
								type="topic" format="dita" scope="local"/> commands for various
							examples. In addition, you can modify log file properties and log-level
							settings while a member is already running by using the <xref
								href="../../tools_modules/gfsh/command-pages/alter.xml#topic_7E6B7E1B972D4F418CB45354D1089C2B"
								type="topic" format="dita" scope="local"/> command. </note>
						<ol id="ol_E500EBEF363246A7855DE97D002A5121">
							<li id="li_06B41BC1477D4575B23EEB7B8AEBC496">Set
									<codeph>log-level</codeph>. Options are <codeph>severe</codeph>
								(the highest level), <codeph>error</codeph>,
									<codeph>warning</codeph>, <codeph>info</codeph>,
									<codeph>config</codeph>, and <codeph>fine</codeph>. The lower
								levels include higher level settings, so a setting of
									<codeph>warning</codeph> would log <codeph>warning</codeph>,
									<codeph>error</codeph>, and <codeph>severe</codeph> messages.
								For general troubleshooting, we recommend setting the log level at
									<codeph>config</codeph> or higher. <note>The
										<codeph>fine</codeph> setting can fill up disk too quickly
									and impact system performance. Use <codeph>fine</codeph> only if
									asked to do so by Pivotal technical support. </note>
							</li>
							<li id="li_5D548D8A108B40B88ED5C10F893AAE1A">Specify the log file name
								in <codeph>log-file</codeph>. This can be relative or absolute. If
								this property is not specified, the defaults are: <ul
									id="ul_334BF8A4E60741CBBF4397197E3F3475">
									<li id="li_13D00B3255BE45B2A076D69752C7AD38">Standard output for
										applications </li>
									<li id="li_ADE2F80A17CB46C7999E20A1246B6FED">For servers, the
										default log file location is:
										<codeblock><i>working-directory</i>/<i>server-name</i>.log</codeblock>
										By default, when starting a server through
											<codeph>gfsh</codeph>, the <i>working -directory</i>
										corresponds to the directory (named after itself) that the
										cache server creates upon startup. Alternatively, you can
										specify a different working directory path when you start
										the cache server. The <i>server-name</i> corresponds to the
										name of the cache server provided upon startup. </li>
									<li id="li_963AEAFD9CA64FAA83EFCE744BCED3EB">For a standalone
										locator, the default log file location is:
										<codeblock><i>working-directory</i>/<i>locator-name</i>.log</codeblock>By
										default, when starting a locator through
											<codeph>gfsh</codeph>, the <i>working -directory</i>
										corresponds to the directory (named after itself) created
										when the locator starts up. Alternatively, you can specify a
										different working directory path when you start a locator.
										The <i>locator-name</i> corresponds to the name of the
										locator provided upon startup. If you are using a colocated
										or embedded locator, the locator logs will be part of the
										member’s log file. </li>
								</ul> For the easiest logs examination and troubleshooting, send
								your logs to files instead of standard out. <note>Make sure each
									member logs to its own files. This makes the logs easier to
									decipher. </note>
							</li>
							<li id="li_C6FE572C73894C8CB2FEC64BA9C331AE">Set the maximum size of a
								single log file in <codeph>log-file-size-limit</codeph>. If not set,
								the single, main log file is used. If set, the metadata file, the
								main log, and rolled child logs are used. </li>
							<li id="li_9C91AA757A8C43089E1C406F95E91A65">Set the maximum size of all
								log files in <codeph>log-disk-space-limit</codeph>. If non-zero,
								this limits the combined size of all inactive log files, deleting
								oldest files first to stay under the limit. A zero setting indicates
								no limit. </li>
						</ol>
					</li>
					<li id="li_FE4346D259034DD39F0797A4B8090D58">If you are using the
							<codeph>gfsh</codeph> command-line interface, <codeph>gfsh</codeph> can
						creates its own log file in the directory where you run the
							<codeph>gfsh</codeph> or <codeph>gfsh.bat</codeph> script. By default,
						gfsh does not generate log files for itself. To enable gfsh logs, set the
						following system property to the desired log level before starting
							gfsh:<codeblock>export JAVA_ARGS=-Dgfsh.log-level=[severe|warning|info|config|fine|finer|finest]</codeblock><p>gfsh
							log files are named <codeph>gfsh-0_0.log</codeph>.</p>
					</li>
				</ol>
			</p>
		</section>
	</conbody>
</concept>
