<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE concept PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN" "http://docs.oasis-open.org/dita/v1.1/OS/dtd/concept.dtd">
<concept id="handling_network_partitioning">
	<title>Configure <keyword keyref="product_name_long"/> to Handle Network Partitioning</title>
	<shortdesc>This section lists the configuration steps for network partition detection. </shortdesc>
	<conbody>
		<section id="section_EAF1957B6446491A938DEFB06481740F">
			<p>The system uses a combination of member coordinators and system members, designated
				as lead members, to detect and resolve network partitioning problems. <ol
					id="ol_4D41D7E7ABD64FBA96A1C1075E1D0B7C">
					<li id="li_0CBFE55931764F89A7DD9EB50F2EED54">Network partition detection can
						work in multicast or in locator-based environments. If you are using
						locators for member discovery, use multiple locators. See <xref
							href="../../topologies_and_comm/p2p_configuration/setting_up_a_p2p_system.xml"
							type="concept" format="dita" scope="local"/>. </li>
					<li id="li_1D5D74CEB2C140149357D9300FD41E33">Enable partition detection
						consistently in all system members by setting this in their
							<codeph>gemfire.properties</codeph>: <codeblock>enable-network-partition-detection=true</codeblock>
						<p>Enable network partition detection in all locators and in any other
							process that should be sensitive to network partitioning. Processes that
							do not have network partition detection enabled are not eligible to be
							the lead member, so their failure will not trigger declaration of a
							network partition. </p><p>All system members should have the same
							setting for <codeph>enable-network-partition-detection</codeph>. If they
							don’t, the system throws a <codeph>GemFireConfigException</codeph> upon
							startup. </p>
					</li>
					<li id="li_041FAD4374304D66B5BCDDE26A0AEAA3">You must set
							<codeph>enable-network-partition-detection</codeph> to true if you are
						using persistent partitioned regions. You <b>must</b> set
							<codeph>enable-network-partition-detection</codeph> to true if you are
						using persistent regions (partitioned or replicated). If you create a
						persistent region and <codeph>enable-network-partition-detection</codeph> to
						set to false, you will receive the following warning
						message:<codeblock>Creating persistent region {0}, but enable-network-partition-detection is set to false.
      Running with network partition detection disabled can lead to an unrecoverable system in the
      event of a network split."</codeblock>
					</li>
					<li id="li_89FC37CD3A1B4B6097F4C5427FB642ED">Configure regions you want to
						protect from network partitioning with <codeph>DISTRIBUTED_ACK</codeph> or
							<codeph>GLOBAL</codeph>
						<codeph>scope</codeph>. Do not use <codeph>DISTRIBUTED_NO_ACK</codeph>
						<codeph>scope</codeph>. The region configurations provided in the region
						shortcut settings use <codeph>DISTRIBUTED_ACK</codeph> scope. This setting
						prevents operations from performed throughout the distributed system before
						a network partition is detected. <note>GemFire issues an alert if it detects
							distributed-no-ack regions when network partition detection is enabled:
							<codeblock>Region {0} is being created with scope {1} but enable-network-partition-detection is enabled in the distributed system. 
This can lead to cache inconsistencies if there is a network failure.</codeblock>
						</note>
					</li>
					<li id="li_413E2A707E874315B675816B75DDE198">These other configuration
						parameters affect or interact with network partitioning detection. Check
						whether they are appropriate for your installation and modify as needed. <ul
							id="ul_0A3F55D1993A4BCEABEB600416A6AF07">
							<li id="li_16A3B19AC5BB4D538B4A223C8A3CD9D3">If you have network
								partition detection enabled, the threshold percentage value for
								allowed membership weight loss is automatically configured to 51.
								You cannot modify this value. (<b>Note:</b> The weight loss
								calculation uses standard rounding. Therefore, a value of 50.51 is
								rounded to 51 and will cause a network partition.) </li>
							<li id="li_BD8192404E6448BE97A082DC145C6BC4">Failure detection is
								initiated if a member's <codeph>gemfire.properties</codeph>
								<codeph>ack-wait-threshold</codeph> (default is 15 seconds) and
									<codeph>ack-severe-alert-threshold</codeph> (15 seconds) elapses
								before receiving a response to a message. If you modify the
									<codeph>ack-wait-threshold</codeph> configuration value, you
								should modify <codeph>ack-severe-alert-threshold</codeph> to match
								the other configuration value. </li>
							<li id="li_9A3280732F9C4C93AE17C2C9185C907B">If the system has clients
								connecting to it, the clients' <codeph>cache.xml</codeph>
								<codeph>&lt;cache&gt; &lt;pool&gt; read-timeout</codeph> should be
								set to at least three times the <codeph>member-timeout</codeph>
								setting in the server's <codeph>gemfire.properties</codeph>. The
								default <codeph>&lt;cache&gt; &lt;pool&gt; read-timeout</codeph>
								setting is 10000 milliseconds. </li>
							<li id="li_44107C9E1D4F4976BD9EF9F719248CC5">You can adjust the default
								weights of members by specifying the system property
									<codeph>gemfire.member-weight</codeph> upon startup. For
								example, if you have some VMs that host a needed service, you could
								assign them a higher weight upon startup. </li>
							<li>By default, members that are forced out of the distributed system by
								a network partition event will automatically restart and attempt to
								reconnect. Data members will attempt to reinitialize the cache. See
									<xref
									href="../autoreconnect/member-reconnect.xml"
								/>. You can modify the number of times that a member will try to
								reconnect by specifying the <codeph>max-num-reconnect-tries</codeph>
								property.</li>
						</ul>
					</li>
				</ol>
			</p>
		</section>
	</conbody>
</concept>
