<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE dita PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Composite//EN" "ditabase.dtd">
<dita>
	<topic id="topic_523F6DE33FE54307BBE8F83BB7D9355D">
		<title>Pulse Quick Start (Embedded Mode)</title>
		<shortdesc>Use Pulse in embedded mode to monitor a <keyword keyref="product_name"/>
			deployment directly from a <keyword keyref="product_name"/> JMX Manager. By default, the
			embedded Pulse application connects to the local JMX Manager that hosts the Pulse
			application. Optionally, configure Pulse to connect to a <keyword keyref="product_name"
			/> system of your choice. </shortdesc>
		<body>
			<p>To run Pulse in embedded mode:  </p>
			<ol id="ol_fgr_2hg_2w">
				<li>
					<p>Configure a <keyword keyref="product_name"/> member to run as a JMX Manager
						node, specifying the HTTP port on which you will access the Pulse Web
						application (port 7070 by default). For example, the following command
						starts a <keyword keyref="product_name"/> locator as a JMX Manager node,
						using the default HTTP port 7070 for the Pulse application: </p>
					<codeblock>gfsh
gfsh&gt; start locator --name=loc1</codeblock>
					<note>
						<p><keyword keyref="product_name"/> locators become JMX Manager nodes by
						default. To start a non-locator member as a JMX Manager node, include the
							<codeph>--J=-Dgemfire.jmx-manager=true</codeph> option. To specify a
						non-default port number for the HTTP service that hosts the Pulse
						application, include the
								<codeph>--J=-Dgemfire.http-service-port=<i>port_number</i></codeph>
						option when starting the JMX Manager node.
						</p>
					</note>
					<p>When the JMX Manager node boots, it starts an embedded Jetty instance and
						deploys the Pulse Web application at the specified or default HTTP port or
						7070 by default. </p>
					<p><codeph>gfsh</codeph> automatically connects to the manager when you start it
						in this way. If you already started a manager process earlier, use the
							<codeph>connect</codeph> command in <codeph>gfsh</codeph> to connect to
						that process. </p>
				</li>
				<li>
					<p>Access the embedded Pulse application from a Web browser. If you are
						connected to the <keyword keyref="product_name"/> cluster using gfsh, use
						the <codeph>start pulse</codeph> command to load the correct URL in your
						browser: </p>
					<codeblock>gfsh&gt; start pulse</codeblock>
					<p>Or, enter the URL http://<i>address</i>:<i>http-service-port</i>/pulse
						directly in your Web browser, substituting the address and HTTP port of the
						manager. For example, you access Pulse on the local locator machine from
						Step 1 at the URL http://localhost:7070/pulse. </p>
				</li>
				<li>If you have configured authentication for the Pulse application, enter the
					username and password of a valid Pulse account in the login screen. Otherwise,
					enter the default "admin" in both fields. Click <b>Sign In</b> to continue.
						<p>See <xref scope="local"
							href="quickstart.xml#topic_AC9FFAA6FB044279BAED7A3E099E07AC"
							type="topic" format="dita"/>. </p>
				</li>
				<li>After you log in, Pulse displays the main cluster view for the local distributed
					system. See <xref href="quickstart.xml#topic_F0ECE9E8179541CCA3D6C5F4FBA84404"
						type="topic" format="dita" scope="local"/>. </li>
			</ol>
			<note>
				<p>When running in embedded mode, the Pulse application connects only to the JMX Manager
				running in the locator or member that hosts Pulse. This enables you to monitor all
				members of that distributed system. You can also view (but not monitor) connected
				WAN clusters, and can view gateway senders and receivers that are configured in the
				local cluster. 
				</p>
			</note>
		</body>
	</topic>
	<topic id="topic_795C97B46B9843528961A094EE520782">
		<title>Hosting Pulse on a Web Application Server</title>
		<shortdesc>Host Pulse on a dedicated Web application server to make the Pulse application
			available at a consistent address, or to use SSL for accessing the Pulse application.
			When you host Pulse in this way, you also configure Pulse to connect to a specific
			locator or JMX Manager node for monitoring. </shortdesc>
		<body>
			<p>To host Pulse on a Web application server:  </p>
			<ol id="ol_gzt_hhg_2w">
				<li>Set the <codeph>http-service-port</codeph> property to zero
						(<codeph>-Dgemfire.http-service-port=0</codeph>) when you start your
						<keyword keyref="product_name"/> JMX Manager nodes. Setting this property to
					zero disables the embedded Web server for hosting the Pulse application. </li>
				<li>
					<p>Create a <codeph>pulse.properties</codeph> file somewhere in the
						classpath of your Web application server. For example, if you are hosting
						Pulse on Tomcat, create the <codeph>pulse.properties</codeph> file in
						the <codeph>$TOMCAT_SERVER/lib</codeph> directory. </p>
				</li>
				<li>Define the following configuration properties in the
						<codeph>pulse.properties</codeph> file: <table id="table_hzt_hhg_2w">
						<tgroup cols="2">
							<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1" colwidth="*"/>
							<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" colwidth="*"/>
							<thead>
								<row>
									<entry colname="col1">Property </entry>
									<entry colname="col2">Description </entry>
								</row>
							</thead>
							<tbody>
								<row>
									<entry colname="col1"><codeph>pulse.useLocator</codeph>
									</entry>
									<entry colname="col2">Specify "true" to configure Pulse to
										connect to a <keyword keyref="product_name"/> Locator
										member, or "false" to connect directly to a JMX Manager.
											<p>When Pulse connects to a <keyword
												keyref="product_name"/> locator, the locator
											provides the address and port of an available JMX
											Manager to use for monitoring the distributed system. In
											most production deployments, you should connect Pulse to
											a locator instance; this allows Pulse to provide
											monitoring services using any available JMX Manager. </p>
										<p>If you specify "false," Pulse connects directly to a
											specific JMX Manager. If this manager is not available,
											the Pulse connection fails, even if another JMX Manager
											is available in the distributed system. </p>
									</entry>
								</row>
								<row>
									<entry colname="col1"><codeph>pulse.host</codeph>
									</entry>
									<entry colname="col2">Specify the DNS name or IP address of the
											<keyword keyref="product_name"/> locator or JMX Manager
										machine to which Pulse should connect. You specify either a
										locator or JMX Manager address depending on how you
										configured the <codeph>pulse.useLocator</codeph> property.
									</entry>
								</row>
								<row>
									<entry colname="col1"><codeph>pulse.port</codeph>
									</entry>
									<entry colname="col2">Specify the port number of the <keyword
											keyref="product_name"/> locator or the HTTP port number
										of the JMX Manager to which Pulse should connect. You
										specify either a locator or JMX Manager port depending on
										how you configured the <codeph>pulse.useLocator</codeph>
										property. <p>If you configured
												<codeph>pulse.useLocator=false</codeph>, then
												<codeph>pulse.port</codeph> must correspond to the
												<codeph>http-service-port</codeph> setting of the
											JMX Manager. </p>
									</entry>
								</row>
								<row>
									<entry colname="col1"><codeph>pulse.jmxUserName</codeph>
									</entry>
									<entry colname="col2">If you configured authentication for the
											<keyword keyref="product_name"/> JMX Manager node,
										specify a valid JMX user name that the Pulse application
										will use to authenticate to the JMX Manager.
										<note>
											<p>The JMX
											account that Pulse uses must have both read and write
											privileges.
											</p>
										</note>
										<p>See <xref scope="local"
												href="../../managing/management/jmx_manager_operations.xml#topic_263072624B8D4CDBAD18B82E07AA44B6"
												type="topic" format="dita"/> for information about
											configuring authentication for JMX Manager nodes. </p>
									</entry>
								</row>
								<row>
									<entry colname="col1"><codeph>pulse.jmxUserPassword</codeph>
									</entry>
									<entry colname="col2">Specify the password of the JMX user
										account to use for authentication at startup. </entry>
								</row>
							</tbody>
						</tgroup>
					</table>
					<p>For example, with this configuration Pulse connects to the locator at
						mylocator[10334] and accesses any available JMX Manager: </p><codeblock>pulse.useLocator=true
pulse.host=locsrv.gemstone.com
pulse.port=10334
pulse.jmxUserName=pulseapp
pulse.jmxUserPassword=pulsepass</codeblock>
					<p>With this configuration Pulse accesses only the JMX Manager instance at
						manager1[8080]:
					</p><codeblock>pulse.useLocator=false
pulse.host=jmxsrv.gemstone.com
pulse.port=8080
pulse.jmxUserName=pulseapp
pulse.jmxUserPassword=pulsepass</codeblock>
				</li>
				<li>(Optional.) Configure authentication for the Pulse Web application using the
					instructions in <xref
						href="quickstart.xml#topic_AC9FFAA6FB044279BAED7A3E099E07AC" type="topic"
						format="dita" scope="local"/>. </li>
				<li>Deploy the Pulse Web application to your application server. <keyword
						keyref="product_name"/> installs the <codeph>pulse.war</codeph> file in
					the <codeph>tools/Pulse</codeph> subdirectory of your <keyword
						keyref="product_name"/> installation directory. Depending on your
					application server, you may need to copy the <codeph>pulse.war</codeph> file
					to a deployment directory or use a configuration tool to deploy the file. </li>
				<li>
					<p>Access the Pulse application using the address, port, and application URL
						that you configure in your Web application server. For example, with Tomcat
						the default URL is http://<i>address</i>:8080/pulse. Your application server
						provides options for configuring the address, port, and application name;
						substitute the correct items to access the deployed Pulse application. </p>
					<p>Pulse connects to the locator or JMX Manager that you configured in the
							<codeph>pulse.properties</codeph> file, authenticating using the
						credentials that you configured in the file. </p>
				</li>
				<li>If you have configured authentication for the Pulse application, enter the
					username and password of a valid Pulse account in the login screen. Otherwise,
					enter the default "admin" in both fields. Click <b>Sign In</b> to continue.
						<p>See <xref scope="local"
							href="quickstart.xml#topic_AC9FFAA6FB044279BAED7A3E099E07AC"
							type="topic" format="dita"/>. </p>
				</li>
				<li>After you log in, Pulse displays the main cluster view for the distributed
					system to which it has connected. See <xref
						href="quickstart.xml#topic_F0ECE9E8179541CCA3D6C5F4FBA84404" type="topic"
						format="dita" scope="local"/>. </li>
			</ol>
		</body>
	</topic>
	<topic id="topic_AC9FFAA6FB044279BAED7A3E099E07AC">
		<title>Configuring Pulse Authentication</title>
		<shortdesc>Pulse requires all users to authenticate themselves before they can use the Pulse
			Web application. If you have configured JMX authentication on the <keyword
				keyref="product_name"/> JMX Manager node, the Pulse Web application itself may also
			need to authenticate itself to the <keyword keyref="product_name"/> JMX Manager node on
			startup. </shortdesc>
		<body>
			<section id="section_D31C25130C3D470083DAC76AE64DD1B6">
				<title>Authenticating the Pulse Application to the JMX Manager</title>
				<p>If you run Pulse in embedded mode, the Pulse application runs on the JMX Manager
					node and no JMX authentication is required. You do not need to specify valid JMX
					credentials to start an embedded Pulse application. </p>
				<p>If you host Pulse on a Web Application server (non-embedded mode) and you
					configure JMX authentication on the <keyword keyref="product_name"/> manager
					node, then the Pulse Web application must authenticate itself with the manager
					node when it starts. Specify the credentials of a valid JMX user account in the
						<codeph>pulse.properties</codeph> file, as described in <xref
						href="quickstart.xml#topic_795C97B46B9843528961A094EE520782" type="topic"
						format="dita" scope="local"/>. </p>
				<note>
					<p>The credentials that you specify must have both read and write privileges in
					the JMX Manager node. See <xref scope="local"
						href="../../managing/management/jmx_manager_operations.xml#topic_263072624B8D4CDBAD18B82E07AA44B6"
						type="topic" format="dita"/>.
					</p>
				</note>
			</section>
			<section id="section_E3703ED899354839BE51278D3AE79062">
				<title>Authenticating Pulse Users</title>
				<p>Pulse implements user authentication using the Spring security framework. The
					authentication configuration is specified in the
						<codeph>spring-security.xml</codeph> file, which is stored in the
						<codeph>WEB-INF</codeph> directory of Pulse WAR file. The
						<codeph>spring-security.xml</codeph> file contains bean definitions for
					role-based resource access, authentication profiles, and authentication
					handlers. The file also contains a default authentication manager bean
					definition.</p>
				<p>Pulse uses a profile-based authentication configuration. You can can choose to
					use either the default configuration profile or a custom configuration. The
					default profile uses the Spring security simple in-memory User Details Service
					to define a single user with the credentials:</p>
				<simpletable frame="all"
						relcolwidth="1.0* 1.0*" id="simpletable_ntf_qg2_xn">
						<strow>
							<stentry>User Name:</stentry>
							<stentry>admin</stentry>
						</strow>
						<strow>
							<stentry>Password:</stentry>
							<stentry>admin</stentry>
						</strow>
						<strow>
							<stentry>Role:</stentry>
							<stentry>ROLE_USER</stentry>
						</strow>
					</simpletable>
				<p>Pulse uses this default authentication profile if you do not specify a profile when starting
					the application, or if you specify the default profile at startup using the
					system property:</p>
				<codeblock>-Dspring.profiles.active=pulse.authentication.default</codeblock>
				<p>You can also configure Pulse to use a custom authentication configuration by specifying
					activating the custom profile at startup with the system property:</p>
				<codeblock>-Dspring.profiles.active=pulse.authentication.custom</codeblock>
				<p>Using a custom configuration enables you to use either the simple in-memory User
					Details Service or an external properties file to authenticate users to the
					application. Even if you choose to use the default Spring security simple
					in-memory User Details Service, using a custom authentication configuration
					enables you to define your own user credentials rather than using the default
					"admin" account. </p>
				<note>
					<p><keyword keyref="product_name"/> also supports using an LDAP provider for
					Pulse authentication. See <xref
						href="#topic_AC9FFAA6FB044279BAED7A3E099E07AC/section_kjx_ylq_kq"
						format="dita"/>
					</p>
				</note>
				<p>To configure and use a custom authentication configuration:</p>
				<ol id="ol_tj3_53z_dw">
					<li>Create a directory in which you will store the custom authentication
						configuration. For
						example:<codeblock>$ mkdir /opt/pulse-config</codeblock></li>
					<li>Ensure that the new directory you created is available on the Java
						CLASSPATH:<codeblock>$ export CLASSPATH=$CLASSPATH:/opt/pulse-config</codeblock></li>
					<li>Create a new text file named
							<codeph>pulse-authentication-custom.xml</codeph> in the new
						directory:<codeblock>$ touch /opt/pulse-config/pulse-authentication-custom.xml</codeblock></li>
					<li>Use a text editor to add the bean definitions for the authentication
						managers and providers that you want to use. The following listings show the
						example file contents for using the in-memory User Details Service and an
						external properties file:<p><b>Example pulse-authentication-custom.xml for
								Spring simple in-memory User Details
								Service</b></p><codeblock>&lt;beans:beans >
  &lt;authentication-manager>
    &lt;authentication-provider>
      &lt;user-service id="userDetailsService">
        &lt;user name="<varname>john</varname>" password="<varname>johnspassword</varname>" authorities="ROLE_USER " />
        &lt;user name="<varname>bob</varname>" password="<varname>bobspassword</varname>" authorities="ROLE_USER" />
      &lt;/user-service>
    &lt;/authentication-provider>
  &lt;/authentication-manager>
&lt;/beans:beans></codeblock><p><b>Example
								pulse-authentication-custom.xml for external properties
							file</b></p><codeblock>&lt;beans:beans >
  &lt;authentication-manager>
    &lt;authentication-provider>
      &lt;user-service properties="classpath:pulse-users.properties">
      &lt;/user-service>
    &lt;/authentication-provider>
  &lt;/authentication-manager>
&lt;/beans:beans></codeblock><p>With
							file-based authentication mechanism, you define the names and passwords
							for valid Pulse users in a <codeph>pulse-users.properties</codeph>
							file, which must be available in the classpath of the Pulse application.
							Each line in the <codeph>pulse-users.properties</codeph> file
							defines the username, password, and access level for a Pulse user with
							the format:
							</p><codeblock><i>username</i>=<i>password</i>,<i>role</i>,{enabled | disabled}</codeblock><p>The
								<i>role</i> entry must correspond to a valid Spring security role.
							For example, this entry shows the default "admin" user enabled with
							basic user access:
						</p><codeblock>admin=admin,ROLE_USER,enabled</codeblock></li>
					<li>When you start <keyword keyref="product_name"/> members, specify the custom
						authentication profile using the
							<codeph>-Dspring.profiles.active=pulse.authentication.custom</codeph>
						system property. For
						example:<codeblock>gfsh> start server --name=server1 --J=-Dspring.profiles.active=pulse.authentication.custom</codeblock></li>
					<li>Start Pulse and log in using credentials that are authorized in the custom
						configuration.</li>
				</ol>
			</section>
			<section id="section_kjx_ylq_kq">
				<title>Using LDAP Authentication in Pulse</title>
				<p>This section provides instructions for using LDAP authentication with Pulse in
					either embedded and non-embedded mode.</p>
				<p>
					<b>Embedded Mode (Jetty)</b>
				</p>
				<p>To configure LDAP for Pulse:</p>
				<ol id="ol_vfq_wtq_kq">
					<li>Create a directory in which you will store the LDAP authentication
						configuration. For
						example:<codeblock>$ mkdir /opt/pulse-config</codeblock>The directory name
						and location are up to you-- just make sure you use the same name when
						specifying the CLASSPATH for the <keyword keyref="product_name"/> JMX
						Manager process.</li>
					<li>Create a file named <codeph>pulse-authentication-custom.xml</codeph>
						with contents similar to the following and place it under the directory you
						created in step 1. For
						example:<codeblock>&lt;beans:beans xmlns="http://www.springframework.org/schema/security"
   	xmlns:beans="http://www.springframework.org/schema/beans"
   	xmlns:context="http://www.springframework.org/schema/context"
   	xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
   	xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.springframework.org/schema/beans
   	http://www.springframework.org/schema/beans/spring-beans-3.2.xsd
               http://www.springframework.org/schema/security
               http://www.springframework.org/schema/security/spring-security-3.1.xsd
               http://www.springframework.org/schema/context
   	http://www.springframework.org/schema/context/spring-context-3.2.xsd">
   	
        &lt;ldap-server url="ldap://ldap.gemstone.com:389/dc=gemstone,dc=com" />

        &lt;authentication-manager>
           &lt;ldap-authentication-provider user-dn-pattern="uid={0},ou=ldapTesting"  
            group-search-base="cn=PULSEUSER,ou=Groups" group-search-filter="memberUid={1}">
           &lt;/ldap-authentication-provider>
       &lt;/authentication-manager>
 
&lt;/beans:beans></codeblock>LDAP
						authentication in Pulse is hardcoded to use the PULSEUSER user group. Make
						sure you have have created users for this group.</li>
					<li>When starting the JMX Manager from gfsh, use the following
						commands:<codeblock>gfsh>start locator --name=loc --J=-Dspring.profiles.active=pulse.authentication.custom --classpath=/opt/pulse-config</codeblock>or
						<codeblock>gfsh>start server --name=server1 --J=-Dspring.profiles.active=pulse.authentication.custom --classpath=/opt/pulse-config</codeblock></li>
					<li>Start Pulse and log in using credentials that are authorized in the LDAP
						configuration.</li>
				</ol>
				<p>
					<b>Non-Embedded (Standalone Web Server) Mode (Tomcat)</b>
				</p>
				<p>To configure LDAP for Pulse:</p>
				<ol id="ol_jgb_mwq_kq">
					<li>Create a directory in which you will store the LDAP authentication
						configuration. For
						example:<codeblock>$ mkdir /opt/pulse-config</codeblock></li>
					<li>The directory name and location of the Pulse configuration files are up to
						you-- just make sure you use the same name when specifying the CLASSPATH for
						the Tomcat server.</li>
					<li>Pass in the Spring profile when starting the web server. In Tomcat, all the
						VM arguments are set in the variable CATALINA_OPTS, which you can define in
						your environment configuration file setenv.bat or setenv.sh. <p>For example,
							under %CATALINA_HOME%/bin or $CATALINA_HOME/bin, you can create a setenv
							batch file or script file (if not already present) that sets the
							following. On
						Windows:</p><codeblock>set CATALINA_OPTS=-Dspring.profiles.active=pulse.authentication.custom
set "CLASSPATH=C:\pulse-config"</codeblock>or
						in
						Unix/Linux:<codeblock>CATALINA_OPTS=-Dspring.profiles.active=pulse.authentication.custom
export CATALINA_OPTS
CLASSPATH=$CLASSPATH:/opt/pulse-config</codeblock></li>
					<li>Create a file named <codeph>pulse-authentication-custom.xml</codeph>
						with contents similar to the following and place it under the directory you
						created in step 1. For
						example:<codeblock>&lt;beans:beans xmlns="http://www.springframework.org/schema/security"
   	xmlns:beans="http://www.springframework.org/schema/beans"
   	xmlns:context="http://www.springframework.org/schema/context"
   	xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
   	xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.springframework.org/schema/beans
   	http://www.springframework.org/schema/beans/spring-beans-3.2.xsd
               http://www.springframework.org/schema/security
               http://www.springframework.org/schema/security/spring-security-3.1.xsd
               http://www.springframework.org/schema/context
   	http://www.springframework.org/schema/context/spring-context-3.2.xsd">
   	
        &lt;ldap-server url="ldap://ldap.gemstone.com:389/dc=gemstone,dc=com" />

        &lt;authentication-manager>
           &lt;ldap-authentication-provider user-dn-pattern="uid={0},ou=ldapTesting"  
            group-search-base="cn=PULSEUSER,ou=Groups" group-search-filter="memberUid={1}">
           &lt;/ldap-authentication-provider>
       &lt;/authentication-manager>
 
&lt;/beans:beans></codeblock>LDAP
						authentication in Pulse is hardcoded to use the PULSEUSER user group. Make
						sure you have have created users for this group.</li>
					<li>Deploy the application and start the server. </li>
				</ol>
			</section>
			<section>
				<title>Configuring Pulse to Use HTTPS </title>
				<p>You can configure Pulse to use HTTPS in either embedded or non-embedded mode.</p>
				<p>In non-embedded mode where you are running Pulse on a standalone Web application
					server, you must use the Web server's SSL configuration to make the HTTP
					requests secure.</p>
				<p>In embedded mode, the <keyword keyref="product_name"/> uses an embedded Jetty
					server to host the Pulse Web application. To make the embedded server use HTTPS,
					you must configure the following <keyword keyref="product_name"/> configuration
					parameters in <codeph>gemfire.properties</codeph> or
						<codeph>gfsecurity-properties</codeph>:</p>
				<ul id="ul_hl4_rqq_kq">
					<li>http-service-ssl-enabled</li>
					<li>http-service-ssl-require-authentication</li>
					<li>http-service-ssl-protocols</li>
					<li>http-service-ssl-ciphers</li>
					<li>http-service-ssl-keystore</li>
					<li>http-service-ssl-keystore-password</li>
					<li>http-service-ssl-keystore-type</li>
					<li>http-service-ssl-truststore</li>
					<li>http-service-ssl-truststore-password</li>
				</ul>
				<p dir="ltr">See <xref href="../../managing/security/ssl_overview.xml"/> for
					details on configuring these parameters.</p>
				<p dir="ltr">The above parameters apply to all HTTP services hosted on the JMX
					Manager, which includes the following:</p>
				<ul id="ul_vnp_vrq_kq">
					<li>Developer REST API service</li>
					<li>Management REST API service (for remote cluster management)</li>
					<li>Pulse monitoring tool</li>
				</ul>
				<p dir="ltr">When the above properties are configured, all HTTP services become
					SSL-enabled and you must configure your client applications accordingly. For
					SSL-enabled Pulse, you will need to configure your browsers with proper
					certificates. </p>
			</section>
		</body>
	</topic>
	<topic id="topic_F0ECE9E8179541CCA3D6C5F4FBA84404">
		<title>Using Pulse Views</title>
		<shortdesc>Pulse provides a variety of different views to help you monitor <keyword
				keyref="product_name"/> clusters, members, and regions. </shortdesc>
		<body>
			<section>
				<p>The following sections provide an overview of the main Pulse views:  </p>
				<ul id="ul_adn_z3z_dw">
					<li><xref scope="local"
							href="quickstart.xml#topic_F0ECE9E8179541CCA3D6C5F4FBA84404/section_9794B5754E474E10ABFBCD8B1DA240F8"
							type="section" format="dita"/>
					</li>
					<li><xref scope="local"
							href="quickstart.xml#topic_F0ECE9E8179541CCA3D6C5F4FBA84404/section_3629814A3DF64D31A190495782DB0DBF"
							type="section" format="dita"/>
					</li>
					<li><xref scope="local"
							href="quickstart.xml#topic_F0ECE9E8179541CCA3D6C5F4FBA84404/section_D151776BAC8B4704A71F37F8B5CE063D"
							type="section" format="dita"/>
					</li>
					<li><xref href="#topic_F0ECE9E8179541CCA3D6C5F4FBA84404/sec_pulsedatabrowser"
							format="dita"/></li>
					<li><xref href="#topic_F0ECE9E8179541CCA3D6C5F4FBA84404/section_bfk_sc3_wn"
							format="dita"/></li>
				</ul>
			</section>
			<section id="section_9794B5754E474E10ABFBCD8B1DA240F8">
				<title>Cluster View</title>
				<p>The cluster view is a high-level overview of the <keyword keyref="product_name"/>
					distributed system. It is displayed immediately after you log into Pulse.
					Information displays around the perimeter of the cluster view show statistics
					such as memory usage, JVM pauses, and throughput. You can use the cluster view
					to drill down into details for individual members and regions in the distributed
						system.<image id="image_CC7B54903DF24030850E55965CDB6EC4"
						href="../../images/pulse_cluster_view.png" placement="break" width="6.5in"
						align="left"/>
				</p>
				<p>Use these basic controls while in Cluster view:</p>
				<ol
						id="ol_C0F76CB7C8904F63BC3A2F1AF91681E3">
						<li>Click Members or Data to display information about <keyword
								keyref="product_name"/> members or data regions in the distributed
							system.</li>
						<li id="li_8A820336235F46A1AFBB02C698EA3294">Click the display icons to
							display the <keyword keyref="product_name"/> members using icon view,
							block view, or table view. Note that icon view is available only when
							displaying Members.<p>For example, the following shows <keyword
									keyref="product_name"/> Members displayed in table view:</p>
							<image href="../../images/member_view_list.png" id="image_npw_sq3_wn"
								/><ul id="ul_x4q_b3r_54">
								<li>While in block view or table view, click the name of a <keyword
										keyref="product_name"/> member to display additional
									information in the <xref
										href="quickstart.xml#topic_F0ECE9E8179541CCA3D6C5F4FBA84404/section_3629814A3DF64D31A190495782DB0DBF"
										type="section" format="dita" scope="local"
										outputclass="noPageCitation"/>.</li>
								<li>Click Topology, Server Groups, or Redundancy Zones to filter the
									view based on all members in the topology, configured server
									groups, or configured redundancy zones.</li>
							</ul><p>The following shows <keyword keyref="product_name"/> Regions
								displayed in table view:</p><image
								href="../../images/pulse-region-detail.png" id="image_glp_1jr_54"
								/><ul id="ul_z2b_m3r_54">
								<li>While in block view or table view, click the name of a <keyword
										keyref="product_name"/> region to display additional
									information in the <xref scope="local"
										href="quickstart.xml#topic_F0ECE9E8179541CCA3D6C5F4FBA84404/section_D151776BAC8B4704A71F37F8B5CE063D"
										type="section" format="dita" outputclass="noPageCitation"
									/>.</li>
							</ul></li>
						<li id="li_332A502FCF6549CD98738E26459E91F4">While in icon view, click a
							host machine icon to display the <keyword keyref="product_name"/>
							members on that machine. </li>
						<li id="li_6065E4348F054D33A245BC5932BA4142">In the Alerts pane, click the
							severity tabs to filter the message display by the level of severity.
						</li>
					</ol>
				<p>
					<b>Cluster View Screen Components</b>
				</p>
				<p>The following table describes the data pieces displayed on the Cluster View
						screen.</p>
				<simpletable frame="all" relcolwidth="1.0* 2.57*"
						id="simpletable_i5t_jst_qn">
						<sthead>
							<stentry>Screen Component</stentry>
							<stentry>Description</stentry>
						</sthead>
						<strow>
							<stentry><b>Cluster Status</b></stentry>
							<stentry>Overall status of the distributed system being monitored.
								Possible statuses include Normal, Warning, or Severe.</stentry>
						</strow>
						<strow>
							<stentry>Total Heap</stentry>
							<stentry>Total amount of memory (in GB) allocated to the Java heap
								across all members.</stentry>
						</strow>
						<strow>
							<stentry>Members</stentry>
							<stentry>Total number of members in the cluster.</stentry>
						</strow>
						<strow>
							<stentry>Servers</stentry>
							<stentry>Total number of servers in the cluster.</stentry>
						</strow>
						<strow>
							<stentry>Clients</stentry>
							<stentry>Total number of clients in the cluster.</stentry>
						</strow>
						<strow>
							<stentry>Locators</stentry>
							<stentry>Total number of locators in the cluster.</stentry>
						</strow>
						<strow>
							<stentry>Regions</stentry>
							<stentry>Total number of regions in the cluster.</stentry>
						</strow>
						<strow>
							<stentry>Functions</stentry>
							<stentry>Total number of functions registered in the cluster.</stentry>
						</strow>
						<strow>
							<stentry>Unique CQs</stentry>
							<stentry>Total number of unique CQs. Corresponds to the UNIQUE _CQ_QUERY
								statistic.</stentry>
						</strow>
						<strow>
							<stentry>Subscriptions</stentry>
							<stentry>Total number of client event subscriptions.</stentry>
						</strow>
						<strow>
							<stentry><b>Cluster Members</b></stentry>
							<stentry>Graphical, block, or table view of the members in the
								cluster.</stentry>
						</strow>
						<strow>
							<stentry>Topology</stentry>
							<stentry>Organizes cluster members by DistributedMember Id.</stentry>
						</strow>
						<strow>
							<stentry>Server Groups</stentry>
							<stentry>Organizes cluster members by server group membership. If no
								server groups are configured, all members appear under the "Default"
								server group.</stentry>
						</strow>
						<strow>
							<stentry>Redundancy Zones</stentry>
							<stentry>Organizes cluster members by redundancy zones. If no redundancy
								zones are configured, all members appear under the "Default"
								zone.</stentry>
						</strow>
						<strow>
							<stentry>Host Machine</stentry>
							<stentry>When you mouse over a machine icon in Topology View, a pop-up
								appears with the following machine statistics:<ul id="ul_onc_5rh_wn">
									<li><i>CPU Usage</i>. Percentage of CPU being used by <keyword
											keyref="product_name"/> processes on the machine.</li>
									<li><i>Memory Usage</i>. Amount of memory (in MB) being used by
											<keyword keyref="product_name"/> processes.</li>
									<li><i>Load Avg</i>. Average number of threads on the host
										machine that are in the run queue or are waiting for disk
										I/O over the last minutes. Corresponds to the Linux System
										statistic loadAverage1. If the load average is not
										available, a negative value is shown.</li>
									<li><i>Sockets</i>. Number of sockets currently open on the
										machine.</li>
								</ul></stentry>
						</strow>
						<strow>
							<stentry>Member</stentry>
							<stentry>When you mouse over a member icon in Graphical View, a pop-up
								appears with the following member statistics:<ul id="ul_tsj_mth_wn">
									<li><i>CPU Usage</i>. Percentage of CPU being used by the
											<keyword keyref="product_name"/> member process.</li>
									<li><i>Threads</i>. Number of threads running on the
										member.</li>
									<li><i>JVM Pauses</i>. Number of times the JVM used by the
										member process has paused due to garbage collection or
										excessive CPU usage.</li>
									<li><i>Regions</i>. Number of regions hosted on the member
										process.</li>
									<li><i>Clients</i>. Number of client currently connected to the
										member process.</li>
									<li><i>Gateway Sender</i>. Number of gateway senders configured
										on the member.</li>
									<li><i>Port</i>. Server port of the cache server member where
										clients can connect and perform cache operations.</li>
									<li><i>GemFire Version</i>. The version of the <keyword
											keyref="product_name"/> member.</li>
								</ul></stentry>
						</strow>
						<strow>
							<stentry>Member</stentry>
							<stentry>In List View, the following data fields are displayed for each
									member:<ul id="ul_ew1_bp3_wn">
									<li><i>ID</i>. DistributedMember Id of the member.</li>
									<li><i>Name</i>. Name of the member.</li>
									<li><i>Host</i>. Hostname or IP address where the member is
										running.</li>
									<li><i>Heap Usage</i>. Amount of JVM heap memory being used by
										the member process.</li>
									<li><i>CPU Usage</i>. Percentage of CPU being used by the
											<keyword keyref="product_name"/> member process.</li>
									<li><i>Uptime</i>. How long the member has been up and
										running.</li>
									<li><i>Clients</i>. Number of clients currently connected to the
										member. It will have a value only if the member acts as a
										CacheServer.</li>
								</ul></stentry>
						</strow>
						<strow>
							<stentry><b>Key Statistics</b></stentry>
							<stentry>Displays a few key performance measurements of the distributed
								system (over the last 15 minutes).</stentry>
						</strow>
						<strow>
							<stentry>Write/Sec</stentry>
							<stentry>Number of write operations per second that have occurred across
								the cluster. Each put/putAll operation counts as a write; for
								example, a putAll of 50 entries is counted as one write.</stentry>
						</strow>
						<strow>
							<stentry>Read/Sec</stentry>
							<stentry>Number of read operations per second that have occurred across
								the cluster.</stentry>
						</strow>
						<strow>
							<stentry>Queries/Sec</stentry>
							<stentry>Number of queries per second that have been executed across the
								cluster.</stentry>
						</strow>
						<strow>
							<stentry><b>No. of JVM Pauses</b></stentry>
							<stentry>Number of times the JVM has paused during the last five minutes
								to perform garbage collection.</stentry>
						</strow>
						<strow>
							<stentry><b>WAN Information</b></stentry>
							<stentry>If you have configured gateway senders or receivers for a
								multi-site (WAN) deployment, this box displays whether the remote
								cluster is reachable (working connectivity represented by a green
								triangle).</stentry>
						</strow>
						<strow>
							<stentry><b>Disk Throughput</b></stentry>
							<stentry>Total disk throughput for all disks in cluster.</stentry>
						</strow>
						<strow>
							<stentry><b>Alerts View</b></stentry>
							<stentry>Displays alerts for the cluster.</stentry>
						</strow>
					</simpletable>
			</section>
			<section id="section_3629814A3DF64D31A190495782DB0DBF">
				<title>Member View</title>
				<p>When you select an individual <keyword keyref="product_name"/> member in Cluster
					View, Pulse displays the regions available on that member, as well as
					member-specific information such as the configured listen ports.<image
						id="image_EDBD3D333B2741DCAA5CB94719B507B7"
						href="../../images/pulse_member_view.png" placement="break" width="6.5in"
						align="left"/>
				</p>		
				<p>Use these basic controls while in Member View:  </p>
				<ol id="ol_kqk_cjz_dw">
					<li>Click the display icons to display regions using block view or table view. </li>
					<li>Use the drop down menu to select a specific member or search for specific
						members by name. </li>
					<li>Click <b>Cluster View</b> to return to Cluster View. See <xref
							href="quickstart.xml#topic_F0ECE9E8179541CCA3D6C5F4FBA84404/section_9794B5754E474E10ABFBCD8B1DA240F8"
							type="section" format="dita" scope="local"/>. </li>
					<li>Click <b>Data Browser</b> to query region data. See <xref
							href="#topic_F0ECE9E8179541CCA3D6C5F4FBA84404/sec_pulsedatabrowser"
							format="dita"/>. </li>
				</ol>
				<p>
					<b>Member View Screen Components</b>
				</p>
				<p>The following table describes the data elements displayed on the Member View
						screen.</p>
				<simpletable frame="all" relcolwidth="1.0* 2.57*"
						id="simpletable_rp4_vj3_wn">
						<sthead>
							<stentry>Screen Component</stentry>
							<stentry>Description</stentry>
						</sthead>
						<strow>
							<stentry><b>Member Status</b></stentry>
							<stentry>Overall status of the member being monitored. Possible statuses
								include Normal, Warning, or Severe. </stentry>
						</strow>
						<strow>
							<stentry>Regions</stentry>
							<stentry>Total number of regions hosted on the member.</stentry>
						</strow>
						<strow>
							<stentry>Threads</stentry>
							<stentry>Total number of threads being executed on the member.</stentry>
						</strow>
						<strow>
							<stentry>Sockets</stentry>
							<stentry>Total number of sockets currently open on the member.</stentry>
						</strow>
						<strow>
							<stentry>Load Avg.</stentry>
							<stentry>Average number of threads on the member that are in the run
								queue or are waiting for disk I/O over the last minute. Corresponds
								to the Linux System statistic loadAverage1. If the load average is
								not available, a negative value is shown.</stentry>
						</strow>
						<strow>
							<stentry>Clients</stentry>
							<stentry>Current number of client connections to the member.</stentry>
						</strow>
						<strow>
							<stentry><b>Member Regions</b></stentry>
							<stentry>Block or table view of the regions hosted on the member.
							</stentry>
						</strow>
						<strow>
							<stentry>Regions</stentry>
							<stentry>When you mouse over a region in block view, a pop-up appears
								with the following data fields:<ul id="ul_xnn_3dj_wn">
									<li><i>Name</i>. Region name.</li>
									<li><i>Type</i>. For example, REPLICATE, PARTITION.</li>
									<li><i>EntryCount</i>. Number of entries in the region.</li>
									<li><i>EntrySize</i>. The aggregate entry size (in bytes) of all
										entries. For replicated regions this field will only provide
										a value if the eviction algorithm has been set to
										EvictionAlgorithm#LRU_ MEMORY. All partition regions will
										have this value. However, the value includes redundant
										entries and will also count the size of all the secondary
										entries on the node.</li>
								</ul></stentry>
						</strow>
						<strow>
							<stentry>Regions</stentry>
							<stentry>In table view, the following fields are listed for each
									region:<ul id="ul_kcg_b2j_wn">
									<li><i>Name</i>. Region name.</li>
									<li><i>Type</i>. For example, REPLICATE, PARTITION.</li>
									<li><i>EntryCount</i>. Number of entries in the region.</li>
									<li><i>EntrySize</i>. The aggregate entry size (in bytes) of all
										entries. For replicated regions this field will only provide
										a value if the eviction algorithm has been set to
										EvictionAlgorithm#LRU_ MEMORY. All partition regions will
										have this value. However, the value includes redundant
										entries and will also count the size of all the secondary
										entries on the node.</li>
									<li><i>Scope</i>. Scope configured for the region.</li>
									<li><i>Disk Store Name</i>. Name of disk stores (if any)
										associated with the region.</li>
									<li><i>Disk Synchronous</i>. True if writes to disk are set to
										synchronous and false if not. This field reflects the
										configured disk-synchronous region attribute.</li>
									<li><i>Gateway Enabled</i>. Whether gateway sender and receiver
										configurations have been defined on members hosting this
										region. </li>
								</ul></stentry>
						</strow>
						<strow>
							<stentry><b>Member Clients</b></stentry>
							<stentry>In table view, the following fields are listed for each
									client:<ul id="ul_vrz_pgj_wn">
									<li><i>Id</i>. DistributedMember ID of the client process.</li>
									<li><i>Name</i>. Name of the client process.</li>
									<li><i>Host</i>. Hostname or IP address of the client
										process.</li>
									<li><i>Connected</i>. Whether the client process is currently
										connected to the member. </li>
									<li><i>Queue Size</i>. The size of the queue used by server to
										send events in case of a subscription enabled client or a
										client that has continuous queries running on the server. </li>
									<li><i>CPU Usage</i>. Percentage of CPU being used by the client
										process. </li>
									<li><i>Uptime</i>. Amount of time the client process has been
										running. </li>
									<li><i>Threads</i>. Threads being used by the member
										clients</li>
									<li><i>Gets</i>. Total number of successful get requests
										completed.</li>
									<li><i>Puts</i>. Total number of successful put requests
										completed.</li>
								</ul></stentry>
						</strow>
						<strow>
							<stentry><b>Key Statistics</b></stentry>
							<stentry>Displays a few key performance measurements for the member
								(over the last 15 minutes).</stentry>
						</strow>
						<strow>
							<stentry>% CPU Usage</stentry>
							<stentry>Percentage of CPU used by the member.</stentry>
						</strow>
						<strow>
							<stentry>Read/Sec</stentry>
							<stentry>Number of read operations per second that have occurred on the
								member.</stentry>
						</strow>
						<strow>
							<stentry>Write/Sec</stentry>
							<stentry>Number of write operations per second that have occurred on the
								member. Each put/putAll operation counts as a write; for example, a
								putAll of 50 entries is counted as one write.</stentry>
						</strow>
						<strow>
							<stentry><b>Memory Usage</b></stentry>
							<stentry>Total memory used on the member in MB.</stentry>
						</strow>
						<strow>
							<stentry><b>No. of JVM Pauses</b></stentry>
							<stentry>Number of times the JVM has paused during the last five minutes
								due to garbage collection or excessive CPU usage.</stentry>
						</strow>
						<strow>
							<stentry><b>WAN Information</b></stentry>
							<stentry>Displays cluster information. This dialog box only appears if
								you have configured WAN functionality (gateway senders and gateway
								receivers).</stentry>
						</strow>
						<strow>
							<stentry><b>Disk Throughput</b></stentry>
							<stentry>Rate of disk writes on the member.</stentry>
						</strow>
					</simpletable>
			</section>
			<section id="section_D151776BAC8B4704A71F37F8B5CE063D">
				<title>Region View</title>
				<p>The Pulse Region View provides a comprehensive overview of all regions in the
						<keyword keyref="product_name"/> distributed system:<image
						id="image_A533852E38654E79BE5628E938E170EB"
						href="../../images/pulse_data_view.png" placement="break" width="6.5in"
						align="left"/>
				</p>	
				<p>Use these basic controls while in Region View:</p>
					<ol
						id="ol_1462167D70BA40C09F15659AE29EFA73">
						<li id="li_4E4F2E748A8644728C41E242686CA255">Click the display icons to
							display all members that host the region using block view or table view.
								<p>(Click the name of a member to change to that member's <xref
									href="quickstart.xml#topic_F0ECE9E8179541CCA3D6C5F4FBA84404/section_3629814A3DF64D31A190495782DB0DBF"
									type="section" format="dita" scope="local"
									outputclass="noPageCitation"/>.)</p></li>
						<li id="li_F0503DD1B1F54F56B34BF1B84234612E">Search for specific members
							that host the current region.</li>
						<li>Hover over a member name to display information such as the region entry
							count, entry size, and throughput on that member.</li>
						<li id="li_EA895A396C614935A21D6ACA8DF5C864">Click <xref
								href="quickstart.xml#topic_F0ECE9E8179541CCA3D6C5F4FBA84404/section_9794B5754E474E10ABFBCD8B1DA240F8"
								type="section" format="dita" scope="local"
								outputclass="noPageCitation"/> or <xref
								href="#topic_F0ECE9E8179541CCA3D6C5F4FBA84404/sec_pulsedatabrowser"
								format="dita" outputclass="noPageCitation"/> to go to those
							screens.</li>
					</ol>
				<p>
					<b>Region View Screen Components</b>
				</p>
				<p>The following table describes the data elements displayed on the Region View
						screen.</p>
				<simpletable frame="all" relcolwidth="1.0* 2.57*"
						id="simpletable_bqw_p3j_wn">
						<sthead>
							<stentry>Screen Component</stentry>
							<stentry>Description</stentry>
						</sthead>
						<strow>
							<stentry><b>Region Members</b></stentry>
							<stentry>Lists information about <keyword keyref="product_name"/>
								members that host the region, either in block view or table view.
							</stentry>
						</strow>
						<strow>
							<stentry>Region Member (Detail View)</stentry>
							<stentry>When you hover over a region member in block view, a pop-up
								appears with the following data fields:<ul id="ul_njl_423_yn">
									<li><i>Member Name</i>. The name of the <keyword
											keyref="product_name"/> member hosting the region.</li>
									<li><i>EntryCount</i>. Number of entries for the region on that
										member.</li>
									<li><i>EntrySize</i>. The aggregate entry size (in bytes) of all
										entries on that member. For replicated regions this field
										will only provide a value if the eviction algorithm has been
										set to EvictionAlgorithm#LRU_ MEMORY. All partition regions
										will have this value. However, the value includes redundant
										entries and will also count the size of all the secondary
										entries on the node. </li>
									<li><i>Accessor</i>. Indicates whether the member is an accessor
										member.</li>
									<li><i>Reads/Writes</i>. Summary of reads and writes served from
										memory and from disk stores over the last 15 minutes.</li>
								</ul></stentry>
						</strow>
						<strow>
							<stentry>Region Member (Table View)</stentry>
							<stentry>In table view, the following fields are listed for each region
									member:<ul id="ul_pnj_p23_yn">
									<li><i>ID</i>. The unique member ID.</li>
									<li><i>Name</i>. Region name.</li>
									<li><i>Host</i>. Member hostname.</li>
									<li><i>Heap Usage</i>. The total amount of heap used on the
										member in MB.</li>
									<li><i>CPU Usage</i>. CPU usage as a percent of available
										CPU.</li>
									<li><i>Uptime</i>. The amount of time elapsed since the member
										started.</li>
									<li><i>Accessor</i>. Indicates whether the member is an accessor
										member.</li>
								</ul></stentry>
						</strow>
						<strow>
							<stentry><b>Region Detail</b></stentry>
							<stentry>When you have selected a region, the right hand pane displays
								the following information about the region:<ul id="ul_dq4_sch_yn">
									<li><i>Name</i>. Name of the region.</li>
									<li><i>Region Path</i>. Path for the region.</li>
									<li><i>Type</i>. For example, REPLICATE, PARTITION</li>
									<li><i>Members</i>. Number of members that are hosting the
										region.</li>
									<li><i>Empty Nodes</i>. Nodes where the region DataPolicy is
										defined as EMPTY or where LocalMaxMemory is set to 0.</li>
									<li><i>Entry Count</i>. Total number of entries in the
										region.</li>
									<li><i>Disk Usage</i>. Persistent data usage.</li>
									<li><i>Persistence</i>. Indicates whether the region's data is
										persisted to disk.</li>
									<li><i>Memory Usage</i>. The amount of memory used and total
										available memory (also shown as a percentage).</li>
									<li><i>Reads/Writes</i>. Summary of reads and writes served from
										memory and from disk stores over the last 15 minutes.</li>
								</ul></stentry>
						</strow>
					</simpletable>
			</section>
			<section id="sec_pulsedatabrowser">
				<title>Data Browser</title>
				<p>The Pulse Data Browser enables you to query region data. Note that there are two key
					attributes available on DistributedSystemMXBean (see <xref
						href="../../managing/management/list_of_mbeans.xml#topic_4BCF867697C3456D96066BAD7F39FC8B"
					/>) that you can use to configure limits for the result sets displayed in Data
					Browser:</p>
				<ul id="ul_cyn_2jz_dw">
					<li><codeph>QueryResultSetLimit</codeph> limits the number of rows that Data
						Browser queries return. 1000 rows are displayed by default.</li>
					<li><codeph>QueryCollectionsDepth</codeph> limits the number of elements of a
						collection that Data Browser queries return. This attribute applies to query
						results contain collections such as Map, List, and so forth. The default
						value is 100 elements.</li>
				</ul>
				<p>See the <codeph>com.gemstone.gemfire.management.DistributedSystemMXBean</codeph>
					JavaDocs for information on available MBean methods and attributes. </p>
				<p>The following shows an example Data Browser view:<image
						href="../../images/pulse-data-browser.png" placement="break" width="6.5in"
						align="left" id="image_hhp_dz2_44"/>
				</p>
				<p>Use these basic controls while in Data Browser view:  </p>
				<ol id="ol_brp_fjz_dw">
					<li>Search for the name of a specific region. </li>
					<li>Select one or more regions to display the <keyword keyref="product_name"/>
						members that host those regions. The hosting <keyword keyref="product_name"
						/> members appear in the Region Members section. </li>
					<li>Select one or more members from the Region Members section to restrict query
						results to those members. </li>
					<li>Type in the text of a query to execute. See <xref
							href="../../developing/querying_basics/chapter_overview.xml"/>.</li>
					<li>Display a list of previously-executed queries. Double-click on a query from
						the history list to copy it to the Query Editor, or delete the query from
						your history.</li>
					<li>Execute your query or clear the contents of the Query Editor.</li>
					<li>View the current query results.</li>
					<li>Export the query results to a text file.</li>
					<li>Return to <xref
							href="quickstart.xml#topic_F0ECE9E8179541CCA3D6C5F4FBA84404/section_9794B5754E474E10ABFBCD8B1DA240F8"
							type="section" format="dita" scope="local" outputclass="noPageCitation"
						/>. </li>
				</ol>
			</section>
			<section id="section_bfk_sc3_wn">
				<title>Alerts Widget</title>
				<p>The Alerts Widget appears in the right portion of the screen and displays a list
					of alerts.</p>
				<p> The alerts displayed for the cluster appear based on the alertLevel field set in
					the DistributedSystemMXBean. By default, log messages with the level of SEVERE
					are shown as alerts. You can modify the level by using the
						<codeph>DistributedMXBean.changeAlertLevel</codeph> method. See <xref
						href="../../managing/management/notification_federation_and_alerts.xml#topic_212EE5A2ABAB4E8E8EF71807C9ECEF1A/section_7463D13112D54406953416356835E290"
					/> ofr more information.</p>
				<p>
					<image href="../../images/pulse_alerts_widget.png" id="image_jrc_smt_qn"/>
				</p>
				<p>Use these basic controls in the Alerts Widget:</p>
				<ol id="ol_jkr_3jz_dw">
					<li>Select an alert level to view only alerts with a specific severity.</li>
					<li>Enter text in the search box to filter the list of alerts.</li>
					<li>Select an alert and click Clear to remove it from the alert list.</li>
					<li>Click <b>Clear All</b> to remove all alerts from the widget.</li>
					<li>Double-click an alert to open a pop-up window that displays the full text of
						the alert message.</li>
					<li>Click the check mark in an alert pop-up window to acknowledge the alert.
						Acknowledged alerts display a check mark in the list of alerts.</li>
					<li>Triple-click the alert in the pop-up or in the alert list to select the
						message text. You can then copy and paste the text into another
						application.</li>
					<li>Click the <b>X</b> to close the pop-up alert window.</li>
				</ol>
			</section>
		</body>
	</topic>
</dita>
