<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE concept PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN" "http://docs.oasis-open.org/dita/v1.1/OS/dtd/concept.dtd">
<concept id="operators">
	<title>Operators</title>
	<conbody>
		<p><keyword keyref="product_name"/> supports comparison, logical, unary, map, index, dot, and right arrow operators. </p>
		<section id="section_A3FB372F85D840D7A49CB95BD7FCA7C6">
			<title>Comparison Operators</title>
			<p>Comparison operators compare two values and return the results, either TRUE or FALSE. </p>
			<p>The following are supported comparison operators: <table
					id="table_5B768FC5ABE648FAA62DEAEE6EE7D1CC">
					<tgroup cols="2">
						<colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="*"/>
						<colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="*"/>
						<tbody>
							<row>
								<entry>= equal to </entry>
								<entry>&lt; less than </entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>&lt;&gt; not equal to </entry>
								<entry>&lt;= less than or equal to </entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>!= not equal to </entry>
								<entry>&gt; greater than </entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry/>
								<entry>&gt;= greater than or equal to </entry>
							</row>
						</tbody>
					</tgroup>
				</table>
			</p>
			<p>The equal and not equal operators have lower precedence than the other comparison
				operators. They can be used with null. To perform equality or inequality comparisons
				with UNDEFINED, use the IS_DEFINED and IS_UNDEFINED preset query functions instead
				of these comparison operators. </p>
		</section>
		<section id="section_6A85A9DDA47E47009FDE1CC38D7BA66C">
			<title>Logical Operators</title>
			<p>The logical operators AND and OR allow you to create more complex expressions by
				combining expressions to produce a boolean result. When you combine two conditional
				expressions using the AND operator, both conditions must evaluate to true for the
				entire expression to be true. When you combine two conditional expressions using the
				OR operator, the expression evaluates to true if either one or both of the
				conditions are true. You can create complex expressions by combining multiple simple
				conditional expressions with AND and OR operators. When expressions use AND and OR
				operators, AND has higher precedence than OR. </p>
		</section>
		<section id="section_A970AE75B0D24E0B9E1B61BE2D9842D8">
			<title>Unary Operators </title>
			<p>Unary operators operate on a single value or expression, and have lower precedence
				than comparison operators in expressions. <keyword keyref="product_name"/> supports the unary operator NOT.
				NOT is the negation operator, which changes the value of the operand to its
				opposite. So if an expression evaluates to TRUE, NOT changes it to FALSE. The
				operand must be a boolean. </p>
		</section>
		<section id="section_E78FB4FB3703471C8186A0E26D25F01F">
			<title>Map and Index Operators </title>
			<p>Map and index operators access elements in key/value collections (such as maps and
				regions) and ordered collections (such as arrays, lists, and
				<codeph>String</codeph>s). The operator is represented by a set of square brackets
				"[ ]" immediately following the name of the collection. The mapping or indexing
				specification is provided inside these brackets. </p>
			<p>Array, list, and <codeph>String</codeph> elements are accessed using an index value.
				Indexing starts from zero for the first element, 1 for the second element and so on.
				If <codeph>myList</codeph> is an array, list, or String and <codeph>index</codeph>
				is an expression that evaluates to a non-negative integer, then
					<codeph>myList[index]</codeph> represents the (<codeph>index</codeph>+1)th
				element of <codeph>myList</codeph>. The elements of a <codeph>String</codeph> are
				the list of characters that make up the string. </p>
			<p>Map and region values are accessed by key using the same syntax. The key can be any
					<codeph>Object</codeph>. For a <codeph>Region</codeph>, the map operator
				performs a non-distributed <codeph>get</codeph> in the local cache only - with no
				use of <codeph>netSearch</codeph>. So <codeph>myRegion[keyExpression]</codeph> is
				the equivalent of <codeph>myRegion.getEntry(keyExpression).getValue</codeph>. </p>
		</section>
		<section id="section_6C0BB787B2324B85AA02AA19D4822A83">
			<title>Dot, Right Arrow, and Forward Slash Operators </title>
			<p>The dot operator '.' separates attribute names in a path expression, and specifies
				the navigation through object attributes. An alternate equivalent to the dot is the
				right arrow, "<codeph>-&gt;</codeph>". The forward slash is used to separate region
				names when navigating into subregions. </p>
		</section>
	</conbody>
</concept>
