<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE concept PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN" "http://docs.oasis-open.org/dita/v1.1/OS/dtd/concept.dtd">
<concept id="region_types">
	<title>Region Types</title>
	<shortdesc id="shortdesc_559DCD41E31446DB9DF5ECFD15AC867B">Region types define region behavior
		within a single distributed system. You have various options for region data storage and
		distribution. </shortdesc>
	<conbody>
		<section id="section_E3435ED1D0D142538B99FA69A9E449EF">
			<p>Within a <keyword keyref="product_name"/> distributed system, you can define
				distributed regions and non-distributed regions, and you can define regions whose
				data is spread across the distributed system, and regions whose data is entirely
				contained in a single member. </p>
			<p>Your choice of region type is governed in part by the type of application you are
				running. In particular, you need to use specific region types for your servers and
				clients for effective communication between the two tiers: <ul
					id="ul_328ea15b-8d11-43f9-87ba-e1753f26c239">
					<li id="li_5248B58F175548E1A5B025EE0BEAD1A8">Server regions are created inside a
							<codeph>Cache</codeph> by servers and are accessed by clients that
						connect to the servers from outside the server's distributed system. Server
						regions must have region type partitioned or replicated. Server region
						configuration uses the <codeph>RegionShortcut</codeph> enum settings.</li>
					<li id="li_CE0BDAC63C4443A5B49D61B18EADB851">Client regions are created inside a
							<codeph>ClientCache</codeph> by clients and are configured to distribute
						data and events between the client and the server tier. Client regions must
						have region type local. Client region configuration uses the
							<codeph>ClientRegionShortcut</codeph> enum settings. </li>
					<li id="li_D663937A9D0042EE8F10AC182331AAF0">Peer regions are created inside a
							<codeph>Cache</codeph>. Peer regions may be server regions, or they may
						be regions that are not accessed by clients. Peer regions can have any
						region type. Peer region configuration uses the
							<codeph>RegionShortcut</codeph> enum settings. </li>
				</ul><note>
					<p>When you configure a server or peer region using <codeph>gfsh</codeph> or
						with the <filepath>cache.xml</filepath> file, you can use <i>region
							shortcuts</i> to define the basic configuration of your region. A region
						shortcut provides a set of default configuration attributes that are
						designed for various types of caching architectures. You can then add
						additional configuration attributes as needed to customize your application.
						For more information and a complete reference of these region shortcuts, see
							<xref
							href="../../reference/topics/region_shortcuts_reference.xml#reference_lt4_54c_lk"
						/>.</p>
				</note>
			</p>
		</section>
		<section id="section_A3449B07598C47A881D9219574DE46C5">
			<p>These are the primary configuration choices for each data region. </p>
			<table id="table_4938AC356E914601BDCCE593D406923A">
				<tgroup cols="3">
					<colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="1.00*"/>
					<colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="1.46*"/>
					<colspec colname="3" colnum="3" colwidth="1.25*"/>
					<colspec colname="4" colnum="3" colwidth="*"/>
					<thead>
						<row>
							<entry>Region Type </entry>
							<entry>Description </entry>
							<entry>Best suited for... </entry>
						</row>
					</thead>
					<tbody>
						<row>
							<entry>Partitioned </entry>
							<entry>System-wide setting for the data set. Data is divided into
								buckets across the members that define the region. For high
								availability, configure redundant copies so each bucket is stored in
								multiple members with one member holding the primary. </entry>
							<entry>Server regions and peer regions <ul
									id="ul_CA1A76A4C5F8480987183210514D4AB0">
									<li id="li_7CD5FE9E556E4D529A17C50EFD0F12F1">Very large data
										sets </li>
									<li id="li_78B8667EC08A4D6D9546B22BB443C609">High availability </li>
									<li id="li_4C25E8C0EF7F4748B93828F91605FE23">Write performance </li>
									<li id="li_B3616616134F4148A6760AA8D681F5B2">Partitioned event
										listeners and data loaders </li>
								</ul>
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>Replicated (distributed) </entry>
							<entry>Holds all data from the distributed region. The data from the
								distributed region is copied into the member replica region. Can be
								mixed with non-replication, with some members holding replicas and
								some holding non-replicas. </entry>
							<entry>Server regions and peer regions <ul
									id="ul_16F3AD50156547A89C2791BA5A6EEF3D">
									<li id="li_641F926151DC4C269A07A0834A4EAC58">Read heavy, small
										datasets </li>
									<li id="li_A61FB31ED24A4946B86AB455F179CB4F">Asynchronous
										distribution </li>
									<li id="li_E23F6D58B64A440798C9D0D34841CD23">Query performance
									</li>
								</ul>
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>Distributed non-replicated </entry>
							<entry>Data is spread across the members that define the region. Each
								member holds only the data it has expressed interest in. Can be
								mixed with replication, with some members holding replicas and some
								holding non-replicas. </entry>
							<entry>Peer regions, but not server regions and not client regions <ul
									id="ul_3E314E6D3E984F3885BC7DD746A6E2BC">
									<li id="li_51E6F1279FA742678EF8A4F282DB8884">Asynchronous
										distribution </li>
									<li id="li_95E11B06AB804601BDFC7E8ED4D1C279">Query performance
									</li>
								</ul>
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>Non-distributed (local) </entry>
							<entry>The region is visible only to the defining member. </entry>
							<entry>Client regions and peer regions <ul
									id="ul_3B03514F163F490381FDBF3480D4BF3F">
									<li id="li_B960CF57C546492EB947241DE6450063">Data that is not
										shared between applications </li>
								</ul>
							</entry>
						</row>
					</tbody>
				</tgroup>
			</table>
		</section>
		<section id="section_C92C7DBD8EF44F1789FCB36281D3F8BF">
			<title>Partitioned Regions</title>
			<p>Partitioning is a good choice for very large server regions. Partitioned regions are
				ideal for data sets in the hundreds of gigabytes and beyond. </p>
			<note>Partitioned regions generally require more JDBC connections than other region
				types because each member that hosts data must have a connection. </note>
			<p>Partitioned regions group your data into buckets, each of which is stored on a subset
				of all of the system members. Data location in the buckets does not affect the
				logical view - all members see the same logical data set. </p>
			<p>Use partitioning for: <ul id="ul_EEF600FD984346B285B8E82F5E47BD29">
					<li id="li_FF7B924C7DB1458695E824AF02B92997"><b>Large data sets</b>. Store data
						sets that are too large to fit into a single member, and all members will
						see the same logical data set. Partitioned regions divide the data into
						units of storage called buckets that are split across the members hosting
						the partitioned region data, so no member needs to host all of the region’s
						data. <keyword keyref="product_name"/> provides dynamic redundancy recovery
						and rebalancing of partitioned regions, making them the choice for
						large-scale data containers. More members in the system can accommodate more
						uniform balancing of the data across all host members, allowing system
						throughput (both gets and puts) to scale as new members are added. </li>
					<li id="li_6528B3B018844D5881A1C536267A9E9B"><b>High availability</b>.
						Partitioned regions allow you configure the number of copies of your data
						that <keyword keyref="product_name"/> should make. If a member fails, your
						data will be available without interruption from the remaining members.
						Partitioned regions can also be persisted to disk for additional high
						availability. </li>
					<li id="li_394A5D02F8094790A3BE53EAA13CF04C"><b>Scalability</b>. Partitioned
						regions can scale to large amounts of data because the data divided between
						the members available to host the region. Increase your data capacity
						dynamically by simply adding new members. Partitioned regions also allow you
						to scale your processing capacity. Because your entries are spread out
						across the members hosting the region, reads and writes to those entries are
						also spread out across those members. </li>
					<li id="li_75C74CD33F2946D094E35AF0B95D9666"><b>Good write performance</b>. You
						can configure the number of copies of your data. The amount of data
						transmitted per write does not increase with the number of members. By
						contrast, with replicated regions, each write must be sent to every member
						that has the region replicated, so the amount of data transmitted per write
						increases with the number of members. </li>
				</ul>
			</p>
			<p>In partitioned regions, you can colocate keys within buckets and across multiple
				partitioned regions. You can also control which members store which data buckets.
			</p>
		</section>
		<section id="section_iwt_dnj_bm">
			<title>Replicated Regions</title>
			<note>Replication is a good choice for small to medium size server regions. </note>
			<p>Replicated regions provide the highest performance in terms of throughput and
				latency. </p>
			<p>Use replicated regions for: <ul id="ul_307615353A48423E85CBD2AFF4F05A5C">
					<li id="li_D8B8E58C75EA46F7B754F508F648D05A"><b>Small amounts of data required
							by all members of the distributed system</b>. For example, currency rate
						information and mortgage rates. </li>
					<li id="li_F7B15052C77B417F9D39889033C9F3B4"><b>Data sets that can be contained
							entirely in a single member</b>. Each replicated region holds the
						complete data set for the region </li>
					<li id="li_C72620EFE1F443F8AAFC28009A6DE29C"><b>High performance data
						access</b>. Replication guarantees local access from the heap for
						application threads, providing the lowest possible latency for data access. </li>
					<li id="li_94D285258ADD4291806DAEB3CEED1E47"><b>Asynchronous distribution</b>.
						All distributed regions, replicated and non-replicated, provide the fastest
						distribution speeds. </li>
				</ul>
			</p>
		</section>
		<section id="section_2232BEC969F74CDB91B1BB74FEF67EE1">
			<title>Distributed, Non-Replicated Regions</title>
			<p>Distributed regions provide the same performance as replicated regions, but each
				member only stores data it has expressed interest in, either by subscribing to
				events from other members or by defining the data entries in its cache. </p>
			<p>Use distributed, non-replicated regions for: <ul
					id="ul_C23E4ECB092B48049DE3A3CB50AFBB73">
					<li id="li_3A68FC2B4D044F8EBDF38F2AB9EE6C97"><b>Peer regions, but not server
							regions or client regions</b>. Server regions must be either replicated
						or partitioned. Client regions must be local. </li>
					<li id="li_E68FDFB364884391AA987EA3F6000228"><b>Data sets where individual
							members only need notification and updates for changes to a subset of
							the data</b>. In non-replicated regions, each member only receives
						update events for the data entries it has defined in the local cache. </li>
					<li id="li_782D017266ED48289BE05BAB69537AE1"><b>Asynchronous distribution</b>.
						All distributed regions, replicated and non-replicated, provide the fastest
						distribution speeds. </li>
				</ul>
			</p>
		</section>
		<section id="section_A8150BDBC74E4019B1942481877A4370">
			<title>Local Regions</title>
			<p>
				<note>When created using the <codeph>ClientRegionShortcut</codeph> settings, client
					regions are automatically defined as local, since all client distribution
					activities go to and come from the server tier. </note>The local region has no
				peer-to-peer distribution activity. </p>
			<p>Use local regions for: <ul id="ul_9F2EE05E49214FEABD83D5806C681C27">
					<li id="li_7FC21C4DD7AF4866AAA2235698158060"><b>Client regions</b>. Distribution
						is only between the client and server tier. </li>
					<li id="li_CD4AD2D0597D475CB215BDB0ADD779AC"><b>Private data sets for the
							defining member</b>. The local region is not visible to peer members.
					</li>
				</ul>
			</p>
		</section>
	</conbody>
</concept>
