<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE concept PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN" "concept.dtd">
<concept id="concept_B18B7754E7C7485BA6D66F2DDB7A11FB">
	<title> Storage and Distribution Options</title>
	<shortdesc><keyword keyref="product_name"/> provides several models for data storage and
		distribution including partitioned or replicated as well as distributed or non-distributed
		(local cache storage). </shortdesc>
	<conbody>
		<section id="section_787D674A64244871AE49CBB58475088E">
			<p>At its most general, data management means having current data available when and
				where your applications need it. In a properly configured <keyword
					keyref="product_name"/> installation, you store your data in your local members
				and <keyword keyref="product_name"/> automatically distributes it to the other
				members that need it according to your cache configuration settings. You may be
				storing very large data objects that require special consideration, or you may have
				a high volume of data requiring careful configuration to safeguard your
				application's performance or memory use. You may need to be able to explicitly lock
				some data during particular operations. Most data management features are available
				as configuration options, which you can specify either using gfsh's cluster
				configuration service, <codeph>cache.xml</codeph> file or the API. Once configured,
					<keyword keyref="product_name"/> manages the data automatically. For example,
				this is how you manage data distribution, disk storage, data expiration activities,
				and data partitioning. A few features are managed at run-time through the API. </p>
			<p>At the architectural level, data distribution runs between peers in a single system
				and between clients and servers. </p>
				<ul id="ul_7fcf8a80-2802-4a41-8668-42d212e8b318">
					<li id="li_1887D0A416E948E18D7467201869B6D3">
						<p>Peer-to-peer provides the core distribution and storage models, which are
							specified as attributes on the data regions. </p>
					</li>
					<li id="li_17DF686D11FD448DA69406BA31E71660">
						<p>For client/server, you choose which data regions to share between the
							client and server tiers. Then, within each region, you can fine-tune the
							data that the server automatically sends to the client by subscribing to
							subsets. </p>
					</li>
				</ul>
			<p>Data storage in any type of installation is based on the peer-to-peer configuration
				for each individual distributed system. Data and event distribution is based on a
				combination of the peer-to-peer and system-to-system configurations. </p>
			<title>Peer-to-Peer Region Storage and Distribution</title>
			<p>The storage and distribution models are configured through cache and region
				attributes. The main choices are partitioned, replicated, or just distributed. All
				server regions must be partitioned or replicated. Each region’s
					<codeph>data-policy</codeph> and <codeph>subscription-attributes</codeph>, and
				its <codeph>scope</codeph> if it is not a partitioned region, interact for finer
				control of data distribution. </p>
		</section>
		<section id="section_A364D16DFADA49D1A838A7EAF8E4251C">
			<title>Storing Data in the Local Cache</title>
			<p>To store data in your local cache, use a region <codeph>refid</codeph> with a
					<codeph>RegionShortcut</codeph> or <codeph>ClientRegionShortcut</codeph> that
				has local state. These automatically set the region <codeph>data-policy</codeph> to
				a non-empty policy. The regions without storage can send and receive event
				distributions without storing anything in your application heap. With the other
				settings, all entry operations received are stored locally. </p>
		</section>
	</conbody>
</concept>
